<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Episcopal jurisdiction asserted according to the right constitution thereof, by His Majesties laws, both ecclesiastical and temporal, occasioned by the stating and vindicating of the Bishop of Waterford's case, with the mayor and sheriffs of Waterford / by a diligent enquirer into the reasons and grounds thereof.</title>
            <author>Stanhope, Arthur, d. 1685?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 240 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61271</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5221</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21281</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12054614</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12054614</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53134</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61271)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53134)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 581:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Episcopal jurisdiction asserted according to the right constitution thereof, by His Majesties laws, both ecclesiastical and temporal, occasioned by the stating and vindicating of the Bishop of Waterford's case, with the mayor and sheriffs of Waterford / by a diligent enquirer into the reasons and grounds thereof.</title>
                  <author>Stanhope, Arthur, d. 1685?</author>
                  <author>Gore, Hugh, 1612 or 13-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 134 [i.e. 132] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Benjamin Tooke ..., and are to be sold by Mary Crooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Stanhope by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 134 [i.e. 132].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Emmanuel College Library, Cambridge, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gore, Hugh, 1612 or 13-1691.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:53134:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur, </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Guli. Fitz. Gerald</hi> Rev. in Chriſto Patri Archiepiſc. <hi>Dublin.</hi> toti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſque <hi>Hiberniae</hi> Domino, D. Cancellario a Sac. Domeſt.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Decemb. 27. 1670.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53134:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>EPISCOPAL JURISDICTION <hi>Aſſerted,</hi> According to the right Conſtitution thereof, BY His Majeſties <hi>Laws, both Eccleſiaſtical and Temporal.</hi> OCCASIONED By the Stating and Vindicating of the BISHOP of <hi>WATERFORD</hi>'s CASE, With the Mayor and Sheriffs of <hi>Waterford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Diligent Enquirer into the Reaſons and Grounds thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ne quid falſum audeant, Ne quid verum non audeant.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl> My Lord <hi>Coke</hi>'s Rule given to all ſuch as take upon them to write: <hi>Iurisdiction of Courts,</hi> cap. 9.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>Benjamin Tooke,</hi> Printer to the King's moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſty; And are to be Sold by <hi>Mary Crooke,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:53134:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53134:2"/>
            <head>THE BISHOP of WATERFORD'S CASE WITH THE MAYOR and SHERIFFS OF WATERFORD, <hi>Stated and Vindicated,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He late Proceedings at <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terford,</hi> betwixt the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and the <hi>Mayor</hi> and <hi>Sheriffs</hi> of that City, making a great Noiſe abroad, and furniſhing Diſcourſe for moſt Companies that met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; I made it a while my buſineſs, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into the true ſtate thereof; the better to diſcover, if I could, what proportion the Matter it ſelf held with the Talk made, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53134:3"/>Cenſures paſſed by Men thereon: While I was thus employed, I could not chooſe but obſerve, That there was ſtill retained too much of the old Malignity of ſpirit; and how readily ſome perſons catched at any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, to inveigh againſt <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and traduce both their <hi>Order,</hi> and <hi>Juriſdiction.</hi> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, That they who were moſt loud an clamorous againſt the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Waterford</hi> proceedings in this <hi>Caſe,</hi> were indeed ſuch a leaſt underſtood the true Grounds and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons thereof; inſomuch, as when they have vented their Clamors with greateſt eagerneſs, they have been known for all that, to ask, <hi>What it was that the Biſhop did?</hi> Whereas they who had attained ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent knowledge therein, were more mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and reſerved.</p>
            <p>Hereupon I judged, That this Enquiry would be feaſonable, becauſe I might thereby be able to give my ſelf ſatisfaction about it, and, peradventure, be inſtrumental to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceiving the unwary and eaſily ſeduced; or, convincing the wilfully erring perſons there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: This, I think, will be no difficult Task to perform; if Men will but once be brought to think that they may miſtake, or that they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53134:3"/>may be too much byaſſed with prejudices, and, thereupon, reſolve to act like what they would be thought to be, ingenuous and ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Men. In proſecuting of this Deſign, I propoſe two things as the principal Subjects of this Enquiry; The one is, <hi>concerning the matter of Fact;</hi> The other is, <hi>concerning the matter of Right</hi> in theſe proceedings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concerning the matter of Fact,</hi> my entrance into that ſhall be, by premiſing a paſſage or two, relating to the preceding, and to this preſent <hi>Biſhop;</hi> which may inform us what manner of welcome both were ſaluted withall, at their firſt coming to <hi>Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When at His MAJESTIES Happy Reſtauration, the late <hi>Biſhop</hi> firſt came thither, the graver and better Sort gave him a chearful Entertainment; but, a perverſe Generation, very prevalent in that City, treated him at a far different rate; I think, no Uſages could be more barbarous and rude, than he experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced there: Frequent Affronts were offered him, <hi>Libels</hi> ſpread abroad of him, <hi>Papers of Queries</hi> ſent and tendred to him; ſuch, as were full of ridiculous Non-ſenſe, yet full of Petulancy and Malice.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:53134:4"/>
            <p>The induſtry and travel of that <hi>Pious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> to reduce to, and ſettle that People in their Duty and Obedience to Gods Church, and Gods Anointed; His Aſſiduity in Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching; His Exemplarineſs of Living, are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently known to all: The baſe ſlighting of which, will (I fear) lie heavy one day on the Conſciences of ſome Men.</p>
            <p>When this <hi>Prelate</hi> was one time about to diſcharge two ſolemn Offices, the one of <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,</hi> he found his <hi>Pulpit, fouly defiled with Excrements</hi> (ſo as muſt not be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) and the other Office of <hi>Baptiſing,</hi> the <hi>Font was defiled in the like beaſtly and unſeemly manner.</hi> Theſe, and many other unkind and ungrateful Uſages, contributed not a little to the ſhortning of his life; and (God forgive me if I judge uncharitably) the ſame, I think, have been continued, to work the like effect on his Succeſſor; and, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure, they would be more encreaſed, if they could but accompliſh the Eradication of the whole Order, together with the extincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of both their perſons.</p>
            <p>The worthy <hi>Prelate,</hi> now in the See of <hi>Waterford,</hi> at his Entrance thereinto, having firſt inſpected the ſtate of his Dioceſs at large,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53134:4"/>and ſet in order the Affairs thereof. His next care employed him about the Cathedral Church of <hi>Waterford,</hi> where too he met with the like barbarous welcome that his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor had done before; for ſhortly after his firſt coming to <hi>Waterford,</hi> going to Solemn Prayers at the Cathedral, attended with many of his Clergy, he found the way that he muſt walk, from the Body of the Church into the Choire towards the Biſhops Throne, <hi>moſt beaſtly defiled with Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments again:</hi> But not diſcouraged here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, the Repairing, Beautifying, and Adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that Church, is that which he is ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly intent upon; ſo as that in a ſhort time, he brought the Choire thereof (at no little Expence and Charge of his own) to that comely and graceful Uniformity that it is now to be ſeen in; ſuch, as may at once delight and awe the Beholders, ſo well attemper'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether are ſome innocent and pleaſing Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, with the more ſolemn and grave Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture added thereto; for which, he received ſhortly after, the Thanks of a <hi>ſcurrilous Libel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Body of that Cathedral, together with ſome Out-Chappels adjoining thereto, the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53134:5"/>Tower and Bells do by Ancient <hi>Charter-party</hi> belong to the Corporation of <hi>Waterford,</hi> to keep in good and decent Repair: In lieu of which, the ſaid Corporation of <hi>Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> have the diſpoſing of all Burying places therein, and receive to their own uſe ſuch Emoluments and Profits as do accrue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by: And, as I have been Credibly informed from a knowing perſon, that has inſpected the Ancient Records of that City, the Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion became Enfeoffed in certain Lands, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed for theſe purpoſes, namely, <hi>To main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Publick School-maſter;</hi> And, <hi>To uphold in good and conſtant Repair, the Body of the Cathedral, Out-Chappels, Tower and Bells,</hi> as is before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Biſhop</hi> being Religiouſly zealous in proſecuting this good Work which he had begun, intimates to the <hi>Mayor,</hi> and reſt of the Corporation of <hi>Waterford,</hi> the Duty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to them in behalf of the Church; he is very inſtant, and preſſing with them, that what in Duty they were obliged to do, they would with Alacrity and Chearfulneſs enter upon: But, Excitements to Acts of Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſuch pious Works as this, find but cold
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53134:5"/>Entertainment in theſe dayes of languiſhing Piety and Charity: And ſo truly they did with theſe Men, They alledging their preſent Poverty, and exhauſted Revenue, whereby they were rendred unable to undertake ſo chargeable a work: Nay, there wanted not ſome, who gave it out openly enough, That the proceeding in ſuch a Deſign, was, if not unneceſſary, yet then unſeaſonable: And that if it muſt be done, <hi>the Clergy,</hi> who had got an ample Revenue in the City, were the fitteſt to effect the ſame.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding theſe little Shiftings and Tergiverſations uſed by theſe Men, the <hi>Biſhop</hi> is not diſcouraged yet in his Religious endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours; but perſiſting ſtill in his purpoſe, what by entreaties and perſwaſions, his own good example, and other rational motives, he at laſt prevails with them. Hereupon, both to eaſe the Charge of the Corporation in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and to forward the Work, Voluntary Subſcriptions are gathered from many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as well Strangers, as others, Citizens of <hi>Waterford,</hi> for the new Caſting and Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Ring of Bells, the <hi>Biſhop</hi> himſelf ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing very liberally and bountifully thereto; and from his particular Friends, procuring ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53134:6"/>other conſiderable Subſcriptions, which Subſcriptions, as I have heard, came to near <hi>One hundred pounds.</hi> To this was added, By the <hi>Mayor</hi> and <hi>City-Council,</hi> a great Tax or Rate (which, together with the Subſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, might make in all <hi>Two hundred and ſeven pounds,</hi> or thereabouts) and by them Levied upon the Inhabitants of the City. I diſpute not how juſtifiable the making and Levying this Tax was, nor why that which ought to have come from the Chamber and Publick Revenue of the City, was to be ſupplied by a perſonal Tax upon the People; whether this was done to make good their former Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legation of Poverty, or whether this was done to ſave the City-ſtock, I take not upon me to determine; perhaps it was for both theſe ends, and perhaps it was for one more (like the Actings of a wiſe and politick People) namely, to reflect the <hi>Odium</hi> thereof from the querulous Inhabitants upon the Biſhop, as if by his forcible impulſe and inſtigation, they were neceſſitated to this extraordinary courſe: But while theſe things were thus car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on, one remarkable matter intervened, well worthy here to be inſerted and taken notice of.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:53134:6"/>
            <p>When the Bells in their metal were to be ſent to <hi>Briſtol</hi> for the New-caſting of them, and (as I have before touched) Subſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons had been made by many perſons both of that City, and ſuch as were ſtrangers for the very purpoſe of New-caſting, and Hanging of the Bells; yet ſuch were the ſordid and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurious Deſigns of the chief Leaders of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs in <hi>Waterford,</hi> whether to intervert the money deſigned for that, to ſome other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or to ſave their own ſlender proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerned therein, the <hi>Mayor</hi> that then was, that is, he that was <hi>Mayor</hi> in the Year <hi>One thouſand ſix hundred ſixty and ſeven:</hi> This perſon, the <hi>Mayor</hi> (I ſay) <hi>dealt under-hand</hi> with one <hi>Aram</hi> (in whoſe Ship the Bells were to be carried over) to this purpoſe; <hi>That he ſhould reſerve a certain quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of the metal, which would in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue be ſufficient to defray the Charges of Caſting the reſt; and the remainder to be made uſe of for ſuch a Ring of Bells as had been there afore time, which</hi> (was ſaid) <hi>would ſerve the turn well enough:</hi> For this we are to know, that beſides the metal of five Bells that were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the Tower of the Cathedral of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53134:7"/>
               <hi>Waterford,</hi> the Biſhop had added ſeven Bells more, that had been retrieved out of the hands of ſome private perſons, who in the late times of Confuſion and Demoliſhment, had ſecured them in their own poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>This <hi>pretty thrifty Project,</hi> the ſaid <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi> acquaints the Biſhop withall, and ſhews him the then <hi>Mayors</hi> inſtructions under his hand, and deſires the Biſhops advice and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection what to do therein: The Biſhop here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſends to the <hi>Mayor,</hi> deſires his company, ſpeaks with him, urged to him the baſeneſs and unworthineſs of the thing he had given dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for, brought the <hi>Mayor</hi> to a ſudden a baſhment and confuſion; and ſo altered quite, and prevented the Deſign of defraying the Charge of Caſting the Bells, by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding a great part of their own metal. And over and above that, ſpoiled their Plot, of their <hi>being Gainers of Two hundred pound and upward</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> by the Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions and Tax before mentioned) which in likelihood would have paſſed current, if this <hi>holy Cheat</hi> had not been diſcovered; for this is to be further obſerved, That beſides the voluntary Subſcriptions before ſpoken of, the great Tax that I ſaid was laid on the people of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53134:7"/>
               <hi>Waterford,</hi> was pretended to be Subſidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, and as a Supplement to the Subſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the Bells; ſo as the Deficiencies of theſe might be made up by the help of the other.</p>
            <p>And this very thing was then pretended, when this unworthy Deſign was in agitation, and ready to be put in execution. This <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi> is now dead; nevertheleſs, there is a competent Witneſs, a perſon of good Credit yet remaining alive, who ſaw the Paper of Inſtructions that was given by the <hi>Mayor,</hi> and was preſent when it was delivered to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and heard the Biſhops Expoſtulation with the <hi>Mayor</hi> about the ſame.</p>
            <p>Such then was the ſtate that the Church buſineſs was in on the City part: when <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmas</hi> comes leading to the Year <hi>One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred ſixty and eight (Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> is the time for the New Elected Mayor and Sheriffs to be Sworn, and take their place) much was expected from this New Mayor, as having profeſſed to bear a Filial reſpect and obedience to the Church: And truly there wanted not plenty of good promiſes, and ſome plauſible overtures from him; but very little in the Church-concerns was done. Much
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53134:8"/>noiſe and out-cry there was about the money levied and collected; That Workmen were not paid; That ſome Materials belonging to the Work were not ſatisfied for; That what money was collected, was not diſtributed, as was intended. I know not how grounded they were, but ſome Suſpitions were concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ſome whiſpering Rumors paſſed abroad, that inſtead of this money being diſpoſed to a Publick uſe, it went into private Pockets. And if it were ſo, it was ſaid, That would not have been the firſt inſtance of that kind in <hi>Waterford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereupon the Biſhop, in order to conſult with the <hi>Mayor</hi> and <hi>Sheriffs,</hi> deſires them to give him a meeting, that as they had underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the raiſing, receiving and diſpoſing the money levied and collected for the Church and the Bells, ſo they might give an account what was become of it, and how diſpoſed of: For, know, that the charge of Caſting the Bells, and providing Clappers, Ropes, and all other things requiſite about them, as they came from <hi>Briſtol,</hi> amounted but to One hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſixteen pound one ſhilling and ſix pence; a Sum, much leſs than what the Rate and Subſcriptions made: But about this time,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53134:8"/>while theſe things were thus diſcuſſing, the ſaid Mayor told a Perſon of good Quality, That as for giving an Account to the Biſhop, he would be content to do it, in caſe he were deſired thereto in a friendly manner; but otherwiſe he would not, becauſe as he was Mayor, ſo he was not ſubject to the Biſhops Juriſdiction.</p>
            <p>Well, notwithſtanding that he was thus (as he termed it, and it was ſo indeed) in a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manner deſired again thus to do; yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he, nor the two Sheriffs did give the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop a meeting as was deſired of them; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Biſhop orders a Proceſs to iſſue out, and Convents them before him in the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory; They refuſe to appear, though being duly Summoned, and ſo run into Contempt. Being called again, and then appearing, they were for their former Contempt enjoined an eaſie Penance; They aggravate their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, with this new Contempt in diſobey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Biſhops Injunction, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon are mildly Cenſured by the Biſhop; Not <hi>Excommunicated,</hi> as was falſely ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor'd and mouth'd abroad by Men that regarded not what proceeded from them,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53134:9"/>whether Truth or Falſhood, ſo it might but ſerve their purpoſes; but large intermiſſions of time there were betwixt every of theſe Proceedings, as will be ſhewed hereafter: And thus ſtands <hi>the matter of Fact</hi> in this whole Tranſaction.</p>
            <p>Upon a Reflection now made on this whole matter in one Review, Will not the <hi>Carriage</hi> of theſe perſons appear of a ſtrange form and kind, to any ſober and indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Man? Hardly, I think, will it be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel'd by Preſident of any ſuch that has for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been; Hardly be entertained with Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, that any ſuch had lately been. And the whole Proceeding being ſo as is here briefly declared, Let the <hi>Perſons concerned here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,</hi> be ſo ingenuous, as freely to confeſs and acknowledge the ſame. If yet this be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (ſo may the trueſt Narrative of things be, and yet have never the leſs of Truth in it for all that) yet there is ſo much, and ſo clear Evidence to Verifie what has been ſet down, That if any Attempt be made of ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to ſuch a Denial, then an eaſie produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of this Evidence, will both ſhame thoſe Deniers, and add to the Confirmation of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53134:9"/>Truth hereof. Howbeit, ſome particularities in ſeveral paſſages of this Proceeding, may find in the following Sections a more ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Diſcovery and Enlargement. In the mean time, the Queſtion <hi>de Jure,</hi> falls in to be diſcuſſed, concerning the juſtifiableneſs of the Biſhops proceedings herein.</p>
            <p>Three main Exceptions I find much inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon, and urged againſt theſe Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, in relation to the Perſons thus Convented and Cenſured; for they being the Mayor and Sheriffs of a City under His Majeſties Government, and repreſenting His Perſon; it is ſaid, That thereupon they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came exempt from any Epiſcopal Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Exception is, in relation to the Cauſe they were called in queſtion upon; for that is affirmed not to be of Eccleſiaſtical, but Civil cognizance, becauſe ſaid to be ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on a real Contract betwixt the Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and the Church; and ſo the holding Plea, and judging of Contracts, belongs not to the Conſiſtory, but to the Temporal Courts.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:53134:10"/>
            <p>The third Exception is, in relation to the manner of Proceedings, which are affirmed to have been precipitous and haſty, without ſuch form and regularity as ought to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved therein, and therefore illegal and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtifiable.</p>
            <p>To theſe three Exceptions, I ſhall oppoſe and endeavour to make good theſe three fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Propoſitions, which will both invali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date any force that might be in the Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and likewiſe aſſert and make good the Legality of what was done herein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I. Prop.</hi> The Biſhops Juriſdiction in the Caſe before mentioned, was Legally found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in reſpect of the Perſons proceeded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>II. Prop.</hi> The Biſhops Juriſdiction over theſe perſons, was Legally founded, in reſpect of the Cauſe proceeded upon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>III. Prop.</hi> The Biſhops Juriſdiction was Legally managed in this Cauſe againſt theſe Perſons, in reſpect of the manner obſerved in the proceedings thereof.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53134:10"/>
            <p>I. <hi>Prop.</hi> The firſt Propoſition, The Biſhops Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction in the caſe before mentioned (was legally founded in reſpect of the Perſons proceeded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt) To make this good, is that, which I am firſt obliged to endeavour. And I do it thus, by laying my foundation in this received Maxime concerning Spiritual juriſdictions; That in all matters and cauſes of Eccleſiaſtical cognizances, all Perſons within any Dioceſs regularly and <hi>de jure communi,</hi> are ſubject to the juriſdiction of the Biſhop of that Dioceſs: The original proceeding of which inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution (I mean as to the actual Exerciſe of ſuch juriſdiction) depends upon, and derives principally from the bounty and munificence of Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors and Princes. As for juriſdiction meerly ſpiritual convei'd in, and at the time of Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, inhaerent in every Biſhop, as he is ſuch, I here ſpeak not of, otherwiſe than as it is the foundation and ground from which this Actual exerciſe does ariſe, and has the enlargements made to it, both ſubjectively in reſpect of perſons made ſubordinate thereto; and objectively in reſpect of matters and cauſes appropriated to it.</p>
            <p>Sundry inſtances making this Aſſertion good, might be had in the Imperial Law: But ſo it will appear to be, to him that will but conſult, <hi>Titulum de Epiſcopali judicio in Codice Theodoſiano, Et Titulum de Epiſcopali Audientia in Codice Juſtinaneo. Et leg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omni innovatione ceſſante. leg. Privilegia ibidem de Sacro, Sanctis Eccleſiis:</hi> whence <hi>Tholoſanus Syntag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat. lib.</hi> 47. <hi>de diviſione judicii num.</hi> 12. 13. Inferrs this rule, <hi>Prelati ſunt ordinarii Judices Rerum &amp; Perſonarum ſuae juriſdictionis:</hi> And moreover adds this, <hi>Caeſares tuentur &amp; defendunt ſacerdotate judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53134:11"/>&amp; Privilegia ejus legibus ſtabiliunt:</hi> And <hi>Gotho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred</hi> on the former of theſe Laws, infers this as a ſtanding rule, <hi>Innovatum contra Canones non ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtit.</hi> By the ancient Canons Biſhops were inveſted with this judiciary power: Chriſtian Emperours favourably confirm the ſame, and any innovation thereupon is of no force. The ſame power of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction in Biſhops is allowed of and made good by <hi>Charles</hi> the Great <hi>In Capitular.</hi> lib. 6. cap. 28.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paulus Fiaceſius</hi> in his Book called <hi>Praxis Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palis cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Articul. S.N.S.</hi> Layes down this Rule, <hi>Epiſcopus in ſua dioeceſi, habet intentionem fundatam ſuper omnes de diaeceſi:</hi> And to confirm the ſaid rule ſo laid down by him, he produces there the Authority of many places in the body of the Canon Law. Indeed where the matter is not of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal cognizance, It is the incompetency of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or cauſe, not the quality, or place, or office of any perſon, that exempts him from that juriſdiction; for as the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rementioned Author obſerves, <hi>Num.</hi> 2 <hi>Ibidem Epiſcopus alium Epiſcopum morantem in ſua dioeceſi, ratione delicti ibidem commiſſi judicare &amp; punire poteſt.</hi> If a Biſhop have juriſdiction over another Biſhop within his own Dioceſs, where the Fuct is of Eccleſiaſtical cognizance; there is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ike, if not a more forcible reaſon, that the Biſhops power ſhould reach to all others of his Dioceſs.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Javolenus</hi> has delivered this Rational and elegant Rule, <hi>Cui juriſdictio Data eſt, ea quoque con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſa eſſe videntur ſine quibus juriſdictio Explicari non poteſt L.</hi> 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>de juriſdictione omnium judicum.</hi> The granting, of a juriſdiction, implyes a grant of all thoſe things that conduce to a right diſcharge
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53134:11"/>and exerciſe of it: A power is included herein of preſiding over and calling all parties under that ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction to anſwer in judgement, of uſing Coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive means to ſuch as are refractory and contumaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and bringing matters to a final and full Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Gothofred</hi> ſayes well hereupon: <hi>Quoties caſus omiſſus virtute &amp;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>expreſſi comprehendi poteſt, toties ad illum fieri debet extenſio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leaſt this poſition may leſs pleaſingly relliſh with ſome pallates, becauſe of the Authority I have hither to made uſe of to eſtabliſh it by: The Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial or Civil Law being not allowed in theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, ſave only in ſome particular Courts and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which is to be ſaid of the Canon Law likewiſe: And in reſpect of the latter of theſe two, ſome men are apt to look aſquint upon any thing that is drawn out of it, or grounded thereon; They are ready to cry out upon ſuch a thing, as a Popiſh en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachment, tending to Advance the Miter and Keyes above the Crown and Scepter <note n="*" place="margin">Yet theſe make up a part of the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Lawes being ſo qualified as by Statute is required in 25 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</note>. To prevent this, or any the like imputation, my next, and that my principal endeavour, is to ſhew its accordance with the State, Conſtitution, and Lawes of theſe Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> under His Majeſties Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; that is, with the Eccleſiaſtical, and with the Municipal Lawes thereof, and with the Kings Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative Royal. In reſpect of all which, I do not doubt to affirm, That this poſition <hi>viz.</hi> [That all perſons whatſoever within any Dioceſs regularly, and <hi>de jure communi,</hi> are ſubject to the juriſdiction of the Biſhop of that Dioceſs in matters and cauſes of Eccleſiaſtical cognizance.] That this poſition, I ſay, is agreeable to the Eccleſiaſtical Lawes of theſe Kingdoms; Not repugnant to the Municipal Lawes
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53134:12"/>thereof; Neither is it, <hi>thirdly,</hi> any thing intrenching upon, or infringing His Majeſties Prerogative Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; Theſe all require diſtinct and particular conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is agreeable to the Eccleſiaſtical Lawes of theſe Kingdoms, in His late Majeſties Proclamation of Royal Aſſent given to the Book of Canons and Conſtitutions Eccleſiaſtical of this Church of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Anno</hi> 1634. I obſerve two things relating to our preſent purpoſe, the former is a ſtrict injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon all perſons whatſoever to obſerve and obey them. <hi>We do not only by our ſaid Prerogative Royal and Supream Authority in cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, ratifie, confirm and eſtabliſh by theſe our Letters Patents the ſaid Canons, Orders, Ordinances and Conſtitutions, and all and every thing therein contained, as is aforeſaid; but do likewiſe propound, publiſh and streightly enjoyn and command by our ſaid Authority, and by theſe our Letters Patents, the ſame to be diligently obſerved, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted and equally kept, by all our loving Subjects of this our Kingdom, in all points wherein they do or may concern every or any of them, according to this our Will and pleaſure hereby ſignifyed and expreſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other thing I obſerve therein, is that impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Execution of them (which is required to be made, and by whom to be made) upon all perſons <hi>whatſoever that refuſe to obey them:</hi> ſo it afterwards follows <hi>Streightly charging and commanding all Arch-Biſhops, and all others that exerciſe any Eccleſiaſtical juriſdiction within this Realm, to ſee and procure, that the ſame Canons, Conſtitutions, Orders and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, be in all points duly obſerved. Not ſparing to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute the penalties in them ſeverally mentioned upon (Any) that ſhall wittingly or willingly break or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53134:12"/>to obſerve the ſame: as they tender the Honour of God, the peace of the Church, tranquility of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and their duties and ſervice unto <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s their King and Sovereign.</hi> All are commanded to obey theſe, none have an Immunity from being puniſhed if they do not obey them.</p>
            <p>In the laſt Canon of that Book, It is decreed, That if <hi>(Any)</hi> within this Nation ſhall deſpiſe and contemn the Conſtitutions thereof (Ratified and confirmed by Regal power) or affirm that none ſhall be ſubject to them, but ſuch as were preſent and gave their voyces to them, He ſhall be Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, and not reſtored, until he ſhall publickly revoke his Error. In the 140 Canon of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> publiſhed <hi>Anno</hi> 1603. It is more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly and expreſly ſet down and declared, that all <hi>manner of Perſons, both of Clergie and Laity, are to be ſubject to the Decrees mentioned in them in cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Eccleſiaſtical: Although they were not themſelves particularly aſſembled in the ſame Sacred Synod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us now put both theſe things obſerved, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and the reſult is this: Here is a juriſdiction declared in reſpect of certain matters and cauſes, and in reſpect of Perſons indefinitly ſet down over all: And in whom is this juriſdiction declared to be? namely, in Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, &amp;c. over whom is it declared to be? over all ſurely. The injunction of inflicting penalties in caſe of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is as univerſal and extenſive ſubjectively, as is the command of obedience: Here is no diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on nor exemption made of any Perſons, under any qualification, or Veſted with any office, or ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate civil power, ſo as they ſhould be thereby pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledged from Eccleſiaſtical juriſdiction in matters
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53134:13"/>appertaining thereunto. And <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi lex non diſtinguit, ibi nec nos diſtinguere debemus,</hi> where the Law makes none, neither may we make any diſtinction.</p>
            <p>I have made my firſt inſtance in theſe Canons as part of the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Lawes: But I am not to learn, that when the Authority of our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons is urged, and that obedience which is required to them, is called for, There are a generation of ſuch as are wiſe in their own conceits, men of mighty deep underſtandings, who think they pierce further into things, and underſtand more than their poor ſhallow Brethren are able to do: And theſe will queſtion the Validity of theſe Canons, and their legal obligingneſs on the Kings Majeſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. To all ſuch therefore I ſhall fairly offer a few, conſiderations, and then leave in to their own ſober thoughts to determine, wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Coherence there can be betwixt a diſowning, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Authority of our Eccleſiaſtical <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the profeſſion of being dutiful and obediene Subjects.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Many learned men, both of the Municipal and Civil Law, joyn in this opinion, and affirm, That the Kings Majeſty may by virtue of His Supream Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in matters Eccleſiaſtical, confirm and ratifie into the force of Law Canons made in Convocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that they be a part of the Kings Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Lawes. <hi>Princeps tanquam ſupremus poſt Deum gubernator poteſt in cauſis Eccleſiaſticis ſtatuere quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid verbo divino, ſtatutis &amp; conſuetudinibus Regni ſui non repugnaverit</hi> Coſen. <hi>de Politeia Eccleſiaſtic. Anglicana Tab.</hi> 1. <hi>A.</hi> And then he ſpecifies the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his former. Aſſertion thus, <hi>viz.</hi> That this ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream power of our King, is in <hi>Condendis novis le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus, ſive canonibus, in ijsdem adminiſtrandis &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxandis
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53134:13"/>cirea ſtatum Eccleſiaſticum:</hi> and this done, <hi>cum Regius aſſenſus fuerit adhibitus iis, quae Synodus decernenda Cenſuerit ibidem Tab.</hi> 2. <hi>In Synod Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nali vel provinciali Regis reſcripto convocato, nihil tractari aut determinari poteſt niſi eo aſſentiente, nec quicquam vim legis obtinet, priuſquam Regalis aſſenſus adhibitus fuerit. Dr. Zouch. Deſcript. Juris Eccles. p.</hi> 1. Sect. 2. See alſo to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Dr.</hi> Duck <hi>de authoritate Juris civilis in Anglia lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>Sect</hi> 27. And the Lord chief Juſtice <hi>Cook</hi> 4. <hi>p. Inſtit. cap.</hi> 74. cited thereby him.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The King himſelf in the Proclamation before mentioned, declares that ſuch Canons, Conſtitutions, &amp;c. agreed upon by the Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, and Clergie of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to the end and purpoſe by him limited and preſcribed unto them, <hi>He has given His Royal aſſent, according to the form of a certain ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute or Act of Parliament made in that behalf; And by his Prerogative Royal, and Supream Authority in matters Eccleſiaſtical, he has ratified and confirmed the ſaid Canons being one hundred in number, by his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents under his great Seal of</hi> Ireland; And then follows His Majeſties ſtrict injunction upon all His loving Subjects of this Kingdom to obey and execute the ſame, which I inſiſted upon before.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Beſides His Majeſties Prerogative Royal and Supream Authority in cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, the King is likewiſe by Act of Parliament veſted with power for this purpoſe, and that is the Statute 25 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. called the Petition and Submiſſion of the Clergie to the King; For the Biſhops and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie in Convocation having each one ſeverally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed in <hi>verbo ſacerdotis,</hi> never henceforth to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to attempt, alledge, claim, or put in uſe, or enact, promulge or execute any new Canons, Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53134:14"/>or Ordinances without the Kings moſt Royal aſſent had and obtained thereunto; upon which promiſe and ſubmiſſion it was enacted by Authority of Parliament; That all Convocations in time to come ſhould always be aſſembled, by the Authority of the Kings Writ. And that the Kings licenſe and authority being had, they might make, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulge and Execute ſuch Canons, Conſtitutions and Ordinances Provincial and Synodal, which being ratified, confirmed and approved under His Majeſties Great Seal, they then become of legal force upon the Subject. This Proviſo indeed follows, That no Canon nor Ordinance ſhall be made or put in Execution by the Authority of the Convocation of the Clergie, which ſhall be contrariant, or repugnant to the Kings Prerogative Royal, or the Cuſtoms and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of this Realm <hi>&amp;c. Raſtals</hi> collection word <hi>(Rome)</hi> numb. 1. <note n="*" place="margin">Which <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis</hi> is but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of the Common Law, ſays my Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> 4. <hi>Inſtit. cap.</hi> 74. p. 323. So that the ſame is grounded both on Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law.</note> The like Statute to this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar we have enacted in <hi>Ireland,</hi> Entituled, <hi>An Act againſt the Authority of the Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>in viceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimo Octavo Hen.</hi> 8. and referred to in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation before ſpoken of in the ſecond conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>A Great Lawyer one Mr. <hi>J.M.</hi> (in a ſpeech be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Committee of the Lords, at the Parliament held <hi>Anno</hi> 1641.) Having occaſion to ſpeak of this Statute (for his ſpeech was againſt the Canons made the year before) avouched plainly that, that clauſe, <hi>The Clergie ſhall not make Canons without the Kings leave, implyeth not that by his leave alone, they may make them:</hi> But certainly the moſt knowing men in any Science or faculty, have not the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of never miſtaking in what they ſay: for to him that adviſedly conſiders the matter and ſcope
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53134:14"/>of that Statute, it will appear plainly, That the abridging the over-growing power of the Clergie aſſumed by them in making and enacting Canons, and preſſing their authority on others: And to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with this, the cutting them off from any relation to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and making them dependants on the King alone, for the better orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of what ſhould be debated and determined in their Synodical meetings; were, if not the only, yet the principal aims of that Statute: Add here further, that a ſucceſſive and continued practice from the time when that Statute was made to this day, delivers the beſt and trueſt ſenſe of it. <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Practiea eſt legum optima intellectrix.</hi> Baldus.</note> For thus as I have ſet down, it was practiſed in the times of <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th, Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> 1562. King <hi>James Anno</hi> 1603. King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt in this Kingdom of <hi>Ireland Anno</hi> 1634. And though I ſay nothing of the Canons themſelves made in the year 1640. (becauſe all authority as to them is annulled by Act of Parliament, <hi>Anno</hi> 13 <hi>Caroli Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundi</hi>) yet the Commiſſion granted to the Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of that year, at the firſt opening of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and of it, was according to Law; and this ſpeaks plainly of the Kings leave and licenſe granted and alone needful herein; ſee more fully thereof in Dr. <hi>Heylins</hi> life of the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury, p.</hi> 423.424.425.</p>
            <p>I conclude this matter with the deciſion of a great Caſuiſt: He in diſcourſing of Eccleſiaſtical Laws, and the manner how they are enacted in the Church of <hi>England. Jus condendi leges Eccleſiaſticas</hi> (ſaies he!) <hi>eſt paenes Epiſcopos, Presbyteros, aliaſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> perſonas à totius Regni clero rite electas &amp; in legitima Synodo rite congregatas: Ita tamen; ut ejus juris, ſine
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53134:15"/>potestatis exercitium in omni Repub. Chriſtiana ex Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate Supremi Magiſtrat us Politici pendere debeat: Id<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp; aparte Ante (ut loqui ſolemus) &amp; aparte poſt vir: ut nec iis ſtatuendi Canones Eccleſiasticos cauſâ liceat convenire, niſi autipſius mandato &amp; inſſu ad id negotii convocatis: aut ejus ſaltem authoritate, Venia ab eo petita &amp; obtenta munitis: Nec Canones in quos illi ſic conſenſerint, tali ſint, aut vim aliquam habeant obligandi, quoad ſupremi Magiſtratus aſſenſus accedat: Cujus approbatione &amp; publica authoritate ſimulac confirmati fuerint, illico pro legibus habendi ſunt &amp; ſubditos obligant, Biſhop</hi> Sanderſon; <hi>de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcient. obligat. Praelect.</hi> 7. <hi>Sect.</hi> 30. Mr. <hi>Hooker Eccles. Polit. Book</hi> 8. <hi>in p.</hi> 219.220.221. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus much has been ſaid touching the Canons of our Church, and their Authority, ſo far forth at this preſent, as ſuits with the preſent occaſion, and what they were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in proof of.</p>
            <p>In ſeveral Provincial Conſtitutions we find it De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, That concerning matters belonging to Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical cognizance, proceedings may be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any Layman or publick Officers, as Sheriffs and others, even to the inflicting publick Cenſures upon them. Many of this kind will occur to the Reader that is converſant in them; That Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Aeterna Sanctis de paenis,</hi> Enacted in a Council at <hi>Lambeth</hi> under <hi>Boniface</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> Anno 1260. In the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third. And that Conſtitution <hi>ut invadentibus de immunitate Eccleſiae,</hi> Enacted by the ſame <hi>Boniface;</hi> likewiſe the Conſtitution <hi>contingit aliquando eodem,</hi> And <hi>Accidit Novitate perverſa eodem,</hi> Enacted by <hi>John Stratford</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third. Now if it be here ſaid, that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53134:15"/>theſe Conſtitutions were made before the Statute of <hi>Praemunire</hi> came forth, and ſo proceeded more peremptorily, and not with that ſubmiſſive regard and dutiful obedience to the Crown, as they ought to have done. I anſwer, by acknowledging thoſe Conſtitutions to aim indeed at the reſtraining of the Kings Prerogative, and of his Temporal Courts, and therefore not of any force now, or that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings ſhould be guided thereby.
<note n="*" place="margin">Sir <hi>Tho. Ridley</hi> in his View &amp;c. leaves it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deciſion, whether theſe conſtitutions be annulled by the Act of Parliament <hi>viz.</hi> 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 19. He determines not abſolutely, I ſay but refers it to better judgements.</note> But this men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made of them to ſhew Hiſtorically what was then practiſed and held uſually; and moreover to evince, that where the Rights of the Crown are not thereby impaired, nor any of the Kings Temporal Courts invaded; Eccleſiaſtical proceedings may be made againſt any Perſon, and his being in any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate civil office does not exempt him therefrom. I muſt yield to, and acknowledge what the Statute 25 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. has determined, <hi>viz.</hi> All Canons, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, Ordinances and Synodals Provincial that had been then made, are received into the body of the Eccleſiaſtical Laws, and are Eſtabliſhed to be the Eccleſiaſtical Lawes of <hi>England,</hi> and become of good force and validity: but with this neceſſary proviſo herein, <hi>quatenus conſuetudinibus &amp; ſtatutis Regninon repugnant, nec prerogativae Regiae adverſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> Dr. <hi>Zouch de jure Eccleſiaſt. p.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. So the Statute it ſelf reports of them, that they are of force and ſtill binding, ſo far forth, as they be not contrariant, nor repugnant to the Laws, cuſtoms, and ſtatutes of this Realm, nor to the Danger or Hurt of the Kings prerogative Roya.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Formula</hi> of Juridical practice for cauſes Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical ſet forth by <hi>Francis Clerk,</hi> and which is approved in all the Conſiſtories and other Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53134:16"/>Courts of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> In this <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mula,</hi> I ſay, There is a title, namely, the two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifteenth title of that Book, after what manner to begin and proceed in any Eccleſiaſtical cauſe (perhaps at the inſtance of a party) againſt any Community as Dean and Chapter, Maſter, Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, and Scholars of any Colledge, &amp;c. In the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of which title, the manner of proceeding againſt any Mayor and Community of a City, particularly that of <hi>London,</hi> is deſcribed; whence I make this Collection, That what is declared as a matter to be obſerved in Eccleſiaſtical practice, when occaſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a proceeding againſt any Mayor or Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of a City: that does certainly imply, that ſuch a Mayor and Community are ſubject to Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical juriſdiction, and conſequently to ſuch penal coercions and cenſures (the matter ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring it) as are properly inflicted thereby. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto concerning the firſt particular, that this poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is agreeable to the Eccleſiaſtical Law.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As this poſition is agreeable to the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Law, ſo it is not repugnant to the Kings Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Laws, or the Municipal Laws of theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. It is not repugnant to the Statute Law: The Statute called <hi>Magna Charta</hi> confirmed by King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third in the Ninth year of His Reign, and by ſo many Kings ſince this Statute (ſaid to be the Ancienteſt written Law that is now extant, and the Breviate and Summary of all the written Laws of <hi>England</hi> and moſt beneficial to the Subject) declares in the firſt Chapter thereof, That the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhall be free, and have all her Holy rights and liberties inviolable.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:53134:16"/>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Et habeant omnia jur a ſua integra)</hi> that is, all Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical perſons ſhall enjoy all their lawful juriſdictions, and other rights without any diminuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or ſubſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. D. <hi>Coke,</hi> on <hi>Magna Charta. cap.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jura ſua)</hi> ſayes the ſame Author <hi>ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem,</hi> prove plainly, that no new rights were given to them, but ſuch as they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hereby are confirmed, ſo that it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, that what amply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction they had before, is hereby con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed.</p>
               </note> In the Thirty ſeven Chapter of the ſaid Statute, There is a Reſerve to all Archbiſhops, Biſhops, &amp;c. Of all their Liberties and Priviledges: one branch of which Liberties and Priviledges and Rights, is this power of juriſdiction over all perſons in their reſpective Dioceſſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, the Son and Succeſſor of this King, ordained the Statute called <hi>circumſpecte Agatis</hi> in the thirteenth year of His Reign. It has been affirmed concerning this Law, that it was a prelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Conſtitution, becauſe inſerted in the Provincial Conſtitutions in the title <hi>de foro competenti:</hi> or at the moſt, one onely of the Kings Writs iſſuing out on ſome occaſion leading thereunto. But to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Authority hereof, My Lord chief Juſtice <hi>Coke</hi> determines of it after this manner; though ſome have ſaid this was no Statute, but made by the Prelates themſelves: Yet that it is an Act of Parliament, is not only proved by our Books, but alſo by an Act of Parliament. <hi>Inſtit. p.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 487. In this Statute then (ſet down as a boundary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Spiritual and Temporal juriſdiction) full power and authority is given or confirmed rather to the exerciſe of juriſdiction Eccleſiaſtical, over all perſons indiſtinctly, in ſuch caſes as belong to and are mentioned in it.</p>
            <p>In the Ninth year of His Son and Succeſſor King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, came forth the ſtatute called <hi>Articuli cleri,</hi> by the form and purport of which, it appeareth, that for any matter Eccleſiaſtical, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definitely Men may be cited; and if cited, then ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to all judicial conſequences therein. In the Twelfth Chapter of this ſtatute, The queſtion is put, Whether the Kings Tenants be ſubject to the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53134:17"/>Eccleſiaſtical juriſdiction, as others are; and if they may be Excommunicated for their manifeſt contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, and after forty dayes continuing ſo, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they may be ſignified and attached by the Kings Writ? The anſwer given to the queſtion is ſuch: It was never yet denyed, nor ſhall be hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <note n="*" place="margin">The cloſe of which Statute is after this manner. Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving all and every of the Articles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, with all and every of the Anſwers made and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the ſame, do grant and command them to be kept firmly and obſerved for ever, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and gran ting for us and our Heirs, that the foreſaid Prelates and Clergie, and their Succe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, ſhall uſe, execute and practiſe for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the Church in the Premiſes after the Tenor of the Anſwers aforeſaid, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out quarrel, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieting or vexation of our Heirs, or any of our Officers whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they be. <hi>Poult. Collect</hi> of ſtatutes p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 101. in <hi>fine cap.</hi> 16.</note> It ſeems the Kings Tenants ſuppoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſuch ſpecially priviledged perſons, as to be thereby exempted from ſpiritual juriſdiction; but that would not ſerve their turns, And ſo <hi>a pari,</hi> what would not be ſufficient for them, will not be ſufficient for others though in office under the King.</p>
            <p>During the long Reign of Fifty years of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, the great Charter was ſeveral times confirmed. The liberties, priviledges, and franchiſes of the Clergie were new ratified in the fourteenth and five and twentieth years of His Reign. And ſo in the firſt, ſixth and eighth and twelfth years of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond. In the firſt ſecond and fourth years of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, It was enacted, That the Lords Spiritual as well as Temporal, ſhould have and enjoy all their Rights and Liberties.</p>
            <p>I grant indeed that in the Reign of two of theſe preceding Kings, <hi>viz, Edward</hi> the third, and <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> the ſecond, that the two ſtatutes of Proviſo's and Praemunire were made: But he that ſhall duly obſerve the end wherefore, and the matter wherein, and the perſons againſt whom theſe ſtatutes were made, will not be able to find that any abridgment, but rather a firmer ſettlement of Epiſcopal juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, in the right Conſtitution of it, was intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and came thereby: That which was mainly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53134:17"/>aimed at, and provided againſt in theſe ſtatutes, was, to repreſs the encroachments of the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> even upon the Biſhops legal juriſdiction it ſelf. The Pope by His Emiſſaries in <hi>England,</hi> from time to time drained the Kingdom of its Wealth; He in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded the Kings Soveraign Rights, by Mandates <hi>De providendo,</hi> and expectative Graces, granted of Eccleſiaſtical livings before the Incumbents were dead: And beſides, He boldly intrenched on the Kings Temporal Courts, many ſuch unreaſonable greivances there were; which both King and People felt the load of, and which to make them the heavier, were fetch as far as <hi>Rome,</hi> to be put upon them.</p>
            <p>But all this while, here are no exemptions to any particular perſons, or civil Officers to free them from Eccleſiaſtical juriſdiction, where it proceeded in due manner, and was exerciſed in matters proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cognizable by it; That which muſt have the note of remark put upon it, is this: Proviſion is here made under ſevere penalties againſt acting by a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived power from, and in an Uſurped juriſdiction under the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> This no Engliſh Biſhop might do then; This no Biſhop in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> might, or does, or may do now.</p>
            <p>One Act of Parliament will beſt ſerve to give light to another. Now the ſtatute 25 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 21, affirms expreſly, that the ſtatute of proviſion and praemunire of the 16th <hi>Richard ſecundi,</hi> was made againſt ſuch as ſue to the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> againſt the Kings Crown and Dignity: ſo that Epiſcopal juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction in each reſpective Dioceſs, and in matters of Eccleſiaſtical cognizance, is ſo far from being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53134:18"/>by theſe ſtatutes, that in truth it is more firmly fixed and corroborated thereby.</p>
            <p>All theſe things were before the Reformation in <hi>England,</hi> towards the dawning of which, we meet with a noted ſtatute in the 23th year of King <hi>Henry</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. deſigned, as is conceived, to reſtrain the Exorbitances uſed in ſummoning people out of the Dioceſs wherein they inhabit without leave of their Ordinaries: which thing, as it tended to the great vexation of the perſons ſo cited; it alſo aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the very encroaching on the ſeveral Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Rights, on pretence of ſome legantine power, or <hi>Nuncio's</hi> Court or other extraordinary cauſe. In the preamble of which Statute, it is affirmed, That all perſons of any quality or condition may be cited before their Ordinaries: (ſo it be in proper cauſe and due Order) The body of that ſtatute provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, that no citation be made out of the Dioceſs where the party dwelleth, but where ſome ſpiritual offence or cauſe is committed or done. <hi>So that a contrario ſenſu (ſayes the learned and judicious</hi> Dr. <hi>Coſen Apol. p.</hi> 67.) <hi>in any offence or cauſe ſpiritual, any Subject may be cited within his or her Dioceſs: And in ſome peculiar cauſes there mentioned, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited, they may be cited out of their Dioceſs.</hi> Now the power of citing, preſuppoſes a full juriſdiction: that is, a power to proceed further thereupon in all due requiſits and forms that belong to any cauſe, whether it be upon inſtance, or of matter of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <p>Since the Reformation that all juriſdiction Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical is <hi>de facto,</hi> as it was alwayes <hi>de jure</hi> united to, and ſo derived from the Imperial Crown of <hi>England;</hi> there is by the ſtatute of the firſt of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53134:18"/>Queen <hi>Elizabeth, cap.</hi> 1. Full power and authority given to the Eccleſiaſtical Judges for the Executing of Eccleſiaſtical juriſdiction as before time. See alſo a ſtatute made in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in the 28. year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. called an Act againſt the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome:</hi> towards the latter end thereof—<hi>Provided, that notwithſtanding this Act, or any other Act made for the taking away of the ſaid Biſhop of</hi> Romes <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped power, Authority, Prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, Juriſdiction or any other thing or things in the ſame compriſed; That all and every Archbiſhop, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, Arch-Deacon, Commiſſary and Official, and every of them, ſhall, and may uſe and exerciſe in the name of the King only, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. infra p.</hi> 53.</note> all ſuch Canons, Conſtitutions, Ordinances and Synodals provincial, being already made, for the direction and order of Spiritual and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical cauſes, which be not contrariant nor repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Kings Lawes, ſtatutes and cuſtoms of this Land, nor to the Damage and Hurt of the Kings Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Royal, in ſuch manner and form, as they were uſed and Executed before the making of this Act: till ſuch time as the Kings Highneſs ſhall order and determine according to his Lawes of</hi> England, <hi>and ſuch order and determination, as ſhall be requiſite for the ſame, and the ſame to be certified hither, under the Kings Great Seal, or otherwiſe ordered by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And while I am thus enumerating the ſeveral ſtatutes which the former poſition is not contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant to, but rather ſtrengthned by, I muſt not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the making mention of thoſe ſtatutes and Acts of Parliament that are ſet out and publiſhed, meerly upon Eccleſiaſtical cauſes and matters (which are reckoned by ſome, as thoſe that enter into, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53134:19"/>make up the body of the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Laws, <hi>Zouch de jure Eccleſ. p.</hi> 1. <hi>Sec.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) whether theſe be matters of a civil or criminal Nature: matters of civil cognizance are either ſuch as concern Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contracts and other matrimonial cauſes. In <hi>Ireland,</hi> 33 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8 <hi>cap.</hi> 6. In <hi>England.</hi> 32 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 38. 1 and 2 <hi>Edward</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 23. 1 <hi>Elizab.</hi> 1. o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch as concern Teſtamentary matters, 21 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. In this Kingdom, 28 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. Alſo matters of Tythes, and the purſuits and impleadings there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>up on: He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, 33 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 12. In <hi>England</hi> to the two Statutes mentioned before, called <hi>circumſpecte Agatis,</hi> and <hi>Articuli Cleris</hi> Theſe may be added, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 14.27. and 28 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 20. 32 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 7. 2 <hi>Edward</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. Concerning all which, all perſons, without diſtinction of place or office, who are concerned in any of theſe cauſes, they are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Epiſcopal juriſdiction, to which the ſame cauſes do appertain, and by which they are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged. And for matters which are criminal: To paſs by other ſtatutes, I inſtance in theſe two only. The one <hi>De Excommunicato capiendo,</hi> in 5 <hi>Elizab. c.</hi> 23. where the ſeveral crimes therein mentioned, ſubject all ſuch as ſhall be detected and found guilty of any of them to the Eccleſiaſtical Tribunal: The other is the ſtatute for Uniformity of Common-Prayer, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Elizab. cap.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>In this ſtatute, after a charge given in this Solemn and ſtrict manner— <hi>The Queens moſt Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, The Lords Temporal, and all the Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, do in Gods Name earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly require and charge all the Archbiſhops and Biſhops, to endeavor their utmoſt for the due execution thereof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> And then it follows for their power and authority in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53134:19"/>this behalf— Be it further Enacted by the Authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, That all and ſingular the ſaid Archbiſhops, Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and all other their officers, exerciſing Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical juriſdiction, as well in places exempt, as not exempt, within their Dioceſs, ſhall have full power and authority by this Act, to reform, correct and puniſh by cenſures of the Church,</hi> all and ſingular Perſons, <hi>which ſhall offend within any of their Juriſdictions or Dioceſſes after the ſaid Feaſt of</hi> St. John <hi>the Baptiſt next coming, againſt this Act or Statute, any other Law, Statute, Priviledge, liberty or proviſion, heretofore made, had, or ſuffered to the contrary notwithſtanding.</hi> See a ſo the ſtatute made <hi>ſecundo Elizab. cap.</hi> 2 here in <hi>Ireland.</hi> The thing we had in hand to make good was this: That all perſons whatſoever within any Dioceſs regularly, and <hi>de jure communi,</hi> are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Biſhop of that Dioceſs in matters and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Eccleſiaſtical cognizance, &amp; that this poſition is not repugnant to the ſtatute Laws of theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms: This I think has been fully evidenced, and needs no further enlarging upon.</p>
            <p>And to give one inſtance of this juriſdictive and coercive power in Biſhops over all indefinitely, it ſhall be in the matter of ſubſtracting and detaining of Tythes, a cauſe properly and anciently cognizable before them. That ample Charter granted by King <hi>William</hi> the firſt to the Clergie, and mentioned at large by Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> in his Hiſtory of Tythes, <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 225. The concluſion of which is after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: <hi>Quicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> decimam detinuerit per juſtitiam Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi &amp; Regis (ſi neceſſe fuerit) ad redditionem ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guatur.</hi> Startle not, Reader, at the eying of this, that the Biſhops power of Juſticing has here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedency of place before the Kings: conceive not,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53134:20"/>that this was to ſet Epiſcopal power on high, and make Regal Authority ſubordinate to it: But this declares, to whoſe judicial cognizance under the King, the proceeding againſt detainers of Tythes (of what quality and condition ſoever they be) does immediatery appertain, &amp; who is the Officer and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Juſtice therein: And the Kings power being after mentioned, is ſo ſet down by way of judicial order and conſequence, not of ſubordination in power and Authority: Thus much theſe very words <hi>(ſi neceſſe fuerit)</hi> plainly do import, as if it were ſaid, ſhould any of theſe detainers prove refracto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and contumacious againſt the Biſhops authority, ſo that there were a neceſſity of invoking the ſecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar power, the King would then be preſent therewith, and by poenal coercions compel them to give obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience thereto.</p>
            <p>Now for what concerns any other part of the Common Law, it may be alſo both ſafely and truly in reſpect of the thing it ſelf affirmed, That Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical proceedings according to the poſition laid down, bears no contrariety therewith, as is ſet down by <hi>Dr. and Student, lib.</hi> 1 <hi>c.</hi> 6. That Epiſcopal juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction is of force in this Kingdom even by the Laws of this Realm, in certain particular inſtances mentioned, is reported by Dr. <hi>Coſen</hi> from a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Author writing in King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8th time (<hi>Apol. part</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 7.) The Author is ſhewing, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> has not, nor ought to have any juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in His Majeſties Kingdoms by the Laws of this Realm: The medium whereby he proves this thing is this, becauſe Certificates of Biſhops in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain caſes are allowed by the Common Law, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the Kings Courts; But the Popes Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53134:20"/>is not admitted, <hi>vid.</hi> Lord <hi>Coke Inſtit.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 74. <hi>circa initium. &amp; de jure Regis Eccleſiaſtico, p.</hi> 23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 26. <hi>&amp; diverſos caſus thidem citatos.</hi> Beſides, in the ſtatute of Appeals, 24 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. mention is made of ſpiritual juriſdiction exerciſed in cauſes belonging to the ſame, and it is there expreſly ſaid, <hi>That ſuch exerciſe is grounded on the Laws and cuſtoms of this Realm: circa mitium dicti ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuti.</hi> Now certainly a ſtatute beſt informs any one, what is truly, and what is agreeable to the, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law. The Biſhops are by the Common Law the immediate Officers and Miniſters of Juſtice to the Kings Courts in cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, Lord <hi>Coke de jure Regis Eccleſiaſtico, pag.</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>And for what belongs to any cuſtom or ancient uſage that has the force of Law among us, I cannot find out any ſuch that is impugned by what I have affirmed: But thus I may ſafely determine, That if any manner and courſe of things eſtabliſhed by long uſe and conſent of our Anceſtors, and ſtill kept on foot by daily continuance and practice, be a cuſtom, and may ſet up for a Law not-written: Then certainly the thing that has been affirmed (that is, the exerciſe of Eccleſiaſtical juriſdiction by Biſhops over all perſons within their reſpective Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſſes, and in cauſes belonging to it) and thus far endeavoured to be p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oved, is not at all contrariant thereto, but of perfect agreement, yea of the ſame Nature with it.</p>
            <p>Are there any that after all this will make their reply, and tell us of perſons exempted from Epiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> power, and the exerciſe thereof bound up and reſtrained in reſpect of ſuch, and for proof of this will alledge the Authoritative proceeding of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53134:21"/>King <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, who would not ſuffer any Biſhop to Excommunicate any of his Barons or Officers, for <hi>Adultery, Inceſt,</hi> or any ſuch Heinous crime, except by the Kings command firſt made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted therewith. By the way it muſt be known, that the word Baron, is not to be taken in that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited and reſtrictive ſenſe, as to underſtand thereby the Higher Nobility, to which Votes in Parliament do belong: But generally for ſuch who by <hi>Tenure in chief,</hi> or <hi>in Capite</hi> held land of the King, <hi>Selden ſpicelegium ad Eadmerum, referente Tho. Fullero B.</hi> 3. <hi>Hiſtor. Eccleſ. p.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever now ſhall be collected hence to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw what has been before ſaid, is eaſily anſwered: For King <hi>William</hi> very well underſtood his own Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peral power and right over the whole body Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick (whereof the Clergie were a part) And that by vertue thereof, the Actual Exerciſe of both Civil and Eccleſiaſtical juriſdiction did flow from him. And that he might where and when he ſaw cauſe, reſtrain the Execution of either, how long, or in reſpect of what perſons he pleaſed, and this by ſpecial priviledge and immunity granted by him to ſuch perſons: And yet that juriſdiction ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, be no more impeached thereby, than the ordinary ſetled courſe of the common Law, by the Exemption of one or more particular perſons from being proceeded againſt therein. Let us ſeek to underſtand this by a very plain and familiar exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple every day obverſant before us: His Majeſty has a ſtanding Army in <hi>Ireland</hi> in Pay, and under His Command: All the Officers and private Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers therein, for ſome good reaſons beſt known to himſelf in His great wiſdom, are exempted from
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53134:21"/>any Civil, or criminal Impleadments before the Eccleſiaſtical or Temporal Tribunals, without leave firſt had and obtained from His Royal ſelf, or His Vice gerent here. Now will it not be a weak &amp; inconſequent way of arguing, to conclude from hence, that the Judges in the Peinpora Courts have not an univerſal juriſdiction ſubjectively, in reſpect of thoſe over whom they are appointed, becauſe a few a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e by ſpecial priviledge exempted from it? It will be ſo too certainly, to conclude the like of the Biſhops, the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Judges in the Eccleſiaſtical juriſdiction, becauſe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re certain perſon or perſons may by peculiar diſpenſation be taken out of the ſame: let the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt be urged that can be fetch't out of this preſent inſtance from <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, yet we ſhall find enough to ſtil and quiet that (and in the ſame kind too) remember we but the 12th <hi>chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of the ſtatute ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed <hi>Articuli Cleri,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned: By that it will be apparent, That King <hi>William</hi> even in this particular, did not ſo nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly bound Epiſcopal juriſdiction, as King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond did let it looſe, extend and enlarge it. The one exempted his ſervants and Tenants from the Eccleſiaſtical juriſdiction: The other almoſt three hundred years after, and by a ſtatute Law, gave both up, and fully ſubmitted them to it.</p>
            <p>With<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut more adoe: The queſtion is not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the King as Supream Governour over all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, in all Eccleſiaſtical things and cauſes, may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt any of his Retainers, or any ſubordinate Officers in places of Civil power under Him, from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impleaded or proceed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d againſt in Eccleſiaſtical Courts: But the queſtion is, whether he has Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:53134:22"/>done it or no, or if done it, whether to perſons ſo qualified as our caſe proceeds upon. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer I do not, I muſt not, I dare not deny: For the Regal power and Supremacy reaches as far in grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing priviledges and immunities to any (who are thought worthy of the ſame) in reſpect of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical matters and tryals, as it does in reſpect of civil matters and tryals. What he may do in the one, he may do in the other. Thus I read, That the King by His Prerogative may give protection to ſuch perſons as are His debtors, ſo as not to be ſued by their Creditors till Himſelf be ſatisfied, <hi>Fitz. Nat. br. fol.</hi> 28. <hi>B.</hi> Inſtances more might be given of this kind. So he may likewiſe exempt from the Eccleſiaſtical juriſdiction: But that His Majeſtie has Actually done this to perſons ſo qualified as our caſe proceeds upon, and <hi>quatenus,</hi> as they are ſo qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; is that thing the contrary to which I have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto engaged my ſelf to make clear, and have yet ſomething remaining to add thereto: For the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent inſtance from <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror; It was no reſtraining of Epiſcopal juriſdiction, but in ſuch a particular matter reſerving to himſelf the power of appointing the exerciſe of it: or if it yet will be looked upon as a reſtraint put thereon, yet it muſt be withall conſidered, that he did not ſo much limit and reſtrain in this caſe, as he was pleaſed to give greater ſcope to it in a matter of far greater importance, as ſhall be ſhewed by and by.</p>
            <p>Mean while I ſum up this point thus; That the Eſtabliſhed courſe of Eccleſiaſtical proceedings, is not repugnant to the Municipal Laws of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; that by the gracious indulgence &amp; conceſſions of our Pious Princes, a <hi>liberty</hi> and <hi>power</hi> is granted
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53134:22"/>by them to the Biſhops to <hi>exerciſe actually</hi> Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical juriſdiction upon the <hi>Subjects</hi> of the <hi>Crown:</hi> That they may be ſummoned: That refractory and contumacious perſons may by coercive power be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to good order: That compulſories may be iſſued forth and cenſures inflicted, where juſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion requires, and all due requiſits have preceded: They may hear and determine in cauſes of inſtance between party and party, and alſo proceed againſt any criminals (under Eccleſiaſtical cognizance) of what quality and condition ſoever they be, for cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and reformation of manners.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Poſition, That all perſons within any Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs regularly, and <hi>de jure communi,</hi> are ſubject to the juriſdiction of the Biſhop of that Dioceſs in all matters and cauſes of Eccleſiaſtical cognizance, is not any way intrenching upon, or infringing His Majeſties Prerogative Royal. The Kings Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive is called by Sir <hi>Henry Spelman, Gloſſar. ibid. Lex Regie dignitatis:</hi> by the Civilians, <hi>Jus Imperii:</hi> by the later <hi>Feudiſts, jus Regaliorum:</hi> And the import of all theſe, is compriſed in this deſcription given thereof. The Kings Prerogative is that ſpecial pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, preheminence, or priviledge that the King hath in any kind over and above other perſons, and above the ordinary courſe of the Common Law. <hi>Cowell ibidem.</hi> A branch of this is the Kings Legiſtative power in Eceleſiaſtical matters and cauſes, with the advice and conſent of ſuch as are appointed thereto. And by the Statute of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, in the Seventeenth year of His Reign, called <hi>Prerogativa Regis,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>That whatſoever Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious conceſſions the King is pleaſed to make unto the Honour of Gods Church and good of the Common
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53134:23"/>wealth, and for the remedy of ſuch as be grieved; He would not that at any time they ſhould turn in prejudice of Himſelf, or of His Crown; but that ſuch Rights as appertain to Him, ſhould be ſaved in all points:</hi> Raſtal's Collection ibidem. Now the Actual Exerciſe of Juriſdiction Eccleſiaſtical, being that which by ſpecial Favour of our Kings is granted to the Biſhops after a very large and ample manner; if any thing therefore in that Grart, ſhould tend to the diminution of the Rights of the Crown, yet by the Statute before mentioned, theſe is ſtill a <hi>ſalvo</hi> to them in all reſpects whatſoever; ſo that in regard of His Majeſties Prerogative Royal, in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar branch of it, as well as in all the reſt, the Poſition before ſet down, does not, nay, cannot indeed infringe the ſame.</p>
            <p>I touched a little before the derivation of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Juriſdiction as to the executive part of it from the Crown: As every Biſhop at the time of his Conſecration, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es by Solemn Oath recognize the Kings Majeſty to be the onely Supreme Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor in this Realm, in all Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtical things and cauſes, as Temporal; and by receiving from the King a Patent of Reſtitution of His Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralities, is thereby inveſted with Actual Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (that is, a power to exerciſe and execute ſuch Juriſdiction, <hi>in foro externo &amp; contentioſo,</hi> in ſuch cauſes as belong thereto) ſo in the exerciſe and proceedings made in the ſame, he depends upon the King, from whom he derives his a thority and right to exerciſe: In all Appeals made to the King in His Chancery, He defers to him, as <hi>habenti Supremam authoritatem Eccleſiaſticam,</hi> being the chief and Supreme Ordinary; and, acquieſces in his final and ultimate deciſions.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:53134:23"/>
            <p>A little before, I mentioned a Grant of King <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, wherein great ſcope was given to Epiſcopal Juriſdiction; it is now proper to ſet down what that was, and this Hiſtorical account we may take thereof: By this King, an entire Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction was aſſigned to the Biſhops by themſelves, wherein they ſhould have cognizance of all matters and cauſes relating to Religion. It ſeems, by the Ancient <hi>Saxon</hi> Law, the Biſhops and Sheriffs jointly kept their Courts together at certain ſet times of the year; in the Conquerors time, theſe two Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions thus concurring, were parted aſunder: <hi>Fullers Church Hiſtory of Britain,</hi> Book 3. p. 5. from <hi>Eadmer,</hi> who lived in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, gives ſome account hereof <note n="*" place="margin">Spelman in Gloſſar. v. Hundredum.</note>: But I ſhall ſet down the ſame, in the words of a late, and a learned Writer, proper to the occaſion he was upon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conqueſtor porro Forum Eccleſiaſticum à Laico diſtinxit: Nam cum antea ſub Anglo-Saxonibus, ſingulis menſibus Aldermannus ſeu Praeſes unà cum Epiſcopo jus dixiſſent in Curia Centenaria, quam Hundredum dicimus, mandavit Epiſcopis &amp; Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaconis, ne deinceps jus dicant in Curia Centenaria ſed in loco per Epiſcopum deſignando, ibique judicent ſecundum Canones &amp; Leges Epiſcopales, &amp; contumaces contra corum mandata Excommunicationis ſententiâ, &amp; Brachio Regio parere cogantur, cum Praecepto Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitibus &amp; Praepoſitis Regiis dato, ne aliquem in jus vocent coram ſe de iis quae ad Forum Epiſcopalem ſpectant.</hi> Dr. Duck, de Authoritate Juris Civilis in Regno Angliae, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>ſect.</hi> 26. And in the margent of his Book, alledges <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Apud quem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> See this Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and fully declared; the ſame being granted and directed to</hi> Rhemigius, <hi>the firſt B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhop of</hi> Lincoln, <hi>ib.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Coke's Inſtit. p.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 54. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>ſect.</hi> 135. <hi>Char.</hi> 2. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. <hi>m.</hi> 1.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:53134:24"/>
            <p>By this it appears, how early the exerciſe of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction by Biſhops was on foot in the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and that as it derived it ſelf from the Crown; for beſides this diſtinct con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting of an Eccleſiaſtical Court from the Court of the Tourn, even before the ſeparation, before ſpoken of, was made; yet the Biſhops had then the judicial cognizance of Eccleſiaſtical cauſes and matters peculiarly reſerved to them, ſo it is plainly colligible from the Laws of King <hi>Edgar,</hi> among which this was one; <hi>Celeberimus autem ex omni Satrapia conventus his quotannis Agitor: cui quidem illius Dioceſeos Epiſcopus &amp; Aldermannus interſunto quorum alter jura divina, alter jura humana populum edoceto:</hi> Lord <hi>Coke</hi> on the Statute of <hi>Circumſpecte Agatis v. Curia Chriſtianitatis.</hi> I might yet trace Antiquity higher in this point, but my reading is too ſlender, and my opportunities too mean, that I ſhould think my ſelf able to give a punctual and exact Account thereof; Take notice only in brief, what the Pen of a learned Writer has ſet down—<hi>The</hi> Britiſh, Saxon, <hi>and</hi> Daniſh <hi>Kings, did uſually with their Clergy, or great Council, make Eccleſiaſtical Laws, and regulate the external Diſcipline of the Church within their Dominions: Among the Laws of King</hi> Edward <hi>the Confeſſor, theſe were two of them; one, that makes it the office of a King to govern the Church as the Vicar of God; another, ſuppoſes a paramount power in the King over the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, becauſe they were to take cognizance of wrong done in Eccleſiaſtical Courts:</hi> Archbiſhop <hi>Bramhall</hi>'s Vindication of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 67. King <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor was indeed after the time of King <hi>Edgar</hi> before mentioned; but taking
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53134:24"/>both together, and what was done by both, thence is ſhewed, that the practice of former Kings was followed by them; and that there was an Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Juriſdiction then and before exerciſed by Biſhops, which exerciſe thereof derived from, and was regulated by theſe and other preceding Kings of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which has been ſaid, makes very fair for our purpoſe, and points out to us to take notice of theſe ſeveral obſervable things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Exerciſe of Juriſdiction Eccleſiaſtical by Biſhops, in the right conſtitution thereof in the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> had no deperdance on <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That much of the intermediate practice in this kind, degenerated from its firſt and right inſtitution; and until the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, was a meer uſurpation and encreachment on the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Crown.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That whereas 'tis ſaid, The Biſhops were to judge <hi>ſecundum Canones &amp; Leges Epiſcopales,</hi> by Canons (I underſtand) the Canons of General and Provincial Councils abroad, eſpecially the firſt four General Councils, according as was Enacted by the Emperor <hi>Juſtinian, Authent. collat.</hi> 9. <hi>Novell.</hi> 131. <hi>cap. de Regulis. &amp; cap. Sancimus igitur:</hi> And by <hi>Leges Epiſcopales,</hi> I underſtand their Home-laws; I mean, the Eccleſiaſtical Laws made by the <hi>Britiſh, Saxon,</hi> and <hi>Daniſh</hi> Kings, with the Council of their Biſhops, variety of which may be found, by him that will conſult Sir <hi>Henry Spelman</hi>'s Councils. The body of the Canon Law was not then in being; my meaning is, it was not ſo as ſuch: The ſeveral particulars that the Decrees conſiſt, and were made up of, were indeed then and long before in being; but they were not compiled together, till near fourſcore years
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:53134:25"/>after this<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and that was done by <hi>Gratian</hi> the Monk, in the year (as ſome ſay, for there is much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the computation of this time) 11 49. (<hi>Ridley</hi>'s view, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 74.) And by <hi>Eugenius</hi> the third allowed to be read in the Schools, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>Of <hi>Greg.</hi> 9. ſet forth <hi>Anno</hi> 1230.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Decret. in ſexto Anno</hi> 1297.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Clementines</hi> of <hi>Clent.</hi> 5 ſet forth <hi>Anno</hi> 1317. And not long after, were extant the <hi>Extravagan's</hi> of <hi>John</hi> the 22d, and other Popes.</p>
               </note> and to be alledged for Law: And for the <hi>Decretals,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Clementines</hi> and <hi>Extravagants,</hi> they came in ſucceſſively along while after: Here, by the way, is ſeen the vanity and wildneſs of ſome mens fancies, that by all means will have Biſhops Courts to be of Pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh extraction; and, that both in their Erection and Conſtitution, they receive influence and authority from the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Conſittory: Than which, nothing is more untrue in its ſelf, and unhiſt or ical, as to the right deducing the primitive Inſtitution hereof (not to ſpeak of the Eaſtern Churches) even in the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This is alſo hence obſervable, That the preſent courſe commanded, and obſerved by the Biſhops in the Exerciſe of this Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, ſuits nearly with the ancient ſtate thereof; and is ſo far from damnifying the Prerogative Royal, that it mainly aſſerts and vindicates the ſame.</p>
            <p>It might perhaps be doubted, That different Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictions in one Kingdom, and thoſe exerciſed by perſons of different profeſſions, though deriving from one Supreme Head, would rather cauſe, than prevent many inconveniencies; and thoſe inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies ſo bad in their nature, as to detract from, rather than adde to the Supreme Magiſtrates Dignity and Prerogative; as namely, by introducing confuſion and diſorder in the management of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:53134:25"/>both, and in the cauſes and matters to be managed in them, and occaſioning continual jealouſies and diſtaſtes betwixt the perſons appointed to manage them, obſerved by my Lord <hi>Bacon</hi>'s Advancement of Learning, <hi>Aphor.</hi> 96. But, in truth, no ſuch ill Effects do follow hereupon; for diſtinct Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons exerciſed by perſons of ſeveral orders and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions in theſe Kingdoms, and veſted with autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from the Supreme Magiſtrates ſo to do (though juridical proceedings therein be different from the ordinary form and preſcribed courſel of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law) argues unplenitude, not a defect of power; an advancing of it, not derogating from it, in that Supreme Magiſtrate granting the ſame; his great wiſdom and prudence in a determinate ſtating the nature and bounds of each Juriſdiction; the appropriating certain cauſes to be heard and determined in them reſpectively, commanding all His Subjects to give due obedience thereunto, in ſuch cauſes as are limited to thoſe Courts, and which any Subject may be concerned in: And as both derive from, ſoito depend upon him, in an equal poiſe as to the Authority belonging to each; ſo that all the ſuppoſed inconveniencies are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently provided againſt: And the ordering all theſe things in this ſet manner, is an effect of the Kings high Prerogative enabling him ſo to do, and is both by Cuſtom and Law among us allowed of <note n="*" place="margin">The King is the indifferent Arbitrator in all Juriſdictions, as well Spiritual as Temporal, and it is a Right of His Crown to diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to them; that is, to declare their bounds: <hi>Lord</hi> Hobbarts <hi>Reports. Dr.</hi> Jame<hi>'s</hi> Caſe.</note>; obſerve with me theſe following inſtances.</p>
            <p>The Kings Majeſty is plyaſed to confirm a peculiar Juriſdiction granted by His Royal Progenitors, to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53134:26"/>the two Univerſities of <hi>Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Oxford:</hi> The Chancellor of each Univerſity, or his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, adminiſter Juſtice according to the Civil Law, and the Cuſtoms and Statutes of the Univerſity, where the perſons at variance together are Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, or one of them at leaſt is ſuch; inſomuch as in perſonal Actions for Debt, matters of Accounts, or any Contracts made within their own Precincts, and in ſome criminal matters likewiſe, none of them may be called to <hi>Weſtminſter Hall;</hi> but the cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance thereof belongs to the Chancellor of the ſaid Univerſity, or his Commiſſary, as is before ſaid. If any Appeals be made from Sentences given in any ſuch Trials, they are firſt interpoſed to the Regents, laſt of all to the Kings Majeſty himſelf: <hi>Cowell. Interp. in verbo (Privilege)</hi> Dr. <hi>Duck ut ſupra. ſect.</hi> 30. Will any man now ſay, That the Exerciſe of this power, is intrenching on the Kings Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, becauſe His great Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> are not applied to, and a Juriſdiction diſtinct from and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent upon them is exerciſed? Surely no, becauſe the Exerciſe of this power is granted by Royal Charter; it proceeds from, it depends upon, it is done in an acknowledgment of the Kings Supreme Power and Prerogative.</p>
            <p>There is a Court of great Dignity and Honour, called the Court of the Conſtable and Earl Marſhal of <hi>England:</hi> Herein are determined all Contracts touching Deeds of Arms out of the Realm, as Combats, Blazons of Armory, and the right of bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Arms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> proper to particular Families; the manner of proceeding in this Court, is according to the form of the Civil Law <note n="*" place="margin">L. <hi>Coke</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of Courts. <hi>ca.</hi> 17.</note>, the uſe and authority of which, is of great ſway herein: Appeals that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:53134:26"/>are interpoſed from any definitive ſentence in this Court, are brought to the Kings Majeſty Himſelf, not to His Chancellor, the municipal Law is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſecluded from hence; Juſtice is admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, Delinquents are puniſhed, without any relation to that, or the Judges thereof; yet the Kings Prerogative is not infringed by the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of this Juriſdiction, becauſe it is derived from the King.</p>
            <p>I might add here the Court of the Admiralty, the peculiar Juriſdiction exerciſed within the Cinque Ports by the Lord Warden thereof: In theſe Courts, matters both civil and criminal are tryed according to the courſe preſcribed by the civil Law; but in the following Leafs I ſhall have occaſion more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly to write ſomething relating to theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and reſpectively to theſe two Courts. Now as it is in theſe different Juriſdictions they derive from the King, His Subjects are bound by command from Him, to obey the Authority thereof; if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to obey, by poenal coercions proper to each, they may be compelled to it; yet ſtill the Royal Prerogative is not any whit diminiſhed, nor the Rights of the Crown at all impaired hereby: As it is thus (I ſay) in the diſtinct Juriſdictions, ſo it is in the exerciſe of Epiſcopal Juriſdiction in the Eccleſiaſtical Courts.</p>
            <p>And now I have uttered thus much, I perceive my ſelf beginning to walk on a narrow, ſlippery ridge, where a ſteep precipice is on each ſide. The danger of falling on one hand, is, leaſt I abaſe the Prerogative ſo low, as to ſubject the King in Eccleſiaſtical cauſes and matters under the Reſolves and Deciſions of Claſſical Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Huic Diſciplinae omnes orhis principes &amp; Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas faſers ſuos ſubmittere &amp; parere neceſſe eſt</hi> Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. Diſciplin. Eccleſiaſt. p. 142, 143. <hi>Biſhop</hi> White <hi>in his Preface to his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe concerning the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</hi>
               </note>,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:53134:27"/>as the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> do; or bring Him in ſubordination to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> do. The danger on the other hand, is the over-exalting of the Prerogative, ſo that it might be thought we attribute to the King (as ſometimes the <hi>Papiſts</hi> object to us) a power to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe Sacerdotal Offices in the Church, to inflict cenſures <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>And yet our Law attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes much in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and that very highly to the King:</hi> Reges Sacro olco unct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpiritualis Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſunt capaces. 33 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>Ayde de Roy.</hi> 107. <hi>Coke.</hi> Cawdrie's caſe. <hi>p.</hi> 16.</note>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to walk even and ſteddy betwixt theſe two dangerous downfalls, is that which muſt be endeavoured; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whereas we own, and ſolemnly recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize the Kings Supremacy in Eccleſiaſtical matters and cauſes, it is to be underſtood according to the ſenſe and meaning ſet down in the words of the 37th Article of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and alſo in the Article of the Church of <hi>Ireland</hi> concerning civil Magiſtrates. The Kings Majeſty hath the chief Government of all Eſtates Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical and Civil within His Dominions, ſee Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Injunctions ſet forth in the firſt year of Her Reign. Now this Supremacy keeps the King above all others within His own Kingdoms; and, it keeps Him from a ſubordination either to the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery</hi> or the <hi>Papacy;</hi> and it is ſuch a Supremacy as is only <hi>Political</hi> and <hi>Architectonical</hi> (as it is phraſed) that is, <hi>a power paramount over all His Subjects, to ſee that each ſort of ſuch as are under His Government, as well Eccleſiaſticks, as others, do their duties in their ſeveral and reſpective ſtations; and that all things be acted by proper and fit Agents, for preſerving both Church and State in tranquility and ſafety.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:53134:27"/>
            <p>Thus it appears, that nothing either belonging to Eccleſiaſtical Order or Juriſdiction, is exerciſed by our Kings in their own perſons, according as is fully declared in the following parts of the ſaid Article. Neither does this give any countenance to <hi>Eraſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm,</hi> as ſome have (improperly enough) inferred from thence; herein, as has been deſcribed, is ſeen the Kings Supremacy: <hi>By it, He is the Keeper of both Tables; He governs and regulates Affairs ſo both in Church and State, as may beſt conduce to the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of true Piety to God, and right Juſtice to Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From this power paramount and Supremacy, does deſcend the Biſhops power of exerciſing Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; that is, exerciſing the ſame actually; I ſay, actually: for, as our Divines do diſtinguiſh (Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop <hi>Bramhall</hi>'s anſwer to <hi>R.C.</hi> p. 160, 161. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Sanderſon de conſcient. obligat. praelect. 7. ſect.</hi> 29, 30. Biſhop <hi>Bilſon of Subjection,</hi> par. 3. p. 293. <hi>in octavo.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hooker Eccleſ. Pol. B.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 213, &amp;c.) <hi>There is an habitual, and there is an actual Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; habitual Juriſdiction flows from Epiſcopal Order, actual Juriſdiction,</hi> is <hi>a Right</hi> and liberty granted, opportunity and means afforded of exerciſing and reducing that habit into act; and that, <hi>in foro ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terno &amp; contentioſo,</hi> after a certain and peculiar manner appointed therein. Thus the King has His Eccleſiaſtical Laws, and His Eccleſiaſtical Courts, and His Eccleſiaſtical Judges <note n="*" place="margin">See Sir <hi>Joh. Davies</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports. <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire verſus finem.</hi>
               </note>; there are cauſes of ſuch and ſuch a Nature appointed by the King to be judged of by them, in thoſe Courts, according to thoſe Laws <note n="*" place="margin">Many things the Popes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken upon them to give dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of, and Enact Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Epiſcopal Juriſdiction (under this <hi>ſalvo</hi>) <hi>in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ad spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alia:</hi> which things are matters meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of civil intercourſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce betwixt man and man; ſuch are thoſe titles in the Canon Law, <hi>de emptione &amp; venditione, de rerum permutatione, de tranſactionibus, de depeſito,</hi> &amp;c. Teſtamentary and Matrimonial, and Decimal matters, are amongſt theſe likewiſe; but although theſe may better ſeem to have the aſpect of matters ſpiritual, yet that ſpiritual men have any Juriſdiction therein, muſt not be imputed to the nature of the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, nor to any ſuperiority that they have over other men by reaſon of them; but this muſt be imputed to the Roval bounty and munificence of pious Kings; who, for the Honor of the Church, have ſo ordered thoſe Cauſes to be of Eccleſiaſtical cognizance, and that their Subjects concerned therein, ſhould be obedient to Eccleſiaſtical Judges therein. Hereupon a Learned Biſhop declares, That the Popes Decrees, Judgments and Executions in theſe Caſes, if claimed from Chriſt as things ſpiritual, and not granted by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> are but open invaſions of Princes Rights, calling thoſe things Spiritual, which indeed be Civil and Temporal. Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi>'s Chriſtian Subjection, <hi>page</hi> 2. Sir <hi>Robert Wiſeman,</hi> The Law of Laws.</note>: All perſons within their reſpective Dioceſſes (that is, certain circuits and precincts of Juriſdiction by the King ſet out to each Biſhop, and thoſe in their bounds and limits, either to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:53134:28"/>or extended, as He pleaſes) are command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be ſubject to them; if they refuſe, may bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſtrained to it. In matters of Appeal, the laſt complaint is ever to be made to Him; He is the final and ultimate Judge, who by fit Delegates ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed thereunto, does redreſs grievances, anſwer complaints, and finally and abſolutely determine what is brought before Him. The Learned Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop and Primate of all <hi>Ireland,</hi> a little before mentioned, has given a full and ſatisfactory Account of this matter; his words are theſe, worthy our beſt obſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neither do we draw or derive any ſpiritual Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction from the Crown, but either liberty and power to exerciſe actually and lawfully upon the Subjects of the Crown that habitual Juriſdiction which we received at our Ordination; or the enlargement of our Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction objectively by the Princes referring more cauſes to the cognizance of the Church; than formerly it had: or laſtly, the increaſe of it ſubjectively, by their giving to Eccleſiaſtical Judges, an external coercive power which before they had not. To go yet one ſtep higher, in caſes that are indeed ſpiritual, or meerly Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:53134:28"/>ſuch as concorn the Doctrine of Faith, or Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Sacraments, or the ordering or degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Eccleſiaſtical perſons, Sovereign Princes have (and have only) an Architectonical power, to ſee that Clergy men do their Duties in their proper places; but this power is alwayes moſt properly exerciſed by the advice and miniſtry of Eccleſiaſtical perſons; and ſometimes neceſſary, as in the degradation of one in Holy Orders by Eccleſiaſtical Delegates:</hi> Vindication of the Church of <hi>England</hi> from Schiſm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Exerciſe of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops thus being ſtated and ſetled in the likeneſs that it carries with the other inſtances before ſet down, neither invades not impairs, but much advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and amplifies the Kings Prerogative. It comes to paſs indeed by this means, that the Kings Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy is preſerved firm and ſafe in the Eccleſiaſtical Polity.</p>
            <p>I know a great Objection is made againſt all this from hence, becauſe that in Eccleſiaſtical proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Citations, Decrees, and other inſtruments, iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue forth in the Biſhops, but not in the Kings Name; whence would be infer'd, That ſuch attempts and judiciary proceedings, made, not in the Kings Name, are invaſive on the Royal Prerogative. In order to the Anſwering of this Objection, let it be obſerved, That there are two great Offices in the Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> the one, that of the Lord High Admiral; the other, that of the Lord War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the Onque Ports: Theſe have great infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in foreign parts, upon the Sea, and within the Lands. I before gave you ſome intimation of their diſtinct Juriſdiction and manner of juriſdical proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, different from the Courts of the Common
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:53134:29"/>Law: Both the juriſdictions of theſe two great Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers are ample and authoritative, yet both the Lord Admiral, and the Lord Warden of the Cinque Ports, do ſend forth Writs in their own Names, and they do it (ſayes Dr. <hi>Cowell in verbo, Court.</hi>) as the Biſhops hold their Courts by the Kings Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity <hi>(virtute Magiſtratus ſui)</hi> In the High Court of the Earl Maiſhal the ſame practice is obſerved. In the Univerſities, Proceſſes, and Writs, iſſue forth in the Chancellor, Vice-chancellor, or their Commiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Name. Will any now preſume to challenge any of theſe juriſdictions for invading the Kings Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative? Will any dare to ſay, That they pare off ſome rights, or pluck ſome flowers from the Kings Imperial Crown? I ſuppoſe not. How comes it to paſs then, that the Biſhops juriſdiction does? What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever may be alledged in defence of the other, may be ſaid (and it may be ſomething more too) in juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of this: And know moreover, That pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in theſe Temporal diſtinct juriſdictions go much further upon the perſons of men, than thoſe of any Eccleſiaſtical Court does, even to the impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning of them, and in all of them (except that of the Univerſity) to the inflicting of capital puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And it deſerves our further obſerving, what the great Lawyer Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> ſayes touching this very thing. Albeit the proceedings and proceſs in the Eccleſiaſtical Courts be in the Name of the Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It followeth not therefore, that either the Court is not the Kings, or that the Law where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they proceed, is not the Kings Law; for taking one example for many, every Leet and View of franck pledge holden by a ſubject, is kept in the Lords Name, and yet it is the Kings Court, and all
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:53134:29"/>the proceedings therein are directed by the Kings Laws; and many ſubjects in <hi>England</hi> have and hold Courts of Record, and other Courts, and yet all their proceedings be according to the Kings Laws and cuſtoms of the Realm, <hi>De jure Regis Eccleſ. p.</hi> 39. The Learned Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> has convincingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated, That Citations and Decrees in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Name, no way encroacheth on the Kings Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; and that they who urge the contrary have this meaning, rather to do the Biſhops hurt, than the King ſervice, and that their affections (ſo far as by what is viſible we are able to judge) are much what alike towards both: <hi>His Book called Epiſcopacy not prejudicial to Regal power, p.</hi> 3, 4. Biſhops pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in Eccleſiaſtical Courts under the Name, Stile, and Seal of the Biſhop. See this largely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed and declared to be warrantable by Law, by my Lord <hi>Coke's comment on the Statute of Marriage,</hi> 32 Hen. 8. p. 685, 686, 687.</p>
            <p>But this Objection is taken up again, and urged with new force from hence; That in the Firſt year of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, it was by Statute Enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That the Biſhops ſhould make their proceſſes in the Kings Name, and that their Seals ſhould be the Kings Arms. This Statute, ſayes Mr. <hi>Raſtall,</hi> was repealed 1 Mariae 1. <hi>And that Statute not being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived by Queen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>in her Reign, all proceeded well enough without danger: But in the firſt Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of King</hi> James, <hi>there paſſed an Act for continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and reviving divers Statutes, and for repealing of ſome others,</hi> 1 Jaccb. <hi>c.</hi> 29. <hi>Into the body where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a clauſe was cunningly conveyed, for the repealing of that Statute of the Reign of Queen</hi> Mary, <hi>by which King</hi> Edward<hi>'s ſtood repealed:</hi> Upon this account it
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:53134:30"/>was, that a little before our late turbulent confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in <hi>England,</hi> this very thing was urged againſt the Biſhops, and their proceedings were declared to be bold uſurpations, and encroachments on the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Royal, and violations of the Law.</p>
            <p>But as it is uſual, where men are prepoſſeſſed againſt any thing, they are apt to run into many miſtakes about the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me: It happened ſo in this very matter; Much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lſe was raiſed, much ſtir made here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon by the Anti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>prelatical party; as if the Biſhops who had given themſelves out to be the moſt zeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous aſſertors, were indeed become the onely dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous impugners of the Kings Prerogative: That now they were deprehended in the very deſign, and therefore muſt needs fall, having no plea to make for themſelves, and having the miſchief of their own viſible and illegal actings witneſſing againſt them. At this rate, their Adverſaries vaunted, and fore-judged them; and no doubt, (as matters went in thoſe times) the ſevereſt animadverſion that could have followed hereupon, would have been made, if further proceedings therein had not been ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly prevented by the wiſdom of a pious and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Prince.</p>
            <p>For the Bleſſed King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, having beee made acquainted, what advantage theſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and buſie people were deſigning to make hereof, to the overthrow of His Eccleſiaſtical Courts, and the Biſhops His Judges in them. He did (as Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> reports in the life of Archbiſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> p. 342.) call together in the year 1637, the two Lords Chief Juſtices, the Lord Chief Baron, and the reſt of the Judges and Barons, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds to them theſe three following particulars to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:53134:30"/>be certified of. 1. Whether proceſſes may not iſſue out of the Eccleſiaſtical Courts in the Name of the Biſhops. 2. Whether a Patent under the Great Seal be neceſſary for the keeping of Eccleſiaſtical Courts, and enabling Citations, Suſpenſions, Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and other cenſures of the Church. 3. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Citations ought to be in the Kings Name, and under His Seal of Arms: And the like for Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Inductions to Benefices, and corrections of Eccleſiaſtical Offences: And the like for Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whether an expreſs Commiſſion or Patent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Great Seal of <hi>England</hi> were requiſite?</p>
            <p>To which three Propoſals, the ſaid Judges unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly on the Firſt of <hi>July</hi> in the fore mentioned year concurred, and certified under their Hands: By Anſwering to the Firſt thing propounded, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matively; and to the other two, negatively: And that the fore-mentioned Statute of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, is not now in force: Whereupon, the King iſſues out His Proclamation, wherein having firſt taxed the libellous Books and Pamphlets, publiſhed againſt the Biſhops; and after a recital made of theſe proceedings, He concludes the Proclamation thus—<hi>That His Majeſtie thought good, with the advice of His Council, that a publick Declaration of theſe the opinions of His Reverend and Learned Judges, being agreeable to the judgement and reſolution of former times, ſhould be made known to all His Subjects, as well to vindicate the legal proceedings of His Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Courts, and Miniſters, from the unjuſt and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous imputation of invading or intrenching on His Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Prerogative, as to ſettle the minds, and ſtop the mouths of all unquiet ſpirits: That for the future, they preſume not to cenſure His Eccleſiaſtical Courts, or
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53134:31"/>Miniſters, in theſe their juſt and warranted proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. And hereof His Majeſty admoniſheth all His ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to take warning, as they will Anſwer the contrary at their peril,</hi> &amp;c. <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Reſolutions unanimouſly given by all the Judges and the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons of the Exchequer (ſaith my Lord</hi> Coke.) <hi>are for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Law of Higheſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, next unto the Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Sir</hi> Edward Coke 2 <hi>Inſtit. p.</hi> 618.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But ſome mens minds will not be ſatisfied with any thing of this nature, yet are willing to embrace what is fortified with Parliamentary Authority. Both therefore to gratifie them, and more through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to confirm the matter in hand, we have alſo this Parliamentary Authority to offer unto them: For although by an Act of Parliament in the Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth year of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, all jurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Eccleſiaſtical was quite abrogated and annulled, (I ſpeak in reſpect of <hi>England;</hi> for here in <hi>Ireland</hi> no ſuch Act was ever made) nevertheleſs at the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Reſtauration of our Gracious Sovereign that now is, <hi>viz. Anno Dom.</hi> 1660. The ſaid Act of the 17. of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt is repealed; and that was <hi>Anno decimo tertio</hi> Caroli <hi>Secundi;</hi> and in that Act of Repeal it is thus declared— That the ſaid Act of the 17. of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. <hi>All Archbiſhops, Biſhops, and all others exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing Eccleſiaſtical jurisdiction, may proceed, determine, ſentence, execute and exerciſe all manner of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal juriſdiction, and all cenſures and coercions appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and belonging to the ſame, before the making of the Act before recited, in all cauſes and matters belonging to Eccleſiaſtical jurisdiction, according to the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Eccleſiaſtical Laws, uſed and practiſed in this Realm, in as ample manner &amp; form, as they did &amp; might lawfully have done before the making of the ſaid Act.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Act is indeed attended with three Proviſoes. The firſt is concerning the High-commiſſion Court, which is excepted from having any revival, or force,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:53134:31"/>or authority given to it, or to the erection of any other ſuch like Court by commiſſion hereby. The ſecond Proviſo is concerning the Oath, called the Oath <hi>ex Officio,</hi> which is excepted againſt, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid to be tendred, or adminiſtred unto any in the exerciſing of any Spiritual jurisdiction. The third Proviſo is, to limit and confine the power of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Judges in all their proceedings, to what was, and by Law might be uſed before the year 1639. (obſerve the year mentioned to be 1639, which plainly includes, allows, and confirms King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt His Proclamation, in the year 1637. In this clauſe and branch of this Statute, proviſion is alſo made againſt any confirmation to be given to the Canons, made <hi>Anno</hi> 1640.</p>
            <p>Theſe particulars onely excepted, and here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided againſt all Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, as to it's exſtenſiveneſs in all cauſes of Spiritual cognizance, &amp; over all perſons (of what quality and degree ſoever they be, or in what Office ſoever they are) in thoſe cauſes, is firmly ratified and eſtabliſhed. <hi>Bartolus</hi> his Rule is truly applicable here, <hi>Exceptio firmat Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam in non-exceptis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let all this be granted (will the Excepters ſay) that proceedings in Eccleſiaſtical Courts againſt private perſons, either in matters of inſtance, or correction, are not entrenching on the Prerogative Royal; yet the caſe is otherwiſe, when ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings are bent upon publick Officers, as Mayors, and Sheriffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe they are veſted with the Kings Authority, and nearly repreſent His Perſon. They are His Miniſters and Diſpenſers of Juſtice, and by ſuch proceedings againſt them, publick af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs might be hindred of their diſpatch, and the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:53134:32"/>Kings buſineſs not be executed. I Anſwer, (there is no otherwiſe in this caſe) For, if the matter be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifiable, that is, if the cauſe any ſuch proceeding is begun upon, do belong to Eccleſiaſtical cognizance, then the Spiritual Juriſdiction in the Biſhops manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment reaches ſuch publick Officers, as well as others, and that without invading, or in the leaſt violating the Kings Prerogative: If occaſions ſo require, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical cenſures may be inflicted on them, as well as on any other of the Kings ſubjects that do of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend. And yet the doing of that will not be a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring the King <hi>in Effigie,</hi> as ſome have, with very little reaſon, and but too much paſſion affirmed. Obſerve we what may be done, and adjuged againſt ſuch publick Officers, in the Kings Temporal Courts.</p>
            <p>A Mayor and Sheriffs may be impleaded before the Kings Temporal Judges in cauſes Civil. The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Waterford</hi> may remember one or two inſtances hereof very lately; when the School-maſter there ſued the Mayor and Sheriffs, before the Lords Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of Aſſize, for detaining the Salary they had contracted to pay him. A Mayor of any City or Corporation, may be arreſted, may, during the time of his Mayoralty, be ſued to an Out-lawry in the Kings Temporal Courts. The Kings Temporal Judges may upon contempts, convent Mayors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; and occaſion ſo requiring, commit them to priſon. It is not long ſince that a caſe in <hi>Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> was coming near this, when in one <hi>Whaley</hi>'s cauſe, a Writ of Error was brought from the Court of the Kings Bench: This the Mayor refuſing to obey, and complaint thereof being made to the Court, a Purſuivant was ordered to attach the Mayor,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:53134:32"/>and bring him before the Judges, there to anſwer his contempt; which undoubtedly would have been done, if the Execution of that Order had not been ſeaſonably prevented, by an <hi>Affidavit</hi> made to this effect, That the Mayor did not refuſe to obey the ſaid Writ of Error, but onely deferred the admitting of it, until he ſate judicially in Court; the ſame having been before privately exhibited to him. By this means that proceeding was ſtopped, which elſe would have manifeſted, that the Mayor of <hi>Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> is not ſo abſolute, but is indeed under controll, and may be convented and puniſhed by the Kings temporal Judges, without any affront done to the King <hi>in Effigie,</hi> or to his power and authority; which he the ſaid Mayor in his proper ſtation, and within his own Precinct does bear.</p>
            <p>And that Sheriffs even while they are in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their Office, may be proceeded againſt in the Kings Temporal Courts, none can be ignorant of, that underſtands the practice of thoſe Courts, and remembers there is ſuch a Court as the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, or has undergone the Office of a Sheriff: A Sheriff, by the Statute of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no tertio Edvardi primi,</hi> for not doing his Duty, and for concealing of Felons, may be fined and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned. One <hi>Bronchard</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time being Sheriff, had an Information Exhibited in the Star-chamber againſt him, for returning one that was not choſen a Knight of the Parliament, <hi>Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Reports of the Lord</hi> Dyer, 425. A She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff of <hi>Barkſhire</hi> was committed to the Fleet, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Court of <hi>Common Pleas</hi> for unjuſt taking of Fees: <hi>Brownloes Reports, ſecond part,</hi> p. 283. I doubt not, but the Learned in the Municipal Laws,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:53134:33"/>are able to furniſh out plenty of inſtances of this kind.</p>
            <p>Well then, Mayors and Sheriffs may be Implead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, may be Out-lawed, may be Arreſted, may be Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, may be Impriſoned in the Kings Temporal Courts, by, from, and before his Temporal Judges: And in all theſe Inflictions, here's no Fining, no Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſting, no Out-lawing, no Impriſoning, no Atta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the King <hi>in Effigie,</hi> nor any intrenching upon his Authority from himſelf to his ſubordinate civil Officers: Here's no hindring the diſpenſing of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, no obſtructing the Kings buſineſs, nor letting the execution of His Majeſties ſervice in the hands of theſe publick Officers; that is, at all dreaded hereby. And pray, How then comes it to paſs, that the caſe is not the ſame, when in matters of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal cognizance, the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Judge in his Eccleſiaſtical Courts proceeds againſt ſuch perſons, by penalties proper and uſually inflicted therein? Is not the Kings Authority in His Eccleſiaſtical Courts in matters belonging to them, as forcible and coercive reſpectively to the manner of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings therein, as the ſame Regal Authority is in the temporal Courts in matters belonging to them, and reſpectively to the manner of proceedings therein? The King hath both Juriſdictions united in Him (as has been largely before ſhewed) <hi>Rex habet omnia jura in manu ſua:</hi> It is a Maxim concerning the King, which I read cited from <hi>Bracton, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 24. <note n="*" place="margin">So it is alſo ſaid, <hi>Rex eſt mixta perſona quia tum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticam turn tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem habet.</hi> 11 Hen. 7.12.</note> Now all is completed in theſe two Juriſdictions, which although they may be diverſe, yet they are not contrary in him; they are both radically and fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentally in him, and derivatively only in all Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Miniſters of Juſtice in either kind. Is the King then abſolute in the one, and yet limited
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:53134:33"/>in the other? leſs powerful in his Eccleſiaſtical, than in his civil Supremacy? That is, Supreme, and not Supreme: Thus to ſay, is either to contradict ones ſelf, or neither better nor worſe than plainly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate from the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Supremacy; and to give him the Name, but to deny the Thing: It incurs the danger of implied, if not direct diſown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Regal Supremacy in all cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, and over all perſons that may be concerned therein. It is plainly to make a <hi>magis</hi> and <hi>minus</hi> in that Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which will not admit any ſuch thing <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Regia dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas eſt indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſibilis.</hi> Coke 4 Inſtit. c. 48.</note>, it being alwayes equally and alike forcible in all; that is, chief and ſupreme in both Adminiſtrations, Eccleſiaſtical and Civil. Let's ſtate a Caſe or two for better il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtration ſake.</p>
            <p>A Suit is commenced in the Eccleſiaſtical Court, before the Biſhop the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Judge pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding therein, concerning a matter (we will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) not properly cognizable there: The Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant hereupon ſues out a Prohibition, which he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibits before the Biſhop, the Eccleſiaſtical Judge. This the Biſhop refuſes to admit, and notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame, proceeds in the cauſe. Complaint hereof being made to the Court granting the ſaid Prohibition, an Attachment is awarded againſt the Eccleſiaſtical Judge
<note n="*" place="margin">It may be ſo, and iſſues out of the Chance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Prohibition came from the King, Bench, or Common Pleas. <hi>Lord Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e. cap.</hi> 8. 4 <hi>Inſtit.</hi>
               </note>: He is apprehended, and brought to anſwer for his contempt, in refuſing to obey the Kings Prohibition. I queſtion not now, but to have a free concurrency of every mans vote, allowing this to be very legal and juſt, becauſe the Kings Authority in the Temporal Court, and in ſuch matters as belong thereunto, is, in this caſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned and diſobeyed, and therefore ought to be anſwered for by the contemners of it.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:53134:34"/>
            <p>Now invert the caſe a little: A Biſhop, the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Judge, convents before him in the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Court, a perſon bearing ſome civil Office, ſuppoſe the Mayor of a Corporation, or ſome Sheriff of a County, perhaps at the inſtance of a party, perhaps in a matter of correction. This Mayor or Sheriff refuſes to appear upon the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moning; or appearing, refuſes to obey ſuch Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions as are given him by the Biſhop; and for his contempt therein, has a cenſure inflicted on him. Tell me, now, ought not this caſe be allowed as le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal and juſt as the other? The reaſon is certainly the ſame, becauſe the Kings Authority in his Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Court and matters belonging thereunto is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, and diſobeyed, and therefore ought to be anſwered for by the contemners of it; and if the reaſon be the ſame, partiality or prejudice may make a diſparity; but in the true nature of the thing there is none at all: For the Kings Authority being equally committed to both ſpiritual and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Judge, in the concernancy of ſuch things as belong to each; the violaters and contemners of either (be they of what quality and condition ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever) are juſtly puniſhable by thoſe in either Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, who are veſted with Authority reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively for executing the ſame.</p>
            <p>But there are thoſe who will not be ſatified with all this; and that they may not ſeem to be without ſome grounds, they are not without their Objections againſt it: It will therefore be very pertinent to the preſent deſign, to free our former Aſſertion from ſuch Inferences as hence may be made contrary to it. The Aſſertion was this, That the Exerciſe of Epiſcopal Juriſdiction over perſons in Office of civil
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:53134:34"/>power and truſt, is not any way intrenching up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or infringing His Majeſties Prerogative Royal. To this, there is firſt oppoſed that Branch and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Statute of <hi>Clarenaon,</hi> of which we find mention made by <hi>Matth. Paris,</hi> in his Hiſtory of the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, the <hi>chapter</hi> that begins thus
[<hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1164.] in theſe words, <hi>Nullus qui de Rege tenet in capite, nec aliquis Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum Miniſtrorum ejus Excommunicetur, nec alicujus eorum terrae ſub interdicto ponantur, niſi prius Dominus Rex, ſi in Regno fuerio, conveniatur, vei juſtitiarius ejus, ſi fuerit extra Regnum, ut rectum de eo faciat: Et ita, ut quod pertinebat ad Regis Curiam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bi termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur: Et de eo quod ſpectat ad Curiam Eccleſiaſticam ad eandem mittatur, ut ibidem terminetur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I did a little before, and do now again acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, That the King of <hi>England</hi> may by His Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Royal, when and to whom he pleaſes, give exemption from Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction: But that He has done it to perſons in ſubordinate Offices of civil power, is not proved from this inſtance; all the diſpute will be, who are comprehended under this expreſſion <hi>(Dominicorum Miniſtrorum)</hi> what kind, and ſort of perſons are pointed at thereby: And here I ſay plainly, that perſons in ſubordinate Offices of civil power, are not theſe <hi>Dominici Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtri Regis.</hi> My Lord <hi>Cokes</hi> Expoſition hereof, is my warrantry and authority for ſaying ſo <note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>p. Inſtit.</hi> Expoſition on the 12th Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Statute called, <hi>Articuli Cleri.</hi> 9 Ed. 2.</note>. The place I refer to in the Margent, will inform us, That <hi>Dominici Miniſtri Regis,</hi> are ſuch as belonged to the Kings Houſhold, as the <hi>Tenentes de Capite,</hi> are ſuch, as held of the King by <hi>Grand Serjeanty,</hi> and <hi>Knights ſervice,</hi> and were to give their attendance on the Kings perſon whenſoever required thereto. To theſe
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:53134:35"/>is this exemption granted; but note here withall, that the exemption in this Statute is not abſolute, but proceeds with a reſerve and a limitation; that if the cauſe, any ſuch perſon is to be convented up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be judged by the King, or His Juſtice in the Kings abſence to belong to the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Court,</hi> thither both cauſe and perſon muſt be ſent, and that perſon (notwithſtanding ſuch exemption) be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt, and that cauſe there be determined. That which is in the principal aim and proviſion of this Statute, is this, that the King be made acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before any cenſures be inflicted on any account, upon any of His ſervants and attendants.</p>
            <p>But there is ſomething further objected (and that ſuppoſed to be more forcible) by a late Author, who has put himſelf to the expence of a great deal of labour and induſtry, in ſearching out of ſome preſidents, and (as he conceives) warrantable Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities whereby to evince the limiting and bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of Epiſcopal Juriſdiction, in reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons veſted with ſecular power, and command; namely, that ſuch perſons are by peculiar (and that Regal) exemption freed from all coercive authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thereof. Among other things produced by him, I pitch eſpecially on two, which appear to have the greateſt ſtreſs laid upon them. The one is an anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Record in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, of this Tenor. The Proveſt of <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> had been Excommunicated by the Archbiſhop of <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> without the Kings Licence; whereupon, King <hi>Henry</hi> writes to that Archbiſhop, and ſharply expoſtulates with him, <hi>That he had Excommunicated His Provoſt without his Licence, and commands him forthwith to abſolve him.</hi> Upon the like account, ſaith the ſame
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:53134:35"/>Author, King <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt, <hi>Clauſ.</hi> 8. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>Dorſ.</hi> 6. and <hi>Clauſ.</hi> 31. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>Dorſ.</hi> 11. iſſued out Writs to his Biſhops, commanding them not to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate his Bayliffs and Officers (and abſolve them, if Excommunicated) without his previous Licence and Order. Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi>'s Animadverſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> on the fourth part of Sir <hi>Ed. Coke's Inſtit.</hi> p. 404.</p>
            <p>At a diſtant view of theſe inſtances produced, they may ſeem to have a goodly appearance, and to ſerve well the end intended in their production; but come we to a nearer inſpection, and more narrow examination thereof, and they will be found weak and uſeleſs for any ſuch purpoſe. Let it be granted, that by Bayliffs are underſtood Sheriffs, and other Officers in ſecular Authority, ſuch as have the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in Corporations, as Mayors, Portrives <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gloſſar</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of <hi>Mat. Paris,</hi> printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1640.</note>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet I make no doubt to affirm, that ſtill the former Aſſertion ſtands firm and unſhaken. To make good this, a little recourſe muſt be had to other Hiſtorical occurrences in the Reigns of theſe two Kings, <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and his ſon and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor <hi>Edward</hi> 1. For theſe will give us the beſt light and guidance to diſcover the grounds wherefore, and and the matters wherein, theſe prohibitory Writs iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued out, and the ends aimed at by them. It has been ſaid, that that Age was the very <hi>Criſis</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, and Papal power in the Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> then was the ſharpeſt conflict betwixt both, and thence forward the Papal power began to dwindle and decline: And as a diſeaſe makes the ſharpeſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault upon Nature, immediately before it begins to abate; ſo did the Papal power at this time before its declenſion. The exerciſe of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, did then <hi>de facto</hi> derive from, and was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:53134:36"/>upon the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> and ſo it came to paſs, that the ſpiritual Court, or Court Chriſtian, was reputed <hi>aliud forum à foro Regio;</hi> and King <hi>Henry</hi> the third experienced many attempts made to limit, and reſtrain his Prerogative, inſomuch, as with great inſolence, his Biſhops threatned to Excommunicate Him
<note n="*" place="margin">Sir <hi>Richard Bakers</hi> Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle, the Reign of <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 3d.</note>. They were propt up and ſupported by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Authority, and after ſuch a daring and confident manner were they inſpirited from <hi>Rome,</hi> as to look upon themſelves in their actings utterly independent on the Crown; and then it was chiefly, that by the greatneſs and prevalency of <hi>Boniface</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Uncle to <hi>Elianor</hi> then Queen of <hi>England,</hi> that many Provincial conſtitutions were Enacted concerning matters of meer temporal cognizanced; and encroachments were daily made on the ſecular Courts, and Excommunications, and other cenſures were thundred out againſt the Kings Bayliffs and Officers: But why? only, becauſe they oppoſed them in the execution of ſuch conſtitutions. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon proceeded theſe prohibitions to the Biſhops; upon theſe grounds they were commanded not to cenſure ſuch Officers and Bayliffs; that is, for ſo exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting their Offices, and diſcharging their Allegiance, and Duty to their Princes. Here was no intent to reſtrain the Biſhops in the right exerciſe of their Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction touching ſuch matters as truly belonged to it, but to keep them from exceeding their own bounds, and medling in matters which were not cognizable before them.</p>
            <p>And thus much appears plainly from that clauſe in the very Record it ſelf (ſet down by this Author in the place before mentioned) <hi>Si vero Praepoſitus noſter aliquid deliquerit contra dignitatem Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:53134:36"/>faciemus cum juri parere, poſtquam delictum fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit nobis denuntiatum, pro quo interim eum abſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vi faciatis.</hi> So that here is no more than what the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Writs of prohibition do import. The King requires to be informed of the true ſtate of that cauſe his Officers are convented upon, ſo he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>equires to be in the caſe of any of his other Subjects, upon addreſs made to him concerning the ſame. If the matter be found to belong indeed to E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſiaſtical cognizance, the parties concerned therein be they in any office or place of power (ſo as belongs to the preſent caſe) they muſt be ſubject thereunto: But if the matter do not ſo belong, the King will reſcue them thence, and ſhield them with his Regal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and not ſuffer an incompetent Court to have any authority over them.</p>
            <p>But ſee the ill luck that this Author has in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging this Record, for whilſt he makes a ſhew of advancing the Kings Prerogative in one kind, he does really depreſs it in anothers I cannot contain my ſelf from calling upon the Reader, and deſiring him to obſerve, and then wonder, that any one ſhould inſiſt upon this Writ, as any way advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the thing he beſtirs himſelf to make good thereby, when it is ſaid in the very body of it in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the Biſhops—<hi>Non attendentes quod ab ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nariis locorum non poſſint Excommunicari Ballivi no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri, niſi de Exceſſibus eorum prius fuerit nobis relata querela propter ſedis Apoſtolicae nobis indultum privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legium.</hi> I wiſh the Reader would be at the pains to conſult the very Record, ſet down by this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor in the place of his Book, referred to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:53134:37"/>
            <p>And I pray, let any one conſider this adviſedly, and then tell me, What right does that man to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> that whil'ſt he appears mightily buſied in aſſerting the Supremacy thereof, will yet make it dependant on Papal Authority? Is it come to this, That the King of <hi>England</hi> muſt ask leave of the Pope to put any reſtraint upon his own Biſhops? The production of this Record makes better to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the Papiſts, than to prove the thing it is produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for; though, in truth, neither the one, nor the other, gets any real advantage hereby. Hiſtorians obſerve many miſcarriages in this Kings Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, during his long Reign of fifty and ſix years; among which, this application which he made to <hi>Rome,</hi> was not the leaſt: The moſt knowing of his Subjects were much diſpleaſed thereat; for, as one Hiſtorian informs us <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat. Paris.</hi> Anno 1250. p. 777.</note> (and he a Votary to the Pope) in another caſe hapning but two years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>viz.</hi> in the 36th year of this Kings Reign, and which this paſſage muſt undoub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edly refer to) <hi>Non ſine redargutione peritorum haec fecit Dominus Rex quod ſcilicet conqueſtus fuerit ſuper haec Domino Papae:</hi> The Pope to be ſure was forward enough to engage himſelf in the concerns of Princes, and ſo would make himſelf more officious to gratifie the King than was needful; whereas the proviſion which by the Laws was made againſt any ſuch encroachments, and the Kings own Regal power to put the ſame Laws in execution, would have given him better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, than any indult or diſpenſation from the Pope could do.</p>
            <p>Well, upon the Reaſons before ſpecified, prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitions iſſued out from King <hi>Henry,</hi> to keep the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops from cenſuring his Officers; but notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:53134:37"/>them, ſtill they would be encroaching on the Kings Rights in his temporal Courts, and ſo they continued to the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, the ſon and immediate ſucceſſor of the former King; and thence proceeded the iſſuing of that Kings pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitory mandates, <hi>Requiring and commanding the Biſhops not to Excommunicate his Bayliffs and Officers without his previous Licence and Order:</hi> That is (as by what is to be collected from the ſtate of affairs in theſe times) until the King fully underſtood the nature of the cauſe theſe Officers and Bayliffs were convented upon; for, as I declared before, they were often cenſured and excommunicated, becauſe they oppoſed the Popiſh encroachments on the Kings temporal Rights; therefore the King would underſtand the true grounds of ſuch proceedings, that if the matter were of civil concernment, his Officers might be freed from ſuch vexatious and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt proſecutions; but if it appeared to be of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical cognizance, they were then delivered up to the Juriſdiction thereof.</p>
            <p>This, I conceive, to be the very genuine and true meaning hereof, for theſe reaſons; firſt, becauſe it is conſonant to the end and purport of other Writs of the like nature; the Author has not recited theſe Records at large, which if he had done, very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably ſomething plainly directing to this concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might have been found therein. Moreover, by the Statute called <hi>prohibitio formata de Statuto Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi Cleri</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Which Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Articles of the Clergy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed in Parl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ament, hold <hi>Anno</hi> 51. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3.</note>, made the beginning of King <hi>Edwards</hi> Reign: The ſpiritual Juriſdiction is not at all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained ſubjectively, that is, reſpectively to perſons being of this or that condition or quality; but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly objectively as to cauſes, namely, ſuch as had been
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:53134:38"/>uſurped before by the ſpiritual Courts. Laſtly, this is made good alſo from approved practice in this very Kings Reign, as will appear by this remarkable ſtory that now follows.</p>
            <p>Thomas, <hi>the Noble Earl of</hi> Lancaſter, <hi>had to wife</hi> Alice, <hi>only Daughter and Heir of</hi> Henry <hi>Earl of</hi> Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln; <hi>at the ſame time,</hi> John <hi>Earl of</hi> Warren <hi>was married to King</hi> Edward <hi>the firſt his Neece; yet the ſaid Earl</hi> Warren <hi>by great force, and ſtrong hand, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſaid</hi> Alice <hi>Counteſs of</hi> Lancaſter <hi>to be fetched from the Earl of</hi> Lancaſters <hi>houſe in</hi> Canford <hi>in</hi> Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet ſhire, <hi>and in great pomp and bravery (in deſpight of the Earl of</hi> Lancaſter) <hi>to be brought to him to his Caſtle of</hi> Rye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gate <hi>in</hi> Surrey, <hi>where they lived in open advowtry.</hi> John Langton <hi>was then Biſhop of</hi> Chicheſter, <hi>and Chancellor of</hi> England; <hi>and being a man of a brave ſpirit, and fearing not the face of great men, according to his office and duty he called the ſaid Earl</hi> Warren <hi>in queſtion, for the ſaid ſhameful and open Adultery, and by Eccleſiaſtical cenſures Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated him for the ſame, as he well deſerved,</hi> ſayes my Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> who reports this Story
<note n="*" place="margin">Exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ion on the Statute called, <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi ſuper Chartas Anno</hi> 28 Edvard 1. page 573.</note>.</p>
            <p>This hapned about the 29th year of King <hi>Edv.</hi> 1. and ſurely is an inſtance proper to inform us what the right ſtate of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction was then; and that ſuppoſing the matter to be indeed belonging to the Eccleſiaſtical Tribunal, no perſon of greateſt dignity under the King, nor any others in civil office and place of power are exempted from it, nor did the Kings prohibitory Writs give any ſuch exemption.</p>
            <p>Thus it was while the Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction did <hi>de facto</hi> ſtand divided from the Crown, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Kings re-aſſumed their Rights in the ſame;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:53134:38"/>But foraſmuch as now there is an entire Union of both juriſdictions in one ſupream King and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: the exerciſe of the Eccleſiaſtical juriſdiction is certainly at leaſt as extenſive, as full, and as Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal now as it was before. And whereas the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining and having the Kings <hi>leave and licence</hi> to the inflicting any cenſures on His Bayliffs and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, is mentioned in thoſe prohibitory Writs, whence it may be inferred, that admitting, Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical judges may proceed againſt, and cenſure (occaſion ſo requiring it) the Kings Officers in civil powers; yet the Kings <hi>leave and order</hi> ſo to do, muſt firſt be had and obtained: To this, I ſay, that now by the right conſtitution of Eccleſiaſtical juriſdiction, and as the exerciſe thereof is derived from the Crown, the Kings <hi>leave and licence</hi> in the whole procedure thereof, is implicitely indeed, yet as truly and certainly had and obtained, as if a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and expreſs mandate from the King were iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued out upon each ſeveral cauſe, civil or criminal that belongs to the cognizance thereof: The E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical judge acts by a power as immediately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the King, as any Temporal Judge does: The Biſhop is as amply and compleatly Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated for the Exerciſe of Eccleſiaſtical juriſdiction, both <hi>ſubjectively, and objectively, in foro Externo &amp; contentioſo</hi> (which Commiſſion paſſes in His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Letters Patents for Reſtauration of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralities) as any other Temporal Judge in any of the Kings Temporal Courts: And upon this account it is as truly affirmed, That nothing is done in the Eccleſiaſtical Court <hi>Rege inconſulto,</hi> as the ſame is ſaid concerning the Temporal Court. <hi>Habet Rex diverſas Curias, in quibus diverſae Actiones terminan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:53134:39"/>ſayes <hi>Bracton,</hi> and he lived in one of theſe Kings Reign, <hi>viz</hi> that of King <hi>Henry</hi> 3d, whence Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> draws this concluſion, <hi>That the King hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and diſtributed all his whole power of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to ſeveral Courts of Juſtice;</hi> and in this he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to Eccleſiaſtical Courts as well as Temporal: And from the Statute 24 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. he declares thus, <hi>That the Laws Eccleſiaſtical and Temporal, were, and yet are adminiſtred, adjudged and executed by ſundry Judges</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">His Juriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Courts, <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 70.</note>, &amp;c. Hence is that ſaying, <hi>That the King does judge by his Judges.</hi> Thus in matters of Eccleſiaſtical cognizance, the King judges by His Eccleſiaſtical Judges; and whatſoever perſons are any way concerned therein, and impleaded in the Eccleſiaſtical Court, the King by His Eccleſiaſtical Judges has the hearing of them, and determining, in their cauſes, and <hi>His leave and licence</hi> goes along therewith.</p>
            <p>By vertue of being thus deputed and commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated by the King, the Biſhops have and execute an exterior Juriſdiction, which is as extenſive and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal over all perſons in cauſes belonging thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, as is the Temporal Juriſdiction, in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Temporal Judges; and where the Kings Commiſſion is, there is His power, and there is His conſent: And where that Commiſſion does not abridge and limit, there all proceedings made by power from it, have aſſuredly the Kings leave and licence in conjunction with them.</p>
            <p>But if ſtill notwithſtanding all that has been ſaid, it be perſiſted in, that there is a diſparity of power in the two Juriſdictions as to the extenſiveneſs thereof <hi>ſubjectively,</hi> ſo as that the Eccleſiaſtical Judge in his way of proceedings may not, but the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:53134:39"/>Temporal Judge in his way may proceed, againſt any civil Officers, as Mayors and Sheriffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> found Delinquents in any kind. I demand, How does it appear to be ſo? What Law is there that conſtitutes this Diſparity? What legal courſe preſcribed and ſet down to reſtrain the Eccleſiaſtical Judge, in caſe he will be intermedling with ſuch perſons? (for it is irrational to imagine there ſhould be ſuch a Law, and yet that it ſhould be deſtitute of ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent means to uphold and maintain it ſelf by.)</p>
            <p>Truly I am not ſo vain, as to ſay there is no Law extant which conſtitutes this Diſparity, becauſe I know no ſuch; but I have been ſeriouſly inquiſitive and diligent in ſearching after this, but cannot attain a knowledge of any ſuch; and would any be ſo kind to inform me, I ſhould thankfully own that kindneſs.</p>
            <p>Next, for any legal courſe preſcribed and ſet down to reſtrain Eccleſiaſtical Judges, in caſe they will be intermedling with ſuch perſons: If there be any ſuch, it muſt be one or other of theſe three wayes. 1. By Writ of <hi>Proviſion</hi> and <hi>Praemunire.</hi> Or, 2. By a Writ of <hi>Indicavit.</hi> Or, 3. By a Writ of <hi>Prohibition.</hi> (By one or other of theſe) the Eccleſiaſtical Judge is reſtrained in his proceedings, and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mmanded to deſiſt from proſecuting further ſuch matters, as being before him, are referred to, in thoſe Writs.</p>
            <p>Now concerning the firſt, <hi>That Proviſion and Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire</hi> has no place nor uſe in this matter, I do for the preſent plainly declare, and afterwards I ſhall have occaſion more largely to prove it. 2. Then, for the Writ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <hi>Indicavit,</hi> that is notoriouſly known to lie there <hi>where a Suit of Tythes is commenced in
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:53134:40"/>the Eccleſiaſtical Court, which does amount to a fourth part or above of the whole Benefice; or it lieth for the Patron, where his Clerk is impleaded for the Advow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> (i. e.) <hi>the Right of Patronage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. There remains only the Writ of <hi>Prohibition:</hi> This is ſaid to be two-fold; <hi>Prohibitio Juris, Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitio</hi>
               <q>
                  <hi>Hominis. Prohibitio Juris</hi> is ſuch as is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on any Statute or Law of this Land. <hi>Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Hominis</hi> is ſuch as has no preciſe word or letter of the Law to ſuſtain it, but is raiſed up by Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and by way of ſurmiſe, and as the wit of man will ſuggeſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now put theſe Prohibitions of both ſorts toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and I dare boldly affirm, that none of either kind have been, or can, or ought to be granted, ſo as to ſuperſede the Eccleſiaſtical Judge from his le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal proceedings againſt any perſon (where the matter proceeded upon is indeed of Eccleſiaſtical cognizance) meerly becauſe ſuch a perſon bears ſome office of civil power, is a Mayor, Sheriff, Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieve, or any other in like place of authority: And this is the reaſon why I take ſo much confidence in delivering this affirmation, becauſe it is the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency of the cauſe brought into tryal before the Eccleſiaſtical Judge; and not this or that quality or condition of the parties proceeded againſt, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes makes way for moving for, and granting of, a Prohibition.</p>
            <p>Thus much has been ſaid for the removal of theſe Objections, and ſtill it is clear and evident, that the exerciſe of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction by the Biſhop over all perſons whatſoever within his Dioceſs, in matters and cauſes truly belonging thereunto, tends not at all to the impa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring or invading the Kings Royal Prerogative.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:53134:40"/>
            <p>It has been the glory of our Kings to keep the Rights and Liberties of the Church ſafe and entire, and never to interpret a juſt exerting and uſing of their Juriſdiction, to be a diminiſhing of their Royal dignity. In ſome old Preſidents of the Writ <hi>de Excommunicato capiendo (A priviledge peculiar to the Church of</hi> England <hi>above all the Realms of</hi> Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom <hi>that I read of,</hi> ſayes Dr. <hi>Coſen, Apol. par.</hi> 1. p. 9.) The King declares thus, <hi>Nolumus quod libertas Eccleſiaſtica per nos vel Miniſtros noſtros quoſcunque aliqualiter violetur Register.</hi> in bre. orig. p. 69. a. And again, <hi>Jura &amp; libertates Eccleſiasticas illaeſa volentes in omnibus obſervari, ibidem.</hi> But I have one greater inſtance hereof to add here: At the time of His Majeſties Coronation, the Oath that He is pleaſed then to take, has this Article therein—<hi>That He will grant, keep and confirm to His people of</hi> England, <hi>the Laws and customs to them granted by the Kings of</hi> England, <hi>His lawful and religious Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors; and namely, the Laws, customs and Franchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes granted to the Clergy by the glorious King St.</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>his Predeceſſor, according to the Laws of God, the true profeſſion of the Goſpel establiſhed in this Kingdom, agreeable to the Prerogative of the Kings thereof, and the ancient customs of this Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Afterwards, one Biſhop preſent, reads this Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to the King before the people with a loud voyce—<hi>Our Lord and King, we beſeech You to pardon and grant, and to preſerve unto us, and to the Churches committed to our charge, all Canonical Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and due Law and Justice; and that You would protect and defend us, as every good King ought to be a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Protector and Defender of the Biſhops and Churches under His Government.</hi>—Whereto
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:53134:41"/>the King anſwereth <hi>with a willing and devout heart, I promiſe and grant my part, and that I will preſerve and maintain to you and the Churches,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>By Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical priviledges that belong to them and their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, there must needs be implyed the Honour of their ſeveral Orders, as, that Biſhops ſhould be above Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>together with all their due Rights and Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions.</hi> Dr. <hi>Stewards</hi> Anſwer to a Letter concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Church, and the Revenues thereof.—</p>
            <p>Of theſe Laws, Cuſtoms and Franchiſes granted to the Church and Clergy, this of actual exerciſing Juriſdiction Eccleſiaſtical in cauſes belonging there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, is (as I have before ſhewed) one, and that a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal one too: Now to imagine, that the King will bind Himſelf by Oath to the confirming of ſuch Charters and Grants, which he either reſolves not to keep, or ſuch as are detrimental to Him, and tend to the impairing His Prerogative, is neither conſiſtent with Reaſon, nor Loyalty, nor Religion. Here is no need of that Writ in the Kings behalf, called, <hi>Ad quod Damnum:</hi> As what damage and prejudice will come to the King by confirming Epiſcopal Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, and allowing the actual exerciſe thereof; for, in truth, the exerciſe thereof kept in its right conſtitution and dependance (for ſuch a Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is only here intended) is ſo far from diminiſhing the Right, and darkning the Jewels, of the Crown, that they receive a greater luſtre and reſplendency thereby.</p>
            <p>We have ſpoken of the Kings Oath, which He is pleaſed at the time of His Coronation to take for the benefit and ſecurity of His Subjects: There is alſo the Subjects Oath which they are to take in Recognition of the Kings Sovereignty, and in te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:53134:41"/>of their fidelity to him, I mean, the Oath of Supremacy; a conſideration of which is very proper and pertinent to the matter in hand, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, that one branch which the Taker there f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſwears to, and declares that—<hi>To his power he will aſſiſt and defend all Juriſdictions, Priviledges, Preheminences and Authorities united and annexed to the Imperial Crown of this Realm.</hi> In which words, the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> eſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Juriſdiction is (if not only) yet ſpecia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly aimed at: Now let ſuch perſons that are p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aced in Offices of civil Power and Authority, and conceit themſelves not ſubject to Eccleſiaſtica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Juriſdiction (becauſe of their being in ſuch Offices) and who yet do take this Oath at the entrance into their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; let them, I ſay, ſoberly and adviſedly bethink themſelves, how conſiſtent an Oath taken for the obſervance and defence of the Eccleſiaſtical J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, is, with a plain diſowning of ſuch Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction as to themſelves, or impugning of it, and bearing themſelves diſobediently to it, or exempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves from it, in matters which the Law has clearly appropriated to it: or, in a word, to act any thing to the prejudice of the lawful proceedings thereof. It is frivolous and vain to alledge, that they acknowledge, and will ſubmit to this Juriſdiction in the King, and yet at the ſame time deny their ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the exerciſe of it by the Biſhops. This, I ſay, is a vain and frivolous Allegation, becauſe it is not a notional and ſpeculative acknowledgment, that ſuch <hi>a Juriſdiction is united and annexed to the Imperial Crown of this Realm,</hi> which only fulfills the imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt of this Oath: But it is an obedience in practice by ſubmitting to the lawful exerciſe of it, that is the ſoope and intendment of it. Now the King exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:53134:42"/>no judiciary power in His own perſon, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits it to His Judges <hi>(the King hath wholly left mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Judicature, according to His Laws, to His Judges</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Lord <hi>Cole. 4 In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it. p</hi> 71.</note>) And the Biſhops are thoſe Judges to whom the Eccleſiaſt. Juriſdiction is committed, and to them the execution thereof belongeth; now what is done in deregation of that power and authority (deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatively) reſiding in them, is done in like manner in deregation of the ſame power primitively; that is, as it is originally in, and derives from the King Himſelf. I have ſaid thus much concerning this branch of the Oath of Supremacy, not that I take upon me to judge any man; but becauſe I take it to be my duty to recommend the conſideration of this thing, as a matter of very weighty concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and fit to be made with all ſobriety and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſs.</p>
            <p>I ſum up all delivered on this firſt Propoſition under this Head, That Biſhops proceeding by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and deriving the actual exerciſe of their Juriſdiction from the King, are the Kings Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Judges, diſpenſing Juſtice in the Kings Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Courts, according to the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Laws. And that the ſame Juriſdiction reaches to, and over all perſons whatſoever within their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Dioceſſes; all which is agreeable to the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Laws of theſe Kingdoms, and not repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Temporal Laws thereof, nor yet infring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in any kind the Kings Prerogative Royal; and therefore the Biſhop of <hi>Waterford</hi>'s Juriſdiction in the Caſe before laid down, was legally founded in reſpect of the perſons proceeded againſt.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:53134:42"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Prob. II.</hi> The ſecond Propoſition is this. The Biſhops Juriſdiction over theſe perſons, was legally founded in reſpect of the cauſe that this proceeding was made upon. The cauſe was the rendring an accompt of Moneys given, and received to pious uſes; and rendring of an accompt of a large Rate, levied to the uſe of the Church , as alſo concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Reparation of the Body of the Cathedrall Church at <hi>Waterford,</hi> That the Biſhop is, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per competent Judge, to exact an accompt of all ſuch Moneys ſo given, and ſo to be diſpoſed of will not, I ſuppoſe, be denied, or, if it be denyed, the worſt of it is, 'tis but the being put to the proof of it, which is no very difficult task; and for ſureneſs ſake ſhall by and by be made good. And for the Reparation of Churches, that the ſame belongs to Eccleſiaſtical though the Law be clear for it, will yee be made more clear, by having thoſe Laws for it, produced. But before that be entred upon, ſome notice muſt be taken of what has been alledged, and paſſed roundly from the mouths of many, that concern'd them ſelves much in his mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: That by ancient contract, the Mayor, Sheriffs, and Commonalty of <hi>Waterford,</hi> ſtand obliged to the making good this Reparation; whence the Inference it made, That all contracts being of civil cognizance therefore the Biſhop was no competent Judge of that branch of the cauſe which was brought before him, the ſame being not cognizable in the Ecoleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Court.</p>
            <p>This Allegation at the firſt hearing, ſeemed mighty fair and plauſible, inſomuch as, ſome perſons, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe no Enemies to Epiſcopal Juriſdiction, were much concerned, and ſtartled thereat: And when they firſt
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:53134:43"/>heard it, they concluded preſently that the Biſhop had taken a matter in hand, which he ought not to have moved a hand towards, as not appertaining to his juriſdiction, and ſo has uſurped on the Temporal Courts: Nay, ſo ſtrangely tranſported were ſome, that in their heats they did not ſtick to affirm, that the Biſhop by doing what he did, had incur'd ſome heavy penalty, which they would not abate of an Ace, leſs than a <hi>praemunire</hi> it ſelf. And many, and hard, and bitter were the cenfures, that ſeveral open mouths pronounced upon him: But cauſes as well as perſons are ſometimes prejudged; and both were ſo in this caſe. As a preparative to the clearing, and making good, that both cauſe, and perſon were thus prejudged, I ſhall ſpeak ſomething concerning the matter of contract, ſo mainly inſiſted upon, and that which raiſed the cry; as if the Biſhop grounded his proceeding on that contract, and therein encroached on the Temporal Juriſdiction.</p>
            <p>Let it therefore for the preſent be ſuppoſed, That the Biſhop did ground his Eccleſiaſtical pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding on that contract (although indeed the cauſe was not ſo laid, yet ſuppoſing it were) the inference that is thence made peradventure is not good, as that the doing thereof was an encroachment on the Temporal Juriſdiction. Peradventure I ſay it is not; For I will not be poſitive in what I am about to write; but referring my ſelf to better judgments, I freely ſubmit to their deciſions herein.</p>
            <p>This I propoſe then, That all matters of contract, ariſing from, or upon cauſes originally of Spiritual cognizance, are not exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ded from the Eccleſiaſtical Tribunal. I put this caſe not much differing from that which we have before us. <hi>Titius</hi> a pariſhioner
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:53134:43"/>of <hi>Dale,</hi> with leave of the Parſon, and reſt of the pariſhioners, builds up an Iſle, or Out chappel, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning to the Pariſh Church of <hi>Dale,</hi> and intends to reſerve the ſame to himſelf, and relations, for the uſe of a burying place, and undertakes to keep this Out-chappel, from time to time, in ſufficient, good, and decent repair. Notwithſtanding this obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo to do, the repair of the ſame is neglected. If the queſtion were put to me, before whom, and in what Court, <hi>Titius</hi> may be ſued, and compelled to make good the reparation thereof, I ſhould not doubt to anſwer, that <hi>Titius</hi> may be proceeded againſt by the Ordinary, <hi>ex Officio,</hi> or impleaded by any voluntary Promoter of the Office, <hi>in cauſa repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationis Capellae,</hi> &amp;c. The Church wardens may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that neglect, and the perſon guilty of it. One Article uſually given to preſent upon, is this, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church or Chappel in the Body, and Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of it, be in good repair; If it be not, through whoſe defaclt comes it to paſs, that it is not; and this Article is grounded on the 93d <hi>Canon</hi> of this Church. So then as the neglect and default is puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by the Ordinary; the reformation likewiſe thereof in making good the repair, (otherwiſe by contract undertaken for) is to be enjoyned by the Ordinary.</p>
            <p>Moreover, Penſions out of Churches, or any An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Portion beeoming due from any Colledge, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick, Cathedral Church, or Deanry, to be paid to any Rector, Vicar, or Curate of a Pariſh Church; if they be detained, the ſame are demandable, and to be recovered in the Eccleſiaſtical Court, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Statute, <hi>viz.</hi> 34 35 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. Now the Right of paying any ſuch Penſions, and Annual
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:53134:44"/>Portions is grounded on Ancient-contract, obliging thereunto.</p>
            <p>In Compoſitions Real for Tythes, made either between the Parſon of one, and the Parſon of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pariſh, for the ſtating and ſetling each others right, and to prevent, litigious impleadings of each other. Alſo compoſitions made between the Parſon, and ſome one or more of his pariſhioners, touching the not paying any Tythes at all, but a certain, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and determinate ſum in lieu thereof: This is uſual in this Kingdom, for Mills that grind corn, to compound for a certain ſum, to be paid inſtead of the Toll-tythe. Now the Eccleſiaſtical Judge before whom theſe compoſitions are to be alledged, may hear and determine thereof. <hi>Tit.</hi> 120. <hi>Cler. Prax.</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Ridley's View,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>part.</hi> 3. <hi>chap.</hi> 3. <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. <hi>Coſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Apol. p.</hi> 1. <hi>ch.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>There is a cauſe of Eccleſiaſtical cognizance, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Negotium ſubtractionis Dotis, cauſa nuptiarum promiſſae.</hi> The caſe is thus; <hi>Titius</hi> in conſideration of Matrimony, to be contracted and ſolemnized with his Daughter <hi>Partia</hi> by <hi>Sempronius,</hi> promiſed Ten pounds to <hi>Sempronius,</hi> The Matrimeny being ſolemnized, and <hi>Titius</hi> not paying the promiſed ſum, <hi>Sempronius</hi> impleads him before the Eccleſiaſtical Judge for the ſame, <hi>Titius</hi> ſues out a prohibition; Notwithſtanding which, <hi>Sempronius</hi> obtains a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation, wherein is affirmed, That the Court Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiaſtical may proceed therein. This you may find re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by Dr. <hi>Coſen. Apol. p.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 26. And the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral. Opinions of Common Lawyers concurring therein. More inſtances might be given of this kind, to evince, That all contracts ariſing from mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which are in their Original of Spiritual cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:53134:44"/>are not excluded from the Eccleſiaſtical Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal; obſerve what is further ſaid: Although promiſes and contracts of Money, are generally pleadable in the Courts of the common Law, yet, as <hi>Bracton</hi> writes, <hi>Cauſae de rebus promiſſis, ob cauſam Matrimonii, in foro Eccleſiaſtico terminari debent; quia cujus juris &amp; juriſdictionis eſt principale, ejuſdem erit, acceſſorium:</hi> And in another place he gives a reaſon for the ſame, <hi>quia ſemper videndum propter quid, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid ſit, aut permittatur.</hi> Zouch. Juriſdiction of the Admiralty. <hi>p.</hi> 64.</p>
            <p>I do not affirm an abſolute parity between theſe caſes, and that which is before us; I refer'd my ſelf before, and do now ſtill ſubmit what is ſaid to the judicious deciſions of others: But, this is yet upon the ſuppoſal, that what is objected, was really ſo, as is objected, the contrary to which is moſt clear; for as touching what relates to this Vindication, there is no need at all, to ſtrain any doubtful or diſputable caſe, to make it favour the matter in hand; for the contract here pretended, was not inſiſted upon, ſo as to make a foundation of any juriſdictive pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, in the Eccleſiaſtical Court thereupon.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, the contract gave occaſion to the Biſhop to call upon, and admoniſh the Mayor, and Sheriffs of <hi>Waterford,</hi> to look after what belonged to their duty to be done. They being thus ſtirred up, make rates, levy, and collect Money from the ſeveral In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants for this end, of repairing the Body of the Cathedral, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They receive the voluntary contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions for the Bells. The Money thus levied, col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and received, is little diſpoſed of for the uſes intended: The Church remains unrepaired, the other works are neglected; now what was regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:53134:45"/>and legally to be done in this caſe, was regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, and legally entred upon; the work of repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it ſelf; the accounting for Money levied, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, contributed and received for that purpoſe, and other matters relating to the Church, are the grounds of this proceeding, as by the ſeveral Acts of Court remaining in the Regiſtry of <hi>Waterford,</hi> may more fully appear.</p>
            <p>Now that theſe are juſtiſiable grounds, whereon legally to found an Eccleſiaſtical proceeding, comes to be made good, which I ſhall do, by laying down and proving theſe three Aſſertions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The rendring an accompt of Moneys given, and received for pious cauſes; and the right diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thereof, belongs to the Biſhop within his own Dioceſs, to call for, and ſee performed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Reparations of Churches, with all the inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents thereunto, both by Temporal, and Spiritual Law, appertain to Eccleſiaſtical cognizance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The penalty of <hi>Praemunire</hi> will not be incurr'd by any Eccleſiaſtical Judge for making ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The rendring an accompt of Moneys given and received for pious cauſes; and the right diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thereof, belongs to the Biſhop within his own Dioceſs, to call for and ſee performed: Pious cauſes are ſet down in the Law to be of many, and various kinds, and to enjoy many and various priviledges; for the many and various kinds of them, ſee <hi>Leg. il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud, &amp; Leg. Sancimus. Cod. de Sacro-ſanctis Eccleſiis;</hi> and <hi>Lindwood in cap. it a quorundam. ad Verb. pias cauſas. de Teſtamentis lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Provincial. Conſtitut.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong which, theſe eſpecially fall under our diſquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; namely, Legacies, or other Donations, either
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:53134:45"/>beſtowed, for the erecting of Hoſpitals, and Almſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, and endowing them with ſufficient means, and adding to ſuch endowments, for the ſuſtentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and maintenance of aged, ſickly, decrepid, weak and helpleſs perſons, as Priſoners, Orphans, Widows, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or ſuch as are beſtowed for the erecting, and repairing of Churches, and providing of ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>naments, and other Utenſils, as are requiſite therein; alſo ſuch as are beſtowed for the celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Divine offices, at certain times, and ſeaſons appointed.</p>
            <p>Now although I have delivered this Aſſertion u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally, yet it is to be underſtood with reſtricti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to thoſe kinds of pious cauſes, that I have parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly ſpecified. The Imperial Law allows a very ample and large power to Biſhops, in order to the regulating and diſpoſing of theſe to their intended purpoſes, <hi>Authent. collat. nona. Tit. de Sanctiſſimis Epiſcopis, cap.</hi> 23. See alſo the Canons called the Apoſtles Canons, <hi>cap. praecipimus</hi> 40 <hi>ibidem. Item cap. Tua nob is; &amp; cap. Johannes. de Teſtamentis.</hi> And concerning ſuch things as belong to Almſ-houſes, and Hoſpitals of any (but Royal) foundations, our Statute Law is very expreſs herein—<hi>And as to other Hoſpitals which be of another foundation, and patronage than the Kings, the Ordinaries ſhall enquire of the manner of the foundation, eſtate and gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the ſame, and of all other matters, and things neceſſary in this behalf, and upon that make correction and reformation after the Laws of</hi> Holy Church, <hi>as to them belongeth,</hi> An. 2. Hen. 5. cap. 1. ſtat. 1.</p>
            <p>And whereas in ſome particular caſes of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it is appointed by the Statute 43 <hi>Elizab. cap.</hi> 4. That by certain Commiſſioners authorized thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:53134:46"/>to under the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> ſuch Lands, Moneys, Goods, and Chattels as have been given to ſuch Godly uſes, as are there mentioned, ſhould be rightly ordered, and all miſemployings thereof be prevented and regulated; yet there is a proviſo in that Statute, to this end—<hi>That neither this Act, nor any thing therein contained, ſhall be any way prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial, or hurtful to the Juriſdiction of the Ordinany or power of the Ordinary; but that he may lawfully in every caſe execute the ſame, as though this Act had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been had or made:</hi> Raſtall.</p>
            <p>And where there is a grant of Money, or other moveable goods, made by any perſon either in his life time, or bequeathed by Legacy, at the time of his deceaſe for ſuch pious cauſes, as the erecting and repairing of Churches, or buying ſuch decent Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments, and Furniture as belong to the ſame, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That the Money, or other moveable goods thus granted, or bequeathed, be diſpoſed for ſuch uſes, and according to the intent of the Donor, belongs to the Biſhops care to look after, and ſee performed: Inſomuch, as they in whoſe hands ſuch Moneys, and Goods are detained, may be convented before the Biſhop, and made to render an accompt thereof. And the proſecution made herein, may be either of <hi>office,</hi> or at the promotion of the Church wardens of that, or ſuch other Pariſh, to which the ſame is given. <hi>Detentio legatorum ad uſum pauperum, &amp; quemlibet alium pium uſum: detentio bonorum ad pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licos uſus Eccleſiae deſtinatorum, ad Epiſcopalem juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictionem pertinent,</hi> Coſen. Tab. vii. A.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe it is, that in Articles given at Epiſcopal Viſitations, <hi>one is to enquire what Lands, Poſſeſſions, or other Richts are belonging, or deemed
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:53134:46"/>and reputed to belong unto any Eccleſiaſtical Benefice, and in whoſe hands they are, and how they have been in their hands:</hi> Which Article of Enquiry is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on the 44th Canon of this Church of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and cognizance of theſe things belong to the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Courts, and may (as I ſaid) be taken there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, by the Eccleſiaſtical Judge, either of meer office, or office promoted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and whether ſoever it be, that ſuch Rights become due by Legacy, or any other Donation.</p>
            <p>A man by his Teſtament bequeaths Goods to the Fabrick of a Church, the Executor is to be ſued for this in Court Eccleſiaſtical, and thus it is determined at common Law; ſee for this a conſultation grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Regiſter. p.</hi> 57. <hi>a.</hi> cited at large by Dr. <hi>Coſen. Apol. par.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 100. But what if any iſſues and profits out of certain Lands and Tenements grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and belonging to any Church, be detained? They alſo may be ſued for, and recovered in Court Eccleſiaſtical: <hi>If a Terr-Tenant holding Land, that hath uſually paid for ſuch a Tenement a pound of wax, or ſuch like, unto the Church, do with-hold it, the Churchwardens may ſue him for it in Court Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal.</hi> Dr. <hi>Coſen. par.</hi> 1. <hi>p,</hi> 45. And he alledges for this an ancient Author, one <hi>Goodall,</hi> who wrote in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> 8th, and intituled his Book, <hi>Of the Liberties of the Clergy by the Laws of the Realm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And obſerve, that although a pound of wax, and ſuch like, is only here mentioned, yet it is not the tenuity, and meaneſs of the thing that gives a right in this caſe to ſue for it in the Spiritual Court: But becauſe there is a right ſo to do, the ſame courſe of proceedings may be followed, were the profits ſo
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:53134:47"/>accrewing, and ſo to be diſpoſed of, far more valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. I will inſtance but in one caſe more (which the Dr. mentions in <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>chap.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 102.) An Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry proceeded <hi>ex Officii ſui debito,</hi> to the correction of crimes, and exceſſes of thoſe that were under his juriſdiction: And amongſt other objected Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles againſt a Knight, for not ſufficient reparations of a Church, tending to the correction of his ſoul, by reaſon of his detaining of that, which he ought not. This, ſayes he, is allowed in the Regiſter, <hi>Tit. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations fol.</hi> 53.6. I might, but ſhall not need, to add more for the proof of this firſt Aſſertion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Reparation of Churches, with the incidents thereunto, both by Temporal and Spiritual Law, appertains to Eccleſiaſtical cognizance, I call theſe the incidents thereunto. The buſineſs of making Rates for ſuch Reparations; inſpecting the money ſo rated; queſtioning thoſe that refuſe to contribute their proportion; and calling to account for money ſo collected. Theſe are all dependant on the other, in caſe of any judicial proceeding that ſhall happen to be made thereon; the reaſon is given in this, as in all other things of like nature, in that excellent law; <hi>Nulli prorſus. Cod. de judiciis;</hi> the ſum of which is this, <hi>Ne continentiae cauſarum dividantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Temporal Law is expreſs for the proof of this, in the Statute of <hi>circumſpecte agatis. An.</hi> 13. <hi>Edwardi Primi.</hi> Among the thirteen caſes there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cired, and appropriated to the Eccleſiaſtical Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.
<q>This is one, <hi>viz.</hi> Prelates may puniſh for lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Church yards uncloſed; or for that the Church is uncovered, or not conveniently decked.</q> This Statute is alſo inſerted in the provincial conſtitutions, collected by <hi>Lindwood, Tit. de fore competenti;</hi> and ſo
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:53134:47"/>is become part of the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Law. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Common Law caſes are cited for this by <hi>Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> in his Guide for Church-wardens, <hi>Sect.</hi> 37. And note, ſayes he, That the Eccleſiaſtical Court hath cognizance of the reparation of the Body of the Church. He inſtances in the Body of the Church, becauſe (not-excluding the other parts) mention is there made of the Pariſhioners, to whom the repair belongs, and who are to contribute to the ſame.</p>
            <p>Dr <hi>Coſen</hi> in the Firſt part of his Apology, <hi>cap.</hi> 7: informs us thus, touching this matter: When a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition was ſued out (ſayes he) for proceeding Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtically in a matter concerning the Reparation of the Body of a Church. A judgement was given thereupon, in a conſultation to this effect (which he ſayes is recorded in the Regiſter, cited by him thus [<hi>pag.</hi> 43. <hi>a.</hi>] <hi>Vobis igitur ſignificamus quod ſuper emendatione &amp; reparatione defectuum corporis Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae juxta conſuetudinem approbatam, facienda, proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere poteritis, &amp; ea facere quae ad forum Eccleſiaſticum nover it is pertinere, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a prohibitione, non obſtante.</hi> And by reaſon of defects in the reparation of a Church (ſayes the ſame Author) <hi>ibid.</hi> Money it ſelf may lawfully be ſued for in a Court Eccleſiaſtical; as appears by another conſultation, <hi>Reg. pag.</hi> 48. <hi>a.</hi> And ſo it is provided in the very Stature of <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte agatis.</hi> The words are theſe mentioned in it. —<hi>In which caſe none other penance can be enjoyned but pecuniary.</hi> See <hi>Lindwood ad verbum. Sub poena. cap. Sint Eccleſiarum Rectores. De Officio Archidiaconi,</hi> Lord <hi>Coke de jure Regis Eccleſiaſtico, p</hi> 9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The penalty of <hi>praemunire</hi> will not be incurred by any Eccleſiaſtical Judge, on account of any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of this Nature. The proof of this Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:53134:48"/>depends upon two things, <hi>viz.</hi> The truth of the two former Aſſertions, that the cauſe proceeded upon, was properly belonging to the Eccleſiaſtical Tribunal, and that the Biſhop the Eccleſiaſtical Judge proceeding therein, acted not by, or from any foreign juriſdiction or power. Both theſe are ſo manifeſtly true, that I might ſuperſede my ſelf the labour of ſaying any more therein. But becauſe ſome mens mouths were opened wide, and loud in that point, as if when by Law they could not, they would yet by their clamorous votes, and confident affirmings, involve the Biſhop in the penalty of this Statute: It will therefore, I think, be both a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable undertaking, and proper to our purpoſe, to write ſomething more particularly concerning the ſame; and the rather, becauſe the imputation of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring the penalty, contained in that Statute, is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes (at leaſt) threatned againſt thoſe that are careful, and active in the diſcharge of their Office of Truſt, in matters of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction.</p>
            <p>It has been the obſervation of a late Hiſtorian, (<hi>Fuller, Church Hiſtory, Book</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 149.) that this Statute of <hi>pramunire</hi> has had the hard hap not to be honoured with ſo many readings thereon, as other Statutes: And therefore I ſuppoſe, the courſe now taken by me, in ſpeaking ſomething hereof, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear the more excuſable: If not having opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of viewing the few readings, that have been made thereon, by the Learned in the Common Law, I have recourſe to ſuch other Writers, as upon ſome occaſional emergency, or other incidental mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, have treated thereof.</p>
            <p>The Writ of <hi>praemunire facias,</hi> grounded princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally on the Statute, made in the 16 year of King
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:53134:48"/>
               <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, <hi>cap.</hi> 5. is awarded againſt thoſe that have procured any Proceſs, or Bull of the Pope from <hi>Rome,</hi> or elſewhere, for any Eccleſiaſtical place, or preferment within this Realm, or doth ſue in any foreign Eccleſiaſtical Court, to defeat, or impeach the Kings Courts; and the party offending here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, is liable to grievous penalties, mentioned in the ſaid Statute: This account of a <hi>praemunire,</hi> (as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted by him from the Statute) I take from Sir <hi>Thomas Ridley,</hi> in his View of the Civil and Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Laws, <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Some later Statutes (ſayes Dr. <hi>Cowell</hi> in the word <hi>praemunire</hi>) do caſt this puniſhment on other offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: <hi>As denying the Kings Supremacy the ſecond time, by the Statute</hi> 1 Elizab. 1. <hi>falls under the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of</hi> praemunire. <hi>And by the Statute</hi> 13 Eliz. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>He that affirmeth the Authority of the Pope, and refuſes to take the Oath of Supremacy, falls under the like penalty: ſo they do likewiſe by the Statute of the</hi> 13 <hi>of the Q.</hi> cap. 1. <hi>that are ſeditious talkers, or affirm the Q. Majeſty to be an Heretick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let us put all theſe together, and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver elſe is collected from the Statutes made before, and after the Reign of King <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, touching theſe matters: Put all theſe (I ſay) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and what, either in groſs or tale, will they make to diſadvantage the matter we have in hand? or what can be found, either in the Biſhop, or his proceedings, impeachable from thence? Is it his being appointed to, and ſetled in the Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcopal See of <hi>Waterford</hi> and <hi>Liſmore?</hi> None can affirm that: For he receives not this by any Bull from <hi>Rome,</hi> but by Donation and Inveſtiture from the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Is it the actual exerciſing of Eccleſiaſtical Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:53134:49"/>within his Dioceſs? That cannot be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; becauſe he is not empowred to this by any Foreign Authority, but by his Majeſties Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents for his Conſecration; and by His Majeſties Letters Patents for reſtauration of the Temporali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Are any of his proceedings againſt the Kings Crown and Dignity? No, They tend not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote any foreign power, but to maintain the Kings Prerogative and Supremacy, over all perſons in cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Eccleſiaſtical: Does he refuſe to take the Oath of Supremacy, or fall under any of thoſe crimes mentioned in the Statutes of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and which are liable to the penalties of <hi>praemunire?</hi> This cannot be ſaid, He took the Oath of Supremacy, on other occaſions required by Law: And he took it (as is appointed) at the time of his Conſecration. Laſtly, are any things done by him, whereby the Kings Courts are impeached and defeated? Not this, becauſe He the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Judge in the Dioceſs of <hi>Waterford</hi> and <hi>Liſmore,</hi> hears and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines matters of Eccleſiaſtical cognizance in the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Court there, according to, and by the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Laws:</p>
            <p>Whence then may we conceive, ariſes this impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a <hi>praemunire?</hi> There is indeed no ground for it, but in the fancies, (and would I had not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſay) in the wiſhes of ſuch, as are ſo ill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, that they do not patiently endure the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal office, much leſs allow the exerciſe of any Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction by a Biſhop.</p>
            <p>Obſervation of former times, and reading, beſides preſent experience of things now, brings to our knowledge the reſtleſs practiſes of ſome, that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour by all contrivances of wit and policy, to
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:53134:49"/>load with odious charges the exerciſe of Epiſcopal Juriſdiction; and (if it may be done) to draw it within the penalties appointed by this Statute of <hi>Praemunire:</hi> yet there are many ſober and wiſe men, who have declared openly enough their opinion, That as all Juriſdiction whatſoever in theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, is radically in the King, and ſo an Union of Eccleſiaſtical and Temporal Supremacy, is in him; there can therefore lie no <hi>Praemunire</hi> at this day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any man exerciſing Juriſdiction ſubordinately under the King; which every Eccleſiaſtical Judge both doth, and acknowledges himſelf to do: See to this purpoſe Dr. <hi>Coſen</hi> in his <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. Sir <hi>Tho: Ridley ut ſupra,</hi> Dr. <hi>Cowell</hi> in the word <hi>Praemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire: Whatſoever,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>is now wrought or threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt the Juriſdiction Eccleſiaſtical, by colour of the ſame</hi> [<hi>Statute of</hi> Praemuni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e] <hi>is but in emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one Court to another, and by conſequent a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation to that Authority, from which all Juriſdiction is now derived, and the maintenance whereof, was by thoſe Princes eſpecially purpoſed:</hi> Nam ceſſante ratione, ceſſat Lek,</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Smith,</hi> a perſon of great judgment, one who well underſtood His Sovereigns Right and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, and wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d not detract any thing in the leaſt manner from it, declares his ſenſe herein after this manner—<hi>Verum in praeſentiarum Curia Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anitatis perinde atque caeterae omnes, virtutem vim au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatem imperium, juriſdictionemque ſuam, praeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Sereniſſimae Majeſti &amp; Diadem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti Regio, poſt immortalem Deum, Poteſtati aut Principi, accepta reſert Nemini. Id ſi verum eſſe concedas (quod eſſe conſtat veriſſimum) tum Sanctioni Statuariae de Praemunire nullus per Angliam locus relinquitur; quando alibi quam
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:53134:50"/>in Curia Regis, ac Reginae, jus nullum dicitur.</hi> De Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. Anglicana. lib. 3. cap. 11.</p>
            <p>There is a certain word indeed in that Statute, <hi>viz. [alibi]</hi> the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> or elſewhere; and this word is ſuppoſed, to be meant of, and refer to, Biſhops Courts: So I read that <hi>Fitz. herbert</hi> a great Lawyer reporteth it. <hi>Tit. praemunire num.</hi> 5. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, ſaving all reſpect to ſo great a Lawyer, yet this is judged by many grave, and learned perſons, (ſee thoſe before mentioned) to be a forced and groundleſs conſtruction made thereof. The word it ſelf is of an ambiguous and variable ſignification; it may refer to the Biſhops Conſiſtories, and it may, as well, not refer to them; it may refer to any Forreign Courts and Judicatories, and any other Courts of theſe Kingdoms, that are not Courts of common Law <note n="*" place="margin">So it ſeems it may refer to the Court of Admiralty, in my Lord <hi>Coke</hi>'s opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 4. <hi>Inſtit. cap.</hi> 22.</note>, or any Courts whatſoever (moſt agreeable to the purport of that Statute) wherein any thing is done <hi>in derogation of the Regality of our Lord the King;</hi> it is a ſlippery and uncertain word, none can take ſure hold of it; no determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and preciſe meaning can be affixed to it.</p>
            <p>This word then being ſo doubtful and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and the penalty of this Statute being ſo ſevere, as Impriſonment during life, for feiture of Goods, Lands, Chattels, Tenements, Ejection out of the Kings favour and protection; and ſince the noted Rule is this, <hi>in poenalibus cauſis benignius interpretan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt.</hi> L. 145. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. de Reg. Juris. parag: finali. Now it would be ſo far from a benigne, as to prove in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a moſt rigorous ſentence, to pronounce the falling under ſo great a penalty, on occaſion of this expreſſion, ſo full of ambiguity and uncertainty.</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:53134:50"/>
            <p>May I preſume, with the good leave of the Learned in the Municipal Laws of this Kingdom, to interpoſe my conjecture concerning this word [<hi>Alibi,</hi> or elſewhere] (for where there is am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguity, there is room for conjecture) I have the ground, of what I have to ſay, from Dr: <hi>Coſen, Apol. p.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. It was in the ſixteenth year of King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, that this Statute was Enacted, that was in the year of our Lord, One thouſand three hundred ninety and three; at which time, and for ſome time after, the Schiſm about creating of Popes (which is reckoned, and ſo called, the Twenty ninth Schiſm, <hi>Iſaacksons Cronolog. p.</hi> 353.) was very rife, and hot in agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Boniface</hi> the Ninth was at <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (called the Seventh) made by the French Cardinals, was at <hi>Avignion</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> here was at the ſame time, as had been before, two Popes actually exerciſing Papal Juriſdiction; both making Cardinals, and both ſtriving to extend their power and authority ſo far, that other Kingdoms, as well as the places where they were reſident, might be under the influence thereof: Now ſo it was, that this Statute of <hi>Praemunire,</hi> being intended for the utter excluſion of all Forreign Authority, it might be judged neceſſary to cut off all intercourſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Kings Subjects, and the Popes Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, whether at <hi>Rome,</hi> or elſewhere; and that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, and other judicial Writs, as well dated from <hi>Avignion,</hi> or any other place, as from <hi>Rome,</hi> might make the purchaſers and purſuers of them, liable to the penalties intended by that Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute.</p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:53134:51"/>
            <p>But there is ſomething further alledged here, That although the Eccleſiaſtical Courts as now eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, are not in the general intent included with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Statute; yet then ſurely they are, when cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes belonging to the Temporal Courts, are by Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Judges retained, and proceeded in: I know it paſſes as a very current Opinion among many, That for an Eccleſiaſtical Judge to deal in any cauſe, not belonging to his Juriſdiction, is <hi>Praemunire:</hi> Great is the Authority that bears up this Opinion; and for the greatneſs ſake of the Authority, many are the Adherers to it. In my Lord chief Baron <hi>Boltons</hi> Juſtice of the Peace, <hi>cap. praemunire.</hi> There is firſt a recital of the ſeveral Statutes, concurring in, and concerning this crime; then follows certain Book caſes, or reſolutions (as his Lordſhip expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes it) added, for the better explanation of thoſe Statutes. One of the ſaid caſes, is to this effect, <hi>viz.</hi> the 21. — <hi>Note that the words of the Statute, are in</hi> Curia Romana vel alibi, <hi>which is intended in</hi> Curia Epiſcopi: <hi>And therefore if a man be Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or profecuted in the Spiritual Court, for a thing which appertains to the common Law, he that proſecutes ſuch a Suit, is in caſe of</hi> praemunire: <hi>for this there is alledged in the margent,</hi> 5 Ed. 4. fo. 6.</p>
            <p>Before I was ſtopped with what is thus ſet down, and what I find affirmed by others to the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, I was ready to ſay, That it muſt be a very forc't ſtreining of that Statute, that will be able to wring ſuch a ſenſe out of it. But, who am I, that I ſhould oppoſe my obſcure meaneſs, to the authority of ſo great a perſon? May I have fair leave therefore, to offer only a few things to be conſidered of touching this matter, in behalf of the Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:53134:51"/>and the Judges belonging to the ſame?</p>
            <p>And firſt, whereas it is ſaid, that by the word <hi>[alibi]</hi> in the Statute, is intended <hi>Curia Epiſcopi:</hi> I refer the Reader to what has been before ſpoken of this particular thing; and further, I may now ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably notifie one thing, obſervable in the very Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute it ſelf, that may lead us by a more certain hand to perceive, what this word <hi>[alibi]</hi> has a reference to, and what it has not: For, whereas in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Statute of <hi>praemunire,</hi> Anno 16. <hi>Richard</hi> 2d. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. It is Ordained, <hi>That none ſhall purchaſe or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue in the Count of</hi> Rome, <hi>or (elſewhere) any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, Bulls,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>nor the ſame bring within the Realm,</hi> viz. <hi>theſe His Majeſties Dominions.</hi> This (be it ſpoken under correction) cannot rationally be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>de Curia Epiſcopi,</hi> here within this Blealm; the reaſon is plain, becauſe <hi>Curia Bomana vel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alibi,</hi> where ſuch Proceſſes and Bulls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are purchaſed and purſued, and from whence they are brought within the Realm; theſe, I ſay, muſt be ſomewhere out of the Realm (for the bringing in of a thing, excludes the obeing of that thing there already) but the Biſhops Courts are within the Realm, and none of theſe Proceſſes brought into the Realm, can be from them; and therefore this word <hi>[alibi]</hi> has no reference to, nor can it be intended of, them.</p>
            <p>Add hereunto, That the occaſion inducing this Statute, and recited in the preamble to lit, ſeems not all to favour this ſenſe of the word: The Coin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Parliament having with great vehemency and earneſtneſs, repreſented the ſeveral Grievances the Kingdom lay under, among others, theſe are eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially mentioned, <hi>viz. The Popes Excommunicating of Biſhops for executing the Kings Commandments;
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:53134:52"/>the Popes tranſlating of them from See to See; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times out of the Kingdom, againſt their own, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Kings Will:</hi> The Lords Spiritual being therefore demanded (as the Lords Temporal had been before) what their Advice and Will was in theſe caſes: The Archbiſhops and Biſhops, and other Prelates, openly diſclaimed the Popes inſolent car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage towards the King, and His Subjects; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, <hi>That they would, and ought to ſtand with the King in theſe caſes, in lawfully maintaining of His Crown, and in all other caſes touching His Crown and Regality, as they be bound by their Allegiance:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon (ſayes the Statute) <hi>It is Ordained and Enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That if any purchaſe or purſue,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>from the Court of</hi> Rome, <hi>or elſewhere,</hi> &amp;c. May I not here well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, what relation either in the occaſion, or ſenſe of the Stature, can be made up betwixt Biſhops Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtories, and this word <hi>[Alibi]?</hi> Biſhops in their Juriſdictions were troubled by the Pope, as the King Himſelf was in the right of His Crown; both are complained of, both redreſſed by this Statute. How can that which is the Grievance complained of in the preamble of the Statute, come to be the thing aggrieving in the latter part of it? The truth is, proviſion is here made againſt the ſetting up, and abetting of all Forreign Authority; <hi>but Domeſtical proceedings in Eccleſiaſtical Courts,</hi> are not related to. This I am confident to affirm, by this Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity following, <hi>The preamble</hi> (ſayes my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> from <hi>Pl. Com. fo.</hi> 369. <hi>Stowells</hi> caſe) <hi>in every Statute is to be conſidered, for it is the Key to open the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the makers of the Act, and miſchiefs which they intend to remedy.</hi> Alſo from a caſe 4 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. <hi>fo.</hi> 4.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:53134:52"/>
               <hi>&amp;</hi> 12. The ſame learned Judge declares thus— <hi>Every Statute ought to be expounded according to the intent of them that made it, where the words thereof are doubtful and uncertain, and according to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſal of the Statute; and there a general Statute is conſtrued particularly, upon conſideration had of the cauſe of making the Act, and of the rehearſal of all the parts of the Act,</hi> &amp;c. 4 Inſtit. cap. 74. It is a general Rule allowed by all Laws in conſtruction of Statutes, <hi>Quamvis lex generaliter loquatur, reſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genda tamen eſt ut ceſſante ratione &amp; ipſa ceſſet, cum enim ratio ſit Anima vigorque ipſius legis, non videtur Legiſlator id ſenſiſſe quod ratione careat etiamſi Verbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum generalitas, prima facie aliter ſuadeat:</hi> Idem. Ibidem.</p>
            <p>And for the Book-caſe related to, and the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence made therefrom, hear what a learned perſon has delivered very fully and appoſitely concerning that: (not in anſwer to this Judges opinion) for he wrote many years before him; but to invalidate an Aſſertion of the ſame nature with this, and from the ſame Book-caſe, <hi>viz.</hi> 5 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 6. <hi>praemunire.</hi> and made by one he then contended with) <hi>This caſe does but ſpeak of the Excommunication by a Biſhop, and not of every dealing whatſoever in a matter belonging to the Kings Regality; and what if it had been twice ſo adjudged, both of them in ſuch corrupt times, when as the Royal Prerogative of the Kings of this Land to be Supreme Governors in all Juriſdiction Eccleſiaſtical, due to them in Right, and by Gods Law, was not</hi> de facto <hi>united to the Crown:
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:53134:53"/>For the Biſhops then did not claim their Juriſdiction Eccleſiaſtical, next and immediately under God, from the Crown, as now they do; but ſeeing this part of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal power, is now no leſs truly and fully veſted in the Crown, than is the Temporal; ſo as the Laws allowed for the Eccleſiaſtical Government, are termed by ſundry Parliaments, the Queens Eccleſiaſtical Laws, and Laws of this Realm, as well as thoſe that were firſt originally made here: And the Biſhops are proved to have their Authority and Juriſdiction Eccleſiaſtical derived down unto them from the Queens Highneſs under the Great Seal of</hi> England. <hi>Is it then the like reaſon, ſtill to compriſe their Juriſdictions and Courts under that word of</hi> [Alibi] <hi>as if their Courts and Juriſdictions were not now the Queens, nor yet belonging to Her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality?</hi> Coſen. Apol. p. 3. ch. 7.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, the holding plea of a matter belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the common Law by an Eccleſiaſtical Judge, (ſo conſtituted as he ought to be, and now is) does not tend to the diſinheriſion of the Crown; that is, not to the impairing of any Regality, Power or Preheminence belonging to the ſame, and therefore cannot be the crime of <hi>praemunire.</hi> The Statute 25 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. declares concerning whom, and how offending the Statute of the 16 <hi>Richard ſecundi,</hi> was framed, namely, ſuch as ſue to the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> againſt the Kings Crown and Dignity Royal; one Statute beſt explains another. So then, where the Authority that is acted by, is the ſame, a miſtake in the matter to be proceeded upon, or manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in, does not infringe that authority: The reaſon is, becauſe the Kings authority empowring to act, is ſtill acknowledged; and what is judicially done thereby, proceeds by power derived from
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:53134:53"/>Him, not from any power ſet up againſt him. I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume it will be readily granted, That the upholding and ſecuring the Kings Supremacy in all cauſes, and over all perſons, is that, which principally, if not ſolely, is aimed at by this Statute: And then it plainly follows, that where that Supremacy is main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, no breach of that Statute can be made, nor penalty incur'd by any, for a miſtake only of the matter, that any Plea (in Subordination to the King as Supream) is held upon.</p>
            <p>The worſt that is to be ſaid in this caſe, is this, That he who being a ſpiritual Judge, does take cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance of any temporal matter, offends in going beyond his Commiſſion; and truly this is bad enough, but not ſo bad neither, as to bring under the guilt of <hi>praemunire:</hi> If it were, obſerve the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, what that would be; for it would as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly and unavoidably expoſe a temporal Judge to the penalty of a <hi>praemunire,</hi> if he proceed to hear and determine in a matter of Eccleſiaſtical cognizance (becauſe that is beyond his Commiſſion) as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> would expoſe a ſpiritual Judge to the ſame penalty, that he intermeddles with cauſes of temporal cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zunce; for obſerve well what <hi>Bracton</hi> ſayes in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to both Juriſdictions, and the proper Judges of each — <hi>Cum diverſi ſint hinc inde Juriſdictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; diverſi Judices, &amp; diverſae cauſae, debet quili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet ipſorum imprimis aeſtimare, an ſua ſit Juriſdictio, ne falcem videatur ponere in Meſſem alienam.</hi> Again, <hi>Non pertinet ad Judices Soeculares, non pertinet cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcere de iis quae ſunt ſpiritualibus annexa ſicut de de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimis,</hi> &amp;c. Bract. l. 5. c. 2. apud Hookerum Eccleſiaſt. Pol. lib. 8. p. 218. I may be thought to have made a ſtrange, confident, and odd inverſion upon theſe
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:53134:54"/>two caſes; but for my ſhare, freely I do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that it is above the reach of my reaſon, to conceive of any difference herein; for as both Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Eccleſiaſtical Courts are now conſtituted, deriving from the ſame Regal Supremacy, that the Temporal Courts do; the conſequence is as good on one hand, as on the other.</p>
            <p>Indeed I ſhould not have expoſed my ſelf to the cenſure of being thought too bold in the concerns of Temporal Courts, and Temporal Judges, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in ſuch an inverſion as this, ſo lyable to be frown'd upon: But the truth is, I found it made to my hand, by the perſon whoſe name I have often uſed, and whoſe Authority I much depend upon: <hi>Is not</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>the Prerogative Royal in and for cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, as high and as rightly ſetled in the Prince, and incident to Her Highneſs Crown and Rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, as the ſame is for Temporal power and authority? What cauſe is there then, ſeeing</hi> [ſeu alibi] <hi>in the Statute ſignifieth (in true conſtruction) any place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hatſoever beſides</hi> Rome: <hi>That every holding Plea by an Eccleſiaſtical Court, of a matter wherein it ought not to hold, ſhould at this time be reckoned a thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Queens Regality, more than dealing in any Eccleſiaſtical cauſe, ſhould be in any temporal Court at</hi> Weſtminſter? <hi>for no Statute of proviſion or</hi> praemu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire, <hi>aſſigneth theſe for cauſes; which have indeed, grown ſince by collections, whil'ſt the Popes uſurpation was continued in the Land. Againſt which oftentimes, the Remedy by prohibition could not ſerve the turn:</hi> Coſen. Apol. par. 3. ch. 7. p. 87.</p>
            <p>But admit the worſt, let there be a diſparity al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, let the failing be on the Eccleſiaſtical Judges ſide, yet ſtill he is the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Judge;
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:53134:54"/>And there is a favour alwayes on a Judges ſide, ſo far as to preſume, That he is fit to Act in what he is appointed to; and that he does Act according to what he is beſt informed of, by his skill, and from his conſcience. <hi>Sacrilegii inſtar eſt dubitare an is Dignus ſit, quem Imperator elegerit;</hi> That perſons merit and integrity is not to be doubted of, whom his Princes will has appointed to any publick Office and Employment, ſay the Emperors <hi>Grat. Valent. &amp; Theod. in Leg. Tertia. C. de crimine Sacrilegii.</hi> Now it is not to be rationally ſuppoſed, that any one exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing the Office of a Judge, will deſignedly and purpoſely hold Plea of ſuch a cauſe, which he either knows to be, or is propounded to him as, belonging to Temporal cognizance: But it may ſo happen, that by nearneſs and coherence of one cauſe with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that which indeed is a Temporal, may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be an Eccleſiaſtical cauſe; and if an Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Judge, minding to do his duty, as the nature of <hi>his office doth require, do yet by reſemblance, and near coherence of one cauſe with another, proceed in that which is Temporal, ſhall this preſently caſt him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a</hi> Praemunire? That is, ſhall the exceeding ſome bounds and limits that the Prince (under whom he exerciſes Juriſdiction) has preſcribed to him, bring him under ſuch puniſhments, as the very enemies and underminers of his State are to endure? This certainly were very harſh and rigorous. I know nothing more to be declined, than ſuch an Office, where the exerciſe of it puts a man into that tickliſh and tottering condition, That he is ready every day (without that exact circumſpection, as is morally impoſſible, for the carefulleſt man alive alwayes to have) to fall into the greateſt penalties and dangers.
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:53134:55"/>It has been ſaid, That a corrivality betwixt the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical and common Lawyer, has ſtill made the one ſeek his own elevation, by the depreſſion of the other: But here, the common Lawyer has got an inſuperable advantage over the other; for let him but hold to this Opinion, and by his Authority make it good, That the bare holding Plea of a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral cauſe in an Eccleſiaſtical Court, makes liable to the penalties of <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>munire,</hi> and the conteſt is at end: There will then be few, that will care to ſtudy the Eccleſiaſtical Laws; fewer, that will dare to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute any Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction.</p>
            <p>A grave and ſober perſon delivers his mind tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this matter, with a great deal of ingenuous freedom and truth: <hi>Hoc Auſterum ſupplicium</hi> (ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Braemunire</hi>) <hi>aliqui Juriſperiti noſtri, Lucri &amp; Ambitionis aeſtu accenſi, verborum, quae in uno Statuto, obſervant generalitatem, ad quemvis levem Judicum lapſum, praeſertim Eccleſiaſticorum, nimis violenter extendunt, ſed hic corum candorem deſideramus, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quorum etiam inſcitiam lugemus.</hi> Dr. Cowell Inſtit. de Publicis Judicis. Sect. 43.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James,</hi> a wiſe and diſcerning Prince, eaſily diſcovered the Grievances that this profeſſion la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured under, and was pleaſed earneſtly to concern himſelf in redreſſing of them. This great King ſpeaking of the uſefulneſs of the Civil and Canon Law among His own Subjects in matters of Pyracy, Wills, Marriages, and things of like nature, proceeds thus—<hi>And this Law has been ſo much encroached up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſithence my coming to the Crown, and ſo had in contempt, that young men are diſcouraged from ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, and the reſt weary of their lives that do profeſs it, and would be glad to ſeek any other
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:53134:55"/>craft</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">K. <hi>James</hi>'s Speech in the Star. Chamber to the Judges, about the 14th year of His Reign.</note> And ſome pages after in the ſame ſpeech, when He comes to give His particular charge to the Judges, he has theſe words, <hi>What greater miſery can there be to the Law, than contempt of the Law; and what readier way to contempt, then when queſtions come, what ſhall be determined in this Court, and what in that? whereupon two Evils do ariſe, the one, that men come not now to Courts of Juſtice to hear matters of right pleaded, and Decrees given accordingly: But only out of a curioſity to hear queſtions of the Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions of Courts diſputed, and to ſee the event, which Court is like to prevail above the other; and the other evil that does ariſe, is this, That Plea's are turned from Court to Court, in an endleſs circular motion, as upon</hi> Ixions <hi>wheel; and this was the reaſon why I found juſt fault with that multitude of prohibitions.</hi> And then having given a notable inſtance relating to what He had before ſpoken of in the concern of Eccleſiaſtical cauſes, and their being turn'd off, and toſſed from Court to Court, He gives this direction to the Judges—<hi>Therefore the only way to avoid this, is, for you to keep your own bounds, and nouriſh not the people in contempt of other Courts, but teach them Reverence to Courts, in your publick Speeches, both in your Benches, and in your Circuits:</hi> Such was the rare providence of that wiſe King, to keep up the Eſteem of the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, and with fair countenance, and good encouragement, to cheriſh the Profeſſors of the Eccleſiaſtical Laws; for the Eccleſiaſtical Laws are ſuch, that, as Himſelf is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to teſtifie in another place of the ſame Speech, <hi>in many caſes cannot be wanting in his Kingdom:</hi> Not permitting any encroachments to be made thereon; much leſs, that the Profeſſors and Judges thereof
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:53134:56"/>ſhould be terrified at every turn, and awed with the heavieſt poenal inflictions, upon the leaſt irregular motion, and undue proceeding; eſpecially ſince o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther milder, yet as effectual means are provided to rectifie ſuch irregularities, and reduce them to the right courſe again.</p>
            <p>For the wiſdom of our Princes, has by expreſs proviſion of Law, ſo well ordered both Juriſdictions, that as both flow from them, ſo both ſhall be kept (to prevent confuſion in either) within their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per bounds; and therefore if the Eccleſiaſtical Judge intermeddles with any thing that appertains not to his Juriſdiction, the ſame Royal Hand that gave forth other things to him, reſtrains him in that. And thus by Writs of Prohibition, the Eccleſiaſtical Judge is ſtopped from proceeding in that which is reſerved for another Tribunal. And if it were not thus, to what end would Prohibitions ſerve? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were they invented? why ſhould ſo ſolemn a proceeding be, before they are granted? why ſo long debating and conſulting, before they ceaſe and loſe their force? Laſtly, why not laid aſide as ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous and needleſs things, after <hi>Praemunire</hi> was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed?</p>
            <p>In the third year of King <hi>James,</hi> certain Articles of Complaint were Exhibited by Archbiſhop <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croft,</hi> before the Kings Majeſty, and His moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Privy Council, touching Abuſes in grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prohibitions. The matter mainly canvaſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Judges of both Juriſdictions, was, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the right ſtating and ſetling the reaſons and grounds of granting Prohibitions: All along which conteſt, there is not any the leaſt mention made of Prohibitions granted with reſpect to the perſons
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:53134:56"/>who were impleaded, but only on the Account of the incompetency of the matter or cauſe which they were impleaded upon; whereas it is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged on both ſides, that where a matter truly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to the Temporal Juriſdiction, is brought into Plea before the Eccleſiaſtical Judge, there any further proceeding in the ſame, is, and ought to be reſtrained by the Writ of Prohibition; but it is not ſaid at all, that the penalty of <hi>Praemunire</hi> is incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thereby.</p>
            <p>And here let me entreat the Reader to fix his eye and underſtanding a little more intenſely upon that which now follows. In the twenty fifth and laſt of thoſe Articles, it is thus ſet down <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Sir <hi>Ed. Coke,</hi> ſecond part of the Inſtitutes of the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> p. 617.</note>: — <hi>Whereas for the better preſerving of His Majeſties two Supreme Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictions before mentioned,</hi> viz. <hi>the Eccleſiaſtical and the Temporal; that the one might not uſurp upon the other, two means heretofore have been of ancient time ordained, that is to ſay, the cenſure of Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Writ of Prohibition; the one to reſtrain the encroachment of the Temporal Juriſdiction upon the Eccleſiaſtical, the other of the Eccleſiaſtical upon the Temporal: We moſt humbly deſire your Lordſhips, that by your means, the Judges may be induced to reſolve us, why Excommunications may not as freely be put in ure for the preſervation of the Juriſdiction Eccleſiaſtical, as Prohibitions are under pretence to defend the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, eſpecially againſt ſuch contentious perſons, as do uittingly and willingly, upon falſe and frivolous ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to the delay of Juſtice, vexation of the Subjects, and great ſcandal of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, daily procure, without fear either of God or me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due Prohibitions as we have heretofore mentioned.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:53134:57"/>
            <p>At the reading of this Article, I was in great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation what Anſwer would be given thereto, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that the buſineſs of reſtraining either Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictions encroaching on the other, was thus brought to a ſhort and plain iſſue; for ſo it ſeems, that if either the Eccleſiaſtical Court encroached on the Temporal, or the Temporal Court encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Eccleſiaſtical, the coercive means applyable for the reſtraint of either, were reſpectively theſe two; <hi>viz. the cenſure of Excommunication, and the Writ of Prohibition;</hi> but <hi>Praemunire</hi> is not mentioned at all.</p>
            <p>But come we to the Anſwer it ſelf, and therein we find a full and ample conceſſion of all that is ſet down in the Article, and ſo, as it is ſet down there; what the Eccleſiaſtical Judges had deſired to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in, is granted to them according to the very ſtating thereof propoſed by them; Take the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer in the very words thereof ſet down by the ſame Author—<hi>The Excommunication cannot be gainfaid, neither may the Prohibition he denyed upon ſurmiſe made, that the matter purſued in the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Court, is of Temporal cognizance; but as ſoon as that ſhall appear unto us judicially to be falſe, we grant the conſultation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A thrifty improver of Advantages, would find this conceſſion uſeful to him, in making and urging many inferences from thence to ſerve well his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; but the intelligent Reader cannot but have his thoughts full of them, and I ſhall therefore for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear the propoſing of any; only this I ſay, That by what was ſet down in the Article, and by what is declared in the Anſwer to it, there appears plai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That <hi>Encroachers</hi> on the Spiritual Juriſdiction, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:53134:57"/>as ſubject to <hi>Excommunication,</hi> as <hi>Encroachers</hi> on the Temporal Juriſdiction are ſubject to <hi>Prohibitions.</hi> That which my preſent deſign leads me to, is to conclude from hence, That ſince <hi>Prohibitions</hi> are by Law the means of reſtraining any <hi>Encroachments</hi> on the Temporal Juriſdiction, therefore <hi>Praemunire</hi> does not lie in that caſe. And indeed how ſhould it? for is not every Eccleſiaſtical Court, the Kings Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Court? and the Laws Eccleſiaſtical, are they not the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Laws? And if in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe Laws by the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, there ſhould happen any exceeding of due limits in thoſe Courts (as who can ſay of any Court that it never exceeds?) yet <hi>Praemunire</hi> cannot lie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; for, as I may very well apply that which King <hi>James</hi> ſaid (in that Speech of His which I mentioned before) when ſome buſie Sticklers were active and forward in fixing a <hi>Praemunire</hi> upon the Officers of the Chancery) <hi>No</hi> Praemunire, <hi>ſayes He, can be granted, but at the Kings Suit; and how can the King grant a</hi> Praemunire <hi>againſt Himſelf?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Court of Admiralty, many more Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are brought, than in the Eccleſiaſtical Courts. There is a greater vicinity and likeneſs betwixt the matters tryable in that Court, and thoſe tryable at common Law, and conſequently greater occaſion and probability of miſtaking: Now certainly ſuch frequency of Prohibitions, with the conſequences of them, would be very dilatory and tedious, if the more compendious way of <hi>Praemunire</hi> were effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; and why not <hi>Praemunire</hi> lie here, as well as in the Court Chriſtian? This is another Court, or a Court under the large meaning of <hi>[Alibi]</hi> proceedings are divers therein from thoſe of the common Law;
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:53134:58"/>and I do not remember to have read any <hi>Praemunire</hi> brought for ſuing in the Admiralty, excepting in two caſes, the one 38 <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. the other in 9 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>Nevertheleſs,</hi> ſaith Dr. <hi>Zouch, although it be ſaid that two</hi> Praemunires <hi>were brought upon ſuch occaſions, yet it doth not appear, that any judgment was given upon them:</hi> See more to this purpoſe, in his Juriſdiction of the Admiralty aſſerted.</p>
            <p>But never to mince the matter, Is it not here that the Shooe wrings? It is the Eccleſiaſtical Court, and that is become the great Eye-ſore; a thing that will not be looked upon as an offence in another Court, is beheld by men through a magnifying Glaſs in this: There are too many that cannot away at any hand with a Biſhops Juriſdiction, and what they do not like, they eaſily quarrel at; hence are all the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices, that upon very little occaſions are taken up, and yet, though good reaſons be given, are hardly laid down again. The Spiritual Court ſhall be ſure to have all the opprobrious, and all the ſcurrilous imputations faſtned to it. Men love thoſe ſins too dearly, that are puniſhable there; and they love to hold too tenaciouſly thoſe rights from others, that are recoverable there: Now no Delinquent loves that Judge who co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rects him for the ſin he loves to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntinue in; or will force from him the rights of others, which he has no mind to part withall. I wiſh it have not been from theſe, or any other ſuch gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unds, that the Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction has had ſo many oppoſites; <hi>and that there has been ſuch lying at catch, and waiting for advantages againſt it,</hi> ſo as to terrifie with the name of <hi>Praemunire,</hi> whenſoever men have a mind to ſay there is (or that there is indeed) ſome real miſcarriage therein.</p>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:53134:58"/>
            <p>Thus far I have enlarged, in making good the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Propoſition; I ſhall collect together under one view, what has been delivered thereon. It was not the matter of any civil contract, but a cauſe indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putably of Eccleſiaſtical cognizance, that was the ground of theſe proceedings, and therefore no <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire</hi> imputable on that Accompt; and admitting the contract had been the ground of theſe proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, yet for the reaſons before ſhewed, no <hi>Praemu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire</hi> could have been incurr'd hereby; and therefore the Biſhop of <hi>Waterford</hi>'s Juriſdiction in the caſe before laid down, was legally founded in reſpect of the cauſe proceeded upon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PROP. III.</hi> The Biſhops Juriſdiction was le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally managed in this cauſe, againſt theſe perſons, in reſpect of the manner obſerved and followed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. It was in favour to the Mayor and Sheriffs, that a civil intimation was given to them from the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, deſiring their meeting with him. This civil intimation was (I will not ſay deſpiſed) but not anſwered with a correſpondent civility in them; for they did not give the meeting to the Biſhop, which he deſired they would. And yet the end of this deſired meeting, was in order to a fair accompting for Moneys received by them for the Churches uſe, and for making good the reparation of the Body of the Cathedral Church: They not giving (I ſay) the Biſhop this deſired meeting, ſome competent time afterwards (I think a weeks ſpace interve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) Proceſs was cauſed to iſſue forth, to call them to appear before the Biſhop in his Conſiſtory, on a certain day after following.</p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:53134:59"/>
            <p>I cannot go forward to the ſequele of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding thus begun, without making ſome little ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſion on theſe perſons (I ſhall forbear giving it any worſe term) diſingenuous carriage, in their <hi>Petition of Complaint Exhibited to the Lord Deputy and Council:</hi> In the firſt Section of which, they ſay, <hi>That they the Petitioners about Ten of the Clock in the Forenoon, on the twentieth of</hi> July <hi>laſt, received a Verbal Summons from the Apparator of the Dioceſs of</hi> Waterford, <hi>to Appear at the Conſiſtory Court of the ſaid Dioceſs, before the Lord Biſhop of</hi> Waterford <hi>at Two of the clock the ſame day</hi>—</p>
            <p>The diſingenuity that I obſerve herein, is moſt notorious; for firſt, they ſpeak of a <hi>Verbal Summons</hi> from an Apparator; than which, nothing can be more ridiculous (ſhall I ſay) or more falſe. 'Tis both contrary to practice for any <hi>Verbal Summons</hi> to be given, by an Apparator to any perſon; and it is of no force, nor validity, if any ſuch were given; and it is contrary to Truth, that any ſuch was given. The Biſhop of <hi>Waterford</hi> better underſtands both what is the ordinary practice, and what will hold good, and is juſtifiable in practice; than to order his Apparator, to call any of his Dioceſs before him, (without a formal Proceſs) by <hi>Verbal Summons</hi> only.</p>
            <p>Next, it is ſaid, <hi>That this Verbal Summons was given at Ten of the clock in the Forenoon, to appear at Two of the clock in the Afternoon of the ſame day.</hi> Here is diſingenuity again: There being no Accord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt what is thus alledged, and the Acts of Court that have been expedited in this proceeding; I have made it my endeavour carefully to conſult theſe, and find, that an Original Citation iſſued out of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtry
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:53134:59"/>againſt theſe perſons, to appear on <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> the 22d of <hi>July,</hi> betwixt the hours of Eight and Ten in the Forenoon of the ſame day: And I find, that this Citation was executed on the perſons of theſe men, by one <hi>Michael Curren,</hi> the uſual Manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary of the Court (according as he declared upon Oath) on the 21 day of the Month of <hi>July,</hi> which was <hi>Tueſday.</hi> This is the firſt Act of proceedings in this cauſe, and if we will credit that (as it is atteſted by the Regiſter, a Sworn Officer, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Publick) then the firſt Section of the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as it relates to theſe proceedings, contains no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Truth in it.</p>
            <p>And as little there is in the firſt part of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Section; for, whereas the Petitioners ſay, <hi>That on the Two and twentieth of the ſaid Month, they were Summoned to Appear at Ten of the clock at the ſaid Court the ſame day.</hi> — The falſity of this appears plainly, by what the aforeſaid Mandatary upon Oath declared, namely, That he had Summoned them on the <hi>Tueſday;</hi> which <hi>Tueſday,</hi> was the One and twentieth, not the Two and twentieth of <hi>July.</hi> And the ground of complaint had been tolerable indeed, if the time of their Summoning, and time of their Appearance had jump't together at one and the ſame hour.</p>
            <p>I now go on further, in drawing out the courſe and ſeries of this Judicial proceeding. The day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come, that is to ſay, <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the 22d of <hi>July,</hi> at which time the forementioned Proceſs was retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and the Biſhop ſitting in his Conſiſtory, the perſons Summoned were called upon, who not Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, their Contumacy was accordingly accuſed, and upon the Accuſation, by Decree of Court, they were pronounced contumacious.</p>
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:53134:60"/>
            <p>The Legality of this manner of proceeding thus far, is ſufficiently known by common practice; and <hi>Lindwood</hi> gives this Rule <hi>(Conſtitut. Provincial. Item omnes: de Judiciis. ad literam F.) ubi aliquis apprehenſus eſt perſonali citatione, ſi ſic citatus perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naliter non compareat efficitur verè contumax.</hi> And the 70th Canon of the Church of <hi>Ireland, allows a Contumacy to be affixed to that perſon who neglects to appear upon citation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have heard, that there was afterwards ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing alledged on their behalf, why they could not appear upon that Summons; and ſomething they ſay in the ſecond Section of their Petition to this purpoſe: <hi>As, that a Council of the City had been ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed againſt that time to conſult about an Anſwer to a Letter ſent by the Lord Deputy.</hi> But two things come here into obſervation, whence it ſeems proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that this matter was made uſe of at a pinch, and ſo to ſerve as a little evaſive ſhift, when there was nothing elſe that could ſeemingly help them; for as they mentioned in the firſt Section of their Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, this Letter was delivered to them from the Lord Deputy the <hi>Monday</hi> before, now the anſwering of that, would not, I ſuppoſe, be delayed until <hi>Wedneſday;</hi> and that very hour of <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> when upon due Summons before perſonally ſerved, they were to appear at the Biſhops Conſiſtory. But, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, it is more then to be preſumed, that the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of their Council (if any ſuch were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed) then upon <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> and at that hour was deſigned as a colour wherewith they might be helped to elude their appearance upon the ſaid Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:53134:60"/>
            <p>Moreover, had they been really engaged in ſo neceſſary and earneſt a buſineſs, yet that could give no hindrance; but they might haye ſent ſome cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditable perſon to make <hi>Affidavit</hi> of their being ſo employed, which thing, in all probability, would have cauſed a reſpiting of their Appearance at that time: <hi>Yes, but they did ſend a Meſſenger</hi> (ſayes the Petition) <hi>who acquainted the Biſhop with the reaſon of their not appearing:</hi> But if any ſuch Meſſenger were ſent, he ſtood there <hi>incognito,</hi> and was as a Mute in the company; for no one did, nor offered to make <hi>Affidavit</hi> theteof.</p>
            <p>Add further, <hi>Wedneſday morning at Ten of the clock was the time they were called to appear at</hi> (ſayes the very Petition it ſelf) but the tenor of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, is betwixt the hours of Eight and Ten: They were buſie at Ten of the Clock to diſpatch their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, yet the Poſt is uſually gone at that time. They were not buſie at Eight, or between Eight and Nine, and then too, their Appearance had been good. What ſhall we think hereof? Truly by all that I can conceive hereof, there could be no ſufficient Allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion grounded hereon, to free them from being in contempt for Non-appearance upon Legal Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
            <p>But allow they had been really aggrieved by this proceeding, and that there being declared contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, had been illegal; Remedy there was for this; a regular courſe might have been taken, which if applied to, would have given redreſs herein: An Appeal to the Archbiſhop of the Province, would have done both theſe. This the Biſhop would not, nay, could not deny them: And if the ground of their Appeal were juſtifiable, they would by that
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:53134:61"/>means have been reſcued from the Biſhops, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected under the Archbiſhops, Juriſdiction. This courſe, I have been told, was ſuggeſted to them; but the Truth is, it reliſhed too much of condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to give any ſhew of ſubmiſſion to Eccleſiaſtical power: High ſpirits will rather want, than be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden for, help, to that hand which they do not like of. Perhaps theſe perſons, lifted up with an Opinion of their Office, as they thought themſelves a degree above the being proceeded againſt by a Biſhop, ſo it would be beneath them, to ſupplicate for any relief from an Archbiſhop.</p>
            <p>Well, upon this, a ſecond Proceſs iſſues out, to call them to Appear, and ſhew cauſe, if they had any, why for their former contempt, they ought not to undergo the penalty of a cenſure. Upon this Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons they appear, yet not a ledging any material, or rationally concluſive Plea, for purging their former contempt, they are upon the accompt thereof en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned an eaſie penance: This only; to make an acknowledgment of their contempt and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and to promiſe future Obedience.</p>
            <p>The Heats before conceived in theſe mens breaſts, and hitherto ſuppreſſed, now break out with ſome violence: They fume and chafe at this impoſition, and diſdain, That Men in their Dignity, being the Kings Lieutenants (ſo they ſtiled themſelves) ſhould be brought to make a publick acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſubmiſſion.</p>
            <p>I am verily perſwaded, that if any reaſonable ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication had been made to the Biſhop by theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſome private acknowledgment and ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion tendred, an eaſie compoſure of what had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, would have followed: But the doing of this
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:53134:61"/>was ſo far from their Reſolves, that a friendly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and propoſal thereof, was with ſcorn rejected. The time appointed for making this Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment comes; and as it came, ſo it paſſed away with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any obſervance of what was enjoyned.</p>
            <p>This repeated contempt might have diſordered a well compoſed temper, but it had no power upon the Biſhop; alter him a little it might (how could it well be otherwiſe) but not ſo as to exaſperate that ſpirit of Lenity, which (as he ought, ſo) he alwayes moderated himſelf by, in matters of cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and other parts of corrective Diſcipline. It directed him indeed to reflect on the Authority he was inveſted withall, and how ſcandalouſly it was deſpiſed; and that the Rod was to be taken in hand, and ſomething at leaſt to be done in a way of correction, that men might not be diſobedient and refractory, and then think they had done well in being ſo; Authority contemned, and paſſing with impunity, uſhers in both Atheiſm and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>Wherefore that more ſevere and dreadful cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Excommunication being laid aſide, it may be (as for other reaſons) ſo upon this conſideration likewiſe, that they might not be diſcapacitated in the execution of their Offices. This great cenſure, I ſay, being laid aſide, another is made uſe of, that with ingenuous Chriſtians might probably attain the end intended, being tempered with more mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and lenity. The cenſure was this: <hi>The perſons ſo offending were ſuſpended</hi> ab ingreſſu in Eccleſiam, <hi>till ſuch time as they had made publick ſatisfaction for the ſcandal given, by their contempt and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:53134:62"/>
            <p>If it ſhould be here ſaid, That the cenſure of ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion <hi>ab ingreſſu in Eccleſiam</hi> (though it be a milder cenſure far than the other) was improperly inflicted in this caſe, becauſe Excommunication is the poenal coercion appropriated to this crime of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; and if that contempt were really ſo ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and notorious, why was not the penalty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, <hi>pro rata culpae?</hi> Beſides, there is ſeldom men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this kind of cenſure, but in one caſe, and that ſet down in the Statute Law, <hi>viz.</hi> 6 <hi>Edvard. ſexti. cap.</hi> 4. impoſed on ſuch as are Brawlers in Churches and Church-yards; but of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation it is ſaid—<hi>Aliarum cenſurarum Eccleſiaſtica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum una,</hi> viz. <hi>Excommunicatio infligitur pro contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia ſola, vel non comparendo in judicio, vel non paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do mandatis Eccleſiae. Dr.</hi> Coſen. Polit. Eccleſ. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glic. Tab. 5. A. Which being ſo, and not applied in the caſe where it ought, thence the proceedings in this cauſe become irregular and illegal.</p>
            <p>To all this it may be returned, firſt, That lenity is there unhappily placed, where they that have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by it, would turn it to the prejudice of thoſe that beſtow it. Beſides, Admit that the cenſure of Excommunication might juſtly have been inflicted in this caſe, on theſe perſons (which moſt certainly might have been) yet the not impoſing that, does not vitiate the proceedings, and make them become irregular and illegal; for this ſuſpenſion is a kind of Excommunication: and although by the Statute, it ſeem peculiarly appropriated to the crime of <hi>braw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and quarrelling in Church, or Church-yards;</hi> yet that, I conceive, is to be underſtood in this ſenſe, That no other cenſure ſhall be inflicted upon that crime, but the ſame cenſure may be inflicted on
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:53134:62"/>other crimes beſides, and ſo conſequently on this, which it was inflicted on here. Suſpenſion I ſaid was a kind of Excommunication, ſome call it <hi>Minor Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicatio (Cowell, word. Suſpenſion)</hi> it is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree below that which is uſually called by that name; for a man being deprived of a liberty of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to Church, he is thereby deprived of all pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickcommunion with the reſt of Gods faithful peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in partaking of the Word and Sacraments, and all other divine Offices. It is called by ſome <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictio divinorum illata in perſonas,</hi> to diſtinguiſh from that which is the interdiction of a place. <hi>Zouch. de Jure Eccleſiaſtico.</hi> part. 2. ſect. 8.</p>
            <p>There are two things wherein this cenſure of Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion differs from Excommunication properly ſo called (I ſpeak here only as to things <hi>in foro exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> in reſpect of outward practice and proceeding thereupon) 1. Becauſe the Secular Arm cannot be implored, or called upon for it. 2. Becauſe it does not render a perſon, on whom it was impoſed, ſo incapable in ſundry reſpects of Secular matters, as the other does. Nor indeed does the Rule laid down before, ſo preciſely bind the Eccleſiaſtical Judge to a literal obſervance of it, that no other cenſure in ſuch a caſe may be uſed inſtead thereof: But it is within the latitude of his Authority, That if there be hopes of attaining the ends of this grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cenſure (as the reducing of refractory and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacious perſons) by inflicting the leſſer: And if there be a concurrency of other peculiar reſpects, beſides, inducing the Judge to uſe that leſſer, then ſurely the greater may be abſtained from, and the courſe and manner of proceedings, ſtill be good and juſtifiable.</p>
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:53134:63"/>
            <p>I have been the longer in removing this Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that might be made againſt the Biſhops proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as to the manner of them, in this particular; becauſe I have heard ſomething debated touching the ſame, and I have had ſome doubtings thereof in my ſelf; but as this cenſure was (I verily believe) with great deliberation, and prudent reſolve inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Biſhop; ſo I am now fully ſatisfied there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, both in reſpect of the nature of it, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of proceeding to the inflicting of it.</p>
            <p>For the coming of things to this head (we muſt know) was not precipitous, and hudled up all on a ſudden; five ſeveral Court-dayes were employed in this Tranſaction: betwixt every of which, fair and competent intervals of time were allowed; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, I muſt needs ſay, conſidering all circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, leſſer time might have ſerved, Canonically enough, to diſpatch a matter of as great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as this <note n="*" place="margin">In the Iſle of <hi>Man,</hi> the Eccleſiaſtical Judge makes much ſhorter w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k; <hi>In hac inſala Judex Eccleſiaſticus, citat, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fi it, &amp; infra octo Dies parent, aut carceri intruduntur.</hi> Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> 4 part. Inſtit. c. 69.</note>: But the Biſhop reſolved (I ſuppoſe) to move circumſpectly and deliberatively in what he Decreed, and therefore took time enough for it; and he deſired, that they whom he had to deal withall, would be tractable, regular and adviſed, in what they ought to have done, and ſo he gave them time enough likewiſe.</p>
            <p>So then, to the inflicting this cenſure was this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter brought. The paſſing of which, the publicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it in the forementioned Cathedral, at due time, and in due manner. The particular intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof given to the perſons themſelves, the grave admonition following to obey the ſame, and retract their former contempts and refractorineſs. All theſe notwithſtanding, the Mayor and Sheriffs the next <hi>Sunday</hi> following come to Church, in an
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:53134:63"/>unwonted, ſtrange and tumultuous manner, attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a confuſed and numerous Rabble of ſuch as had not uſed to viſit the Church at all; nor would then have done it, but that they were countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, nay, commanded, indeed t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> attend the Kings Sword (ſuch a phraſe they uſed) but ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, proved a diſorderly and heady meeting to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>Thus was the Church cenſure contemn'd, baffl'd, trampled upon. Thus was Epiſcopal power expoſed to deriſion and mockery. Thus was the Kings Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in His Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, debaſed and made vile, by thoſe that gave themſelves out to be the great upholders of it, in matters of civil Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; and after all, to make a ſhew of innocency in this whole proceeding, they ſpeed in all haſte to complain firſt, and would have it thought an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their being injuriouſly dealt withall (ſo deſtitute were they of any other) becauſe they have got the ſtart, and cry out loudeſt that they are ſo. They repreſent themſelves as perſons (above any example) the moſt unjuſtly dealt withall, and aggrieved, <hi>by ſtrange, arbitrary, and unheard of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</hi> Their Addreſs was made to His Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy Council in this Kingdom, there they Exhibit their Complaint, thence they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect relief: The Biſhop owns the Kings Authority whereſoever, and in whomſoever it is repreſented, but eſpecially in that High and moſt Honourable Aſſembly; and ſo ſubmits him ſelf and proceedings to the determination, that by their Lordſhips ſhould be made thereof.</p>
            <p>I muſt not omit that to make ſure work, beſides this Addreſs, the pretending Complainants, become
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:53134:64"/>Appellants; for they interpoſe an Appeal <hi>in Scriptis,</hi> from the Biſhop, immediately to the King; that if one courſe they had taken failed, the other, at leaſt might be helpful to them. I cannot paſs by (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I do but touch at them) the many Errors concurring in this latter Eſſay: As that firſt the time of Appealing, from that which they pretended themſelves aggrieved with, was lapſed, when this Appeal was interpoſed. Moreover, that one and the ſame cauſe, by the ſame perſons, at the ſame time, was thus brought to tryal before two diſtinct Judicatories, which is vexatious, at leaſt, in thoſe that procure the ſame to be done ſo.</p>
            <p>That the intermediate Juriſdiction was paſſed by, contrary to the ancient liberties and cuſtoms in ſuch caſes obſerved; and which was among other matters digeſted into Articles and Chapters, confirmed in the Parliament held at <hi>Clarendon,</hi> in the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> 2d, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1164. namely, <hi>That all Appeals in</hi> England <hi>muſt proceed regularly, from the Archdeacon to the Biſhop, from the Biſhop to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop; and if the Archbiſhop failed to do juſtice, the laſt complaint muſt be to the King to give order for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs; that is (ſayes my Lord Primate</hi> Bramhall, <hi>Vindication of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>p.</hi> 75.) <hi>by fit Delegates.</hi> See to this purpoſe, <hi>The Statute of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals,</hi> 24 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. And this contrary to the 56 <hi>Canon</hi> of this Church, <hi>Whereby the pain of Nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is inflicted on all Acts, which are ſped in Appeals, where the Juriſdiction intermediate is paſſed by;</hi> for although it is true, That the Kings Authority ought not to be diſputed, or diſobeyed by any Subject, where it does appear to be; yet that muſt ever be eſteemed <hi>a true and regular obedience,</hi> which the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:53134:64"/>King himſelf by Law has preſcribed, it ſhould be.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, ſuppoſing the Appeal entred by them to have been antecedently good, that is, good in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of time and manner obſerved in interpoſing the ſame; yet it is not good nor valid in its conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, becauſe the time appointed for theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Appellants to receive their <hi>Apoſtles</hi> (that is, <hi>dimiſſory Letters</hi> from the Biſhop or Judge <hi>Aquo,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating his deferring and yielding to the ſaid Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, and aſſigning of time for proſecution of the ſame) is long ſince paſſed away without doing ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And beſides this ſlipping the <hi>Terminus Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> that is, the Term limited and appointed by the Judge, from whom the Appeal is. Moreover, the <hi>primum fatale juris,</hi> for proſecuting and ending of Appeals, is likewiſe lapſed; and no impediment can be warrantably alledged in favour, and on behalf of the Appellants, ſo as to enjoy benefit of reſtitution into, and being allowed their <hi>ſecundum fatale,</hi> or ſecond year for proſecuting their former Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal.</p>
            <p>No impediment, I ſay, can warrantably be alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by theſe Appellants, to capacitate them for this reſtitution; for although the matter, and pretended Grievance complained of againſt the Biſhop (at the hearing thereof) before the moſt Honourable Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, was refer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to two Honourable Members of the ſame; and in the iſſue thereof, from thoſe Honon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Referrees ſomething like the nature of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>promiſe was made between both parties (which might ſeem ſufficient to ſtop the running on of theſe <hi>Fatalia Juris</hi>) namely, in reſpect of the Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, their engaging to perform what belonged to
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:53134:65"/>them to do; and had been required from them by the Biſhop, as, to give account of the Money recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for the Churches uſe, and making good the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of the Body of the Cathedral, and other particular matters before mentioned, and in reſpect of the Biſhop his promiſing to withdraw his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings againſt them thereupon: Although, I ſay, this ſeeming compromiſe might appear as a ſufficient ground of granting admiſſion to the <hi>ſecundum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tale,</hi> ſuppoſing the firſt to be irrecoverably paſt: Nevertheleſs it is not at all ſufficient thereto; the reaſon is, becauſe conditions were not performed on which this reſpite, and ſeeming compromiſe was grounded, and this non-performance of conditions was on the Appellants own part. The Biſhop per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed more than his part in deſiſting hitherto from any further proceeding againſt them: And they not performing the conditions required on their parts, not then, nor ſince, nor to this very day (which yet they ought to have done forthwith) the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit therefore of the other <hi>fatale</hi> is not allowable to them; but being uncapable of any reſtitution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, they are really in the <hi>lapſe,</hi> and the ſaid Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, may be pronounced <hi>pro deſertâ,</hi> and no advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage on the Appellants part to be expected there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from: And if the Biſhop ſhould thus pronounce, and reſume into his cognizance the whole proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again, as there would be both Law and Right enough to juſtifie his ſo doing; ſo there would be a want of both theſe, and of every thing elſe, that might be needful to make up a ſafe and warrantable defence for the Complainants. It is a noted and approved Maxim in poenal proceedings, <hi>That Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of all crimes are leaſt capable of favour or lenity.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:53134:65"/>
            <p>Upon the whole view, it ſufficiently appears how little of truth or reaſon this exception againſt the manner of proceedings, has to bear its ſelf up with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. Look we upon the crimes cenſured, they were deeply ſcandalous and provoking. Look we upon the cenſure inflicted,
'twas comparatively to the crime, and a greater cenſure that might have been inflicted, moderate and eaſie. Look we to the manner of proceeding, it was proper, and without the omiſſion of any one requiſite or formality that of right ought to be uſed therein. Look we to the Order obſerved, It was not looſe and confuſed, but grave and regular. Look we upon the whole cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance it ſelf, This was not haſty and precipitous, but prudentially guided, and proceeding with good maturity and deliberation; convenient intervals of time dividing ſeaſonably every Court throughout the whole Tranſaction, and preventing any thing of ſurprize that might be ſuſpected therein. I pretend not much skill to theſe Affairs; yet being upon the deſign of ſearching (as well as I was able) into the whole ſtate of this matter, I have viewed and reviewed the whole <hi>ſeries</hi> of theſe proceedings, with the ſeveral Acts of Court, Decrees, and other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters incident thereunto: And according to the beſt of what I am able to judge, I cannot find in the ſame, where to faſten any Error, no not in the very niceties and punctualities of practice, much leſs in any material point, and eſſential matter thereof.</p>
            <p>And now after all, If Offenders complaints againſt the forms and preſcriptions of Courts, may paſs for juſt Exceptions, and fair Vindications of themſelves, we ſhall have many crimes, but few criminals; many that will be bold to offend, but few that will ever
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:53134:66"/>acknowledge their being legally convicted for their Offences: 'Tis high time for perſons inveſted with judiciary power, to look about them, and provide ſome new wayes of ſecuring the Authority of their judicial proceedings, if every bold attempt to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion the legality of them, may paſs for a juſtifiable Plea of not obeying them, or imprint a nullity up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. When ſuch Offenders, ſo juſtly and mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cenſured, ſhall dare openly, to tell my Lord, the Kings Deputy, and my Lords of His Majeſties Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil (as theſe men did) That a Biſhop, the Kings principal <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Judge,</hi> within his own Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, has put the Inhabitants of a City into very much diſorder <hi>by ſuch arbitrary, and unheard of manner of proceedings</hi> (when all the diſorder pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from themſelves, and no other, but legal proceedings have been uſed herein) this comes very near the ſaying, That they are wronged in ſpight of any thing that can be ſaid againſt it; and that if they to whom they make their Application, will not believe and redreſs them (as they would have it themſelves) they will venture to ſpeak as hardly of them too: They will commit faults, and then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, and be pettiſh and froward, if they be not ſtroak't and ſoothed up in their complaints. He that charges any in ſubordinate power, with <hi>arbitrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of proceedings, and may eſcape ſo, will at the next turn charge as bad upon thoſe that are in ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Authority, if he have but any matter of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern then at ſtake, and may think to be ſecure when he does ſo.</p>
            <p>This begins in the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, but will it end there? it's to be feared, it will not. Succeſs, impunity and hopes of being countenanced therein,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:53134:66"/>will embolden ſuch men to go further, even to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the like upon all judiciary proceedings in Civil Courts, where their perſons or intereſts are concerned, and where they may be heard with free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and ſafety of popular approbation; it might paſs, for a pretty ſmooth contrivance, for a Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal to avoid the force of a judiciary ſentence, by firſt traducing it, and to get free from the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſubmitting to what is decreed, by affirming confidently, and ſtanding to it, <hi>That the proceedings were illegal, and therefore not to be obeyed.</hi> If this would ſerve the turn, who would be ſuch a Fool, as ever to be guilty? or ſo careleſs of his own eaſe, as ever to undergo any puniſhment? But 'tis worth the wonder of a ſober man, to think that any one ſhould ſhew himſelf (and believe others ought to think him) ſerious herein. But in truth, what has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded, ſo much out-does this, that all our wonder may be well ſpent upon it. That men called to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer in Law, ſhould queſtion the known and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved courſe and proceedings thereof, carries ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing extraordinary with it; but here is much more, That they themſelves ſhould againſt Law ſo plainly fore-judge their own cauſe, and their own perſons, as to exempt, both, from what, and to confine them to what Juriſdiction, they themſelves beſt liked of.</p>
            <p>The Enquiry into the abſurdity, unreaſonableneſs and ill conſequences of which, and the evincing the Right of Epiſcopal Juriſdiction in the caſe in hand, againſt any ſuch illegal pretenſions and attempts: The putting a new mound about that ancient, and eſtabliſhed Juriſdiction, which every pragmatical, pettiſh, and conceited Noveliſt is now ſeeking either
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:53134:67"/>by detraction in his ſpeech, or other crafty Machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations in his practice, firſt to retrench a little, and by and by utterly to aboliſh; has hitherto employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Thoughts, and my Pen. In proſecution of which deſign (it is now no more than time, I ſhould tell the Reader ſo much) I have promiſcuouſly made uſe of Engliſh Statutes, ſince the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, and ſome memorable paſſages of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction done in <hi>England,</hi> as well, as what peculiarly relates to this Kingdom. And I cannot altogether deny, but that I have done this for the Nonce; for (ſetting aſide ſome particular Statutes, relating to the peculiar ſtate and condition of this Kingdom) As to Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, we here conform in the practice and exerciſe of it, and in the Rules and Laws it is exerciſed by, to the ſame, that are uſed in <hi>England.</hi> If I be blamed for this, I protect my ſelf with what a Learned perſon has collected from Sir <hi>John Davys</hi> Reports, in Caſe <hi>de commendam—Ex quibus conſtat Hibernos ſeſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comodare, non ad jura Anglicana tantum, ſed ad Leges Caeſareas etiam, &amp; jus Canonicum quatenus ea inter Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Anglicanas admittuntur.</hi> Dr. <hi>Duck,</hi> de Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Juris Civilis. in Regno Hiberniae, <hi>Sect</hi> 8. To whom I may add the Authority of that greatly Learned Prelate, Primate <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher;</hi> for to this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the ſaid Book, as he did to all the reſt, he gave his particular Atteſtation under his own hand. I mentioned at firſt two ends, which I propoſed to my ſelf in this undertaking; theſe I have had all along in my eye: The one was, that by the beſt reaſon I had, and was able to improve, and by the beſt authority I could find and was able to pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>duce, I might juſtifie the Right (and in the preſent caſe the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:53134:67"/>right proceedings) of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, and ſo give my ſelf a true ſatisfaction therein: The other end is, to give a ſatisfaction to others alſo; for what concerns my ſelf, I have ſufficiently attained it; for what concerns others, I have at leaſt endeavoured to do ſomething in Order thereto.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:53134:68"/>
            <head>Some miſtakings or omiſſions in Pointing, the intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Reader may eaſily obſerve and correct; And that he may pleaſe to do the like in ſuch Lapſes, as are either Literal, or tend to vitiate the Senſe, they are here in one view ſet down before him.</head>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 17, line 7, for Juriſdictions, read Juriſdiction: <hi>ibid.</hi> line 8, for cognizances, read cognizance: page 24, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, line 2, for <hi>Statutis</hi> read <hi>Statute:</hi> page 25, line 29, for in, read is: <hi>ibid.</hi> line 32, for <hi>paenes</hi> read <hi>penes: ibid.</hi> line 34, for <hi>ſine,</hi> read <hi>five:</hi> page 26, line 4, for <hi>vir,</hi> read <hi>viz. ibid.</hi> line 8, for <hi>tali,</hi> read <hi>rati: ibid.</hi> line 27, for <hi>ſanctis,</hi> read <hi>ſanctio:</hi> page 29, margent, Sect. 2, for amplytude, read amplitude: page 30, margent, line 32, for without, read without: page 32, line 16, inſtead of propper cauſe, read a proper cauſe: page 34, line 13, for <hi>Clerii,</hi> read <hi>Cleri:</hi> page 41, line 20, for <hi>Regie,</hi> read <hi>Regiae: ibid.</hi> line 32, for <hi>Prerogativa,</hi> read <hi>Praero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gativa:</hi> page 44, line 34, for King, read King: page 56, line 26, for beee, read been: page 68, line 15, for cognizan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, read cognizance: page 73, line 12, for powers, read power: page 82, line 4, for has, read had: page 103, line 26, for <hi>diverſi,</hi> read <hi>diverſae.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:53134:68"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
